<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Lords day vindicated, or, The first day of the week the Christian Sabbath in answer to Mr. Bampfields plea for the seventh day, in his Enquiry whether Jesus be Jehovah, and gave the moral law? And whether the fourth command be repealed or altered? / by G.T., a well-wisher to truth and concord.</title>
            <author>Trosse, George, 1631-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 250 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3378</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13073198</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13073198</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97175</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63259)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97175)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 401:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Lords day vindicated, or, The first day of the week the Christian Sabbath in answer to Mr. Bampfields plea for the seventh day, in his Enquiry whether Jesus be Jehovah, and gave the moral law? And whether the fourth command be repealed or altered? / by G.T., a well-wisher to truth and concord.</title>
                  <author>Trosse, George, 1631-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 134, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Clement ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to George Trosse. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: [2] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bampfield, Thomas, 1623?-1693. --  Enquiry whether the Lord Jesus Christ made the world.</term>
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97175:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97175:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lords day Vinaicated:</hi> OR The <hi>Firſt day</hi> of the WEEK THE Chriſtian Sabbath. In Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Bampfields</hi> Plea for the <hi>Seventh day,</hi> in his <hi>Enquiry, Whether Jeſus Chriſt be Jehovah, and gave the Moral Law? And whether the Fourth Command be Repealed or Altered?</hi> BY <hi>G. T.</hi> a Well-wiſher to Truth and Concord.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 18.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own Cauſe ſeemeth juſt, but his Neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Clement,</hi> at the <hi>White Swan</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's Church-yard,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97175:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97175:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THo' there be many Books already written on this Subject, the following Preface will juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the Seaſonableneſs of this Modeſt and Judicious Reply to Mr. <hi>B.</hi> eſpecially among ſerious Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in the <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> But it cannot be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit upon other Conſiderations, that ſuch a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe be now Publiſh'd, when the Doctrinal Truth, in the Controverſie of a Weekly Sabbath, is oppoſed by ſo many, and the Practical Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it neglected by ſo many more.</p>
            <p>It has been generally obſerved, that the Power of Godlineſs hath Flouriſhed or Abated in every Age, and in every part of Chriſtendom; as the ſtrict and conſciencious Obſervation of a Weekly-Day of Holy Reſt did obtain, or not: And par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in our own Country, no outward Means can be aſſigned, that hath more availed to help the Preſervation of Pure, Reformed, Chriſtianity among us.</p>
            <p>On which account, it concerns all Chriſtians to enquire what is our Warrant for the Obſervation of <hi>One</hi> day in <hi>Seven?</hi> and likewiſe whether the <hi>Seventh,</hi> or the <hi>Firſt</hi> day of the Week, (which
<pb facs="tcp:97175:3"/>according to a true Account, may alſo be called the Seventh) ought to be obſerved as <hi>the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is ſaid on this Argument in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reply to Mr. <hi>B.</hi> diſcovers ſo much the Candor and Moderation of the Author, as will recommend it to every Impartial Reader. His Diſtance from <hi>London,</hi> and nothing elſe occaſions, or needs this Epiſtle; as will doubtleſs be thought, even by ſuch as have ſome different Conceptions from him, in ſome leſſer Matters of this Controverſie.</p>
            <p>That it may advance the Honour of Chriſt, and help to ſatisfy the Minds of ſome Wavering, and leſs Eſtabliſhed Chriſtians, and promote the real Intereſt of Practical Godlineſs; (upon which the Doctrin of the Weekly Sabbath will have a great Influence,) as it will anſwer the Authors Deſign, ſo our Deſires and Prayers,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Howe. John Shower.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:97175:3"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>IT may afford cauſe of Wonder to conſidering and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſons what ſhould be the Inducements of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the Enquiry whether <hi>the Lord Jeſus</hi> &amp;c. to Print and divulge it at ſuch a time, and under ſuch circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, as we are brought into: And though he hath propoſed no Preface to his Book, to plead for it's Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; yet I think there has ſcarce been a Piece ſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, theſe many Years, that more required and needed it. For,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> He well knows that the whole Chriſtian World is engaged againſt him herein, and that they have Sciptural grounds, and the practice of the moſt ancient Churches, the Doctrin and Teſtimonies of the muſt Orthodox and Learned Fathers, derived immediately from the Apoſtles, with an uninterrupted Succeſſion through ſeveral Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies; and their own Education, Cuſtom and Practice, received down from many Generations, with their own bleſſed Experiences of the Light of Gods countenance; the operations of his Spirit, the activity and growth of their own Graces on that bleſſed Day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for their conſecrating of the firſt day of the Week to Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and their Religious and Devout appropriating it to, and imploying it in thoſe Duties, which immediately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern the Glory of God, and the Spiritual and Eternal Weal of their own Souls: Which things are not eaſily overcome and laid aſide; with as great and Rooted Prejudices againſt his opinion, of <hi>the Seventh-day-Sabbath;</hi> as that 'tis <hi>Judaical, Fanciful,</hi> and <hi>Singular,</hi> ſuch at leaſt as has had but very few Favourers and Abetters either in the <hi>ancient Churches,</hi> (and theſe branded for Hereſie) or elſe in the <hi>modern,</hi> ſome three or four
<pb facs="tcp:97175:4"/>ſtarting up of late years among our ſelves, daring by Writing and Printing to endeavour the Introduction of this Novelty into the belief and practice of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church. All which, and other Prejudices againſt this Opinion cannot ſlightly be eradicated out of the minds of Men; and therefore he could hardly imagin any great ſucceſs to this undertaking, unleſs he could have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced undeniable demonſtrations to our Reaſon, or irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable Teſtimonies of Scripture to our Faith: Which I hope we ſhall ſee he has been far enough from.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> He ſhould alſo have conſidered, and concluded, that theſe Arguments which have been produced hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by thoſe of his perſwaſion, are not likely now to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and convert the whole Chriſtian World to his thoughts and practice: Seeing they have been ſo often, and by ſo many worthy, Learned, Orthodox, and Pious Divines, anſwered, and in the judgment of Wiſe and gracious Perſons, fully confuted, and ſatisfactorily baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled, to the deeper Rooting and more firm Eſtabliſhment of the Churches of Chriſt in their conſtant Obſervance of <hi>the Lords day.</hi> Wherefore, if he would have ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected any thing by this attempt, he ſhould have offered ſome new Inventions of his own, that have never yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countered with any oppoſition: But in all his Book (to the beſt of my Remembrance) I have not met with any one place of Scripture, nor argument drawn therefrom, nor Improvement thereof, for his own Sentiments: Nor yet any Text of Gods word, or Topick againſt ours, no, nor any one ſolution of our Authoritative or Rational proofs, for the confirmation of our Contrary Belief and Practice to his, which has not been already produced by others, and as largely and ſtrenuously managed as by himſelf; and that too in the ſame manner. 'Tis no great Prudence in a Combatant to make uſe of the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:97175:4"/>Weapons, Modes, and Arts, againſt his Antagoniſts which have been frequently Baffled, Defeated, Broken and retorted into his own Bowels. Wherefore, 'tis ſtrange to me, if any Victory over any conſiderate ſtudious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, could be hoped for by ſuch a caſting of the Gantlet.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> But ſuppoſe he could have expected to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelited ſome to his Opinion (as who has not, though the Doctrin be never ſo abſurd, Heterodox and Impious,) yet ſure it could not be thought a ſufficient means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail upon all the Churches; no, nor upon the univerſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>the National Church,</hi> of that Collection of ſo many millions of counterminded Chriſtians and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, whereof he is. He could not certainly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume, that all the Authority of theſe Nations, both Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, would follow his Dictates, or receive new Light from his Torch, and acknowledg themſelves to have been in groſs Error, and in a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Practice ever ſince, and always before the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, ſince they Profeſſed Faith in the Lord Chriſt: And that they ſhould alter all their Acts and Statutes, all their Canons and Articles, in this particular. And herein acknowledg him to be the infallible Apoſtle, or at leaſt the only happy Doctor, of this great part of the Chriſtian World, no nor of the greateſt, or any conſiderable part thereof; but only of a few, here and there of unſetled Scruplous, Superſtitious minds. No perſon could have a Rational and probable Proſpect of a greater Return from ſuch an Adventure, or Crop from ſuch a ſowing: And ſo wiſely have judged, that all his expectations would never quit his coſt, nor be worth his Risk. Eſpecially conſidering that,</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> He ſhould deeply have weighed the ſad and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Conſequences and ſcandalous Effects that his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in Print has a direct tendency to produce. (Though I truſt ſuch a tendency will be obſtructed, and
<pb facs="tcp:97175:5"/>fruſtrated, by the good Spirit of God, and by the Wiſe and ſetled Principles of our people.) The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Tendencies are ſuch as theſe,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> An encouragement to the Profaners and deniers of the <hi>Lords-Day</hi> in their Principles and Practices. They who have no Inclination to ſeparate any Day as <hi>Holy,</hi> to the Holy God, in a performance of Holy Duties, will take advantages from hence, to decry the ſtrict obſervance of the Lords-day, and to fortifie themſelves in their Idleneſs, Recreations, Worldlineſs, and ſinfulneſs thereon; and withall ſlight and deride the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath,</hi> as Judaical, Fanatical, and Singular, and ſo being taken off from the <hi>Firſt-day-Sabbath,</hi> they will acknowledg <hi>none;</hi> but give <hi>that,</hi> and all the following days of the Week to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, and to their Luſts; to Earth and to Hell: And we have heard that this Book has already produced this fearful effect in our City.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> An Offence and Stumbling-Block to ſincere and affectionate Saints; who have their Hearts eſtabliſhed in Grace, and their Heads in the grand Fundamentals of Faith and Practice; but are not acquainted with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations about ſuch remote things as theſe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having very tender Conſciences and dreading to offend God, and to approach unto any moral evil, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch a piece as this, from ſuch an Author, (ſo known to ſome of them) will be apt to be ſtartled, and exceſſively troubled with Fear, leſt they have hitherto lived in Sin, and provoked God all their days, by a Holy reſting upon <hi>the Lords day,</hi> and Working upon Saturday; and ſo all their Services of God upon the one, in the works of their <hi>General,</hi> and the ſervices of themſelves, their Families, and the humane Society (of which they are Members) upon the other, in the works of their <hi>particular Callings;</hi> have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations,
<pb facs="tcp:97175:5"/>and evils to be Repented of, (for we know what Aggravations ſcrupulous Conſciences, and a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Devil, are apt to make of ſmalleſt things) and to live in perpetual fears and doubts, in their continuance in attendance upon Gods Ordinances on thoſe days, whereon they are only to be had (in the moſt ſolemn manner, and all of them at leaſt) in the profeſſing Church of God: And ſo they will be deprived of much of that Spiritual Comfort, and ſaving profit thereby, which they formely received in, and by them: And ſtill would, had not ſuch an unhappy Scandal been laid in their way: Which is no ſmall Offence and Sin againſt Chriſt. And this alſo we know to be another product thereof, ſuch Chriſtians not daring to neglect the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance and Ordinances of <hi>the Lords-day</hi> becauſe of their former Perſwaſion, Practice, and Experience, and yet doing it with doubts and fears, leſt they ſhould Sin thereby, becauſe of this Piece.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> A perverting and withdrawing of the more ſimple and unſtable into this Opinion, which we doubt not to aſſert, and queſtion not to evidence, to be ill grounded and falſe; and ſo will prove a ſcandal indeed, even to lead into and to build up in Sin, and an unwarrantable Practice: And thus to Offend weak ones in Chriſt is a very great Evil, <hi>1 Cor. 8.11, 12.</hi> But ſuppoſe the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors notion be Orthodox, and the contrary Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox; yet another pernicious Tendencie of it is,</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> By a Proſelyting of ſome Perſons, or ſome Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, ſo many as may make Aſſemblies and Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he will be the Author of a needleſs Schiſm and Separation, and of inevitable Feuds, Rancors and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Reproaches and Condemnations: The Obſervers of the Lords day will decry and exclaim againſt the others, as <hi>Jews,</hi> and proud <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> and the keepers of the Seventh day will cenſure and condemn the other, as
<pb facs="tcp:97175:6"/>willful breakers of Gods expreſs Command, and profane compliers with the will and Traditions of Men. And he that has not the Gift of Propheſie, may eaſily foretel what ſinful and diſmall fruits will grow upon ſuch a Root of Bitterneſs. Men ſhould be cautious how they diſturb the peace of the Church, and rent our Saviours ſeamleſs Garment.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> He ſhould ſeriouſly have pondered the Days and Times we are faln into; the ſad and deplorable Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church of God among us, and the dangerous and fearful Prejudices, Rancours, and Enmities begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and fomented thereby; with the uncharitable and inexcuſable Effects they have produced already in Tongue, Pen and Hand, as the general Diviſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Conformiſts</hi> and <hi>Non-Conformiſts:</hi> and the divers Opinions, Parties, and Separated Societies of the Latter. (Though bleſſed be God, the moſt conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and Orthodox of them, the <hi>Independents</hi> and <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians,</hi> have coaleſced in their Subſcriptions to Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Agreement) and how unſeaſonable and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient 'tis therefore to broach <hi>new Opinions</hi> among them, and to increaſe their Diviſions and Animoſities; and ſo alſo give an Advantange to their obſervers to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their prejudices, and augment their Accuſations againſt them, and their Inſultings over them, as fickle, inconſtant, and heady, not knowing where to fix, nor what to hold and Practiſe, now that they have forſaken an univerſal and uninterrupted Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity unto them. Such a ſtout <hi>Non-Conformiſt</hi> to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ought to have uſed all caution, not to have given the leaſt occaſion of weakning or vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying his own Party.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> Lastly, All theſe things laid together in the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of a ſound Judgment, would have informed him, that no ſuch thing as he hath hereby attempted, ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:97175:6"/>have been undertaken, unleſs it had been about the moſt weighty and neceſſary Truths of our Religion; ſuch as do neceſſarily concern the Glory of God and the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Souls, or very near bordering thereupon. Which I hope he does not beleive the Controverſie to be; ſeeing 'tis not not about the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of Duty or the very heart of a Command, but only about the leaſt <hi>Circumſtance</hi> (if I may ſo term it) of it. Not about what Proportion of <hi>time</hi> God ſhall have Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to his ſervice; For that is agreed to be the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth;</hi> But only what <hi>day,</hi> of two of them muſt be <hi>that day</hi> of the Week? And therefore he that obſerves <hi>the Firſt-day,</hi> gives and devotes to God the <hi>Seventh part</hi> of his time, as well and as much as he that does the <hi>Seventh-day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore though the Authors Integrity and Intent may not be queſtioned, yet certainly his <hi>Prudence</hi> in this Work, and the Work under ſuch Circumſtances, are no way plauſible: And he ſhould have applied that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 14.21, 22.</hi> to have deter'd him there-from.</p>
            <p>Wherefore ſeeing this Piece is ſo dangerous, and may do, and already has done, ſo much hurt, its very <hi>Expedient,</hi> if not morally <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> to endeavour a prevention of its evil Conſequences; and there eſpecially where the Author is reſident, and it may moſt infect; and it may well be deemed a Duty of ſome one of the Dreſſers of that part of the Vineyard of the Lord Chriſt, where this Weed or Thorn is ſprung up, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour it's eradication, before it ſpreads any farther, or wounds any deeper.</p>
            <p>That Province therefore which I (moſt unable for, and Naturally altogether averſe from, Polemical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes) ſhall undertake, and with the beſt skill and faithfulneſs, that God ſhall afford, perform, ſhall only
<pb facs="tcp:97175:7"/>be, with all poſſible Brevity and Perſpicuity, to weaken all the Arguments, the Author manages for his Notion; and to confirm and Ratifie all theſe which he endeavours to weaken, and evacuate, for the ancient, general, Scriptural Doctrin of <hi>the Lords-day-Sabbath,</hi> or Sacred Reſt; and herein to follow his own method; Giving ſome tranſient Glances upon things that may occur, ſome what Excentrical or Alien from the Great deſign of this Book: Which I ſhall ſtudy to do with all Candor, and due Deference to the Gentility, Gravity, and (I hope) real Piety, of the Author.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:97175:7"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. I.</hi> SOme general Obſervations premiſed, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the World were made by Chriſt, <hi>as Jeſus Chriſt God-man? page 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. II.</hi> Of Chriſt's being <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and in what ſenſe the Law was given by him? <hi>p. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. III.</hi> Whether after the Creation the Lord reſted on the Seventh-day, and ſo Sanctified and Inſtituted it, and did himſelf obſerve it; as that even <hi>Adam</hi> in a State of Innocence was bound by it, and all Mankind, without diſtinction, before the Fall? <hi>p. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. IV.</hi> Whether the <hi>Ten Commandments</hi> were given by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles? p. 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. V.</hi> Whether Chriſt in the Fleſh did confirm all the <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> and every tittle of the <hi>Fourth?</hi> And whether Chriſt and his Apoſtles did enjoyn, or did not rather ſpeak againſt the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath? p. 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. VI.</hi> Of the Word <hi>Seventh</hi> in the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment; the Sabbath not recommended by Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:97175:8"/>to his Diſciples. Of <hi>Commenius</hi>'s deſire of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>&amp;c. p. 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. VII.</hi> Of the <hi>Ceremonial Law,</hi> and what is <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Poſitive;</hi> what is truly <hi>Moral,</hi> that the Saturday <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> is not; more may be pleaded for <hi>Circumciſion. p. 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. VIII.</hi> Whether Chriſt <hi>in his own Perſon</hi> Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the <hi>Seventh-Week-day-Sabbath</hi> and no other, and what may be gathered from it? The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> equally hold for all the Jewiſh <hi>Ceremonies.</hi> Of the <hi>Pre-Antiquity</hi> of that Day and the falſity of that Argument. <hi>p. 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. IX.</hi> Whether Chriſt <hi>Reſted</hi> on the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath,</hi> while he lay in the <hi>Grave?</hi> And what may be Argued from it? <hi>p. 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. X.</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon what day of the <hi>Week,</hi> Chriſt aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Heaven, whether the <hi>Seventh-day</hi> or <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turday? p. 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. XI.</hi> Whether after the Reſurrection and Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt, the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Firſt Chriſtians?</hi> How long the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> met the <hi>Jews</hi> in their Synagogues on the <hi>Seventh-day,</hi> and for what Reaſon? <hi>p. 51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. XII.</hi> The Argument from <hi>Chriſt's Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> for the <hi>Firſt-day</hi> of the Week to be the <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath</hi> Vindicated. Circumciſion not more aboliſht than the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath: That</hi> aboliſht, the <hi>Firſt</hi> ſucceeds on the Account of <hi>Our Lord's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97175:8"/>ſince that Time, with equal or ſtronger Reaſon than the former continued till he Roſe from the dead. <hi>p. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. XIII.</hi> Other Arguments for the <hi>Firſt-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> Vindicated from the Objections of Mr. <hi>B.</hi> Of a Sabbath-days Journey. <hi>After three Days,</hi> may be underſtood <hi>on the third Day</hi> he roſe again. <hi>John 8.56. Pſalm 118.22. Pſalm 2.7. Acts 20.7.</hi> cleared and Vindicated. Of the beginning of the Chriſtian Sabbath. <hi>p. 61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. XIV.</hi> More Texts cleared, <hi>Rev. 1.9, 10.</hi> of being <hi>in the Spirit on the Lords-day, Math. 12.8. Mark 2.27. Jeſus Chriſt Lord of the Sabbath.</hi> Of the Lord Supper. Chriſts Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on commemorated on the <hi>Firſt-day</hi> of the Week, by Inſtitution. <hi>p. 79</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. XV. Gal. 4.9, 10.</hi> Explained. What days ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from binding Chriſtians. <hi>Col. 2.16.</hi> What <hi>Sabbaths</hi> meant as <hi>Shadows,</hi> to vaniſh when Chriſt came. <hi>Math. 24.20,</hi> no Argument for the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth-day-Sabbath. p. 92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. XVI.</hi> Of the <hi>Morality</hi> of the <hi>Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand:</hi> The difference between <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive:</hi> Between Naturally or Abſolutely <hi>Moral,</hi> and <hi>poſitively</hi> or ſecondarily <hi>Moral:</hi> What the <hi>Fourth Commandment</hi> requires as <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Perpetual. p. 101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. XVII.</hi> When to <hi>begin</hi> the Chriſtian Sabbath, and of the fit Time for <hi>Publick Worſhip</hi> on that day. <hi>p. 116</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:97175:9"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. XVIII.</hi> The Argument of <hi>Tradition</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. <hi>p. 118</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. XIX.</hi> How far the Decalogue is in Force, as to us <hi>Gentiles. p. 125</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. XX.</hi> The Tradition of the Lords-day's Reſt, or Firſt-day of the Week from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time to the end of the <hi>Fourth Century.</hi> Of Eaſter and its Obſervation. The change from the Seventh to the Firſt-day not introduced by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome. p. 127</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sect. XXI.</hi> The Concluſion of the whole, with a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary of what hath been Proved for the Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Firſt-day</hi> of the Week, as the <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath. p. 130</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97175:9"/>
            <head>A REPLY TO Mr. <hi>Bampfield</hi>'s PLEA FOR THE Seventh-day-Sabbath.</head>
            <p>THE very <hi>Title</hi> of the Book is juſtly lyable to Exception, as that which does not fairly ſtate the <hi>Queſtion;</hi> the ſecond Enquiry being <hi>[whether the fourth Command be repealed or altered]</hi> for he very well knows, that theſe againſt whom he Diſputes, even thoſe who acknowledge the Morality of a Sabbath-day, do neither pretend to the Repealing of the Command, nor yet to the Alteration of it as ſuch; for they ſtrenuouſly aſſert the Ratification of the preceptive part of it, though they allow a practical Mutation of a ſingle Clauſe therein; which was at its firſt Injunction, added as a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97175:10"/>Motive for the obſervance of the Seventh Weekly-day: And therefore he ſhould rather have ſtated the Enquiry after ſuch a manner as this, <hi>Whether every Clauſe in the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment be Moral,</hi> or whether every Clauſe of it, be abſolutely <hi>Immutable,</hi> or ſo impoſed from the beginning, as to be ſo. 'Tis not Ingenuous nor Candid, ſo to propoſe the Controverſie, as though the Diſſenters from him, were either Repealers, or Alterers of the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. Moreover, the Annexion of this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the former, and the Subſervience of the former to this, (For 'tis very evident, that that weighty fundamental Enquiry, is made to ſerve this Hypotheſis, by his Connexion thereof, <hi>Page</hi> 5. thereto) as though the Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability of every Tittle to this Command, was founded upon the Deity of our Lord Chriſt, his creating the World, and giving the Moral Law; and the Denial of the one, were vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and conſequentially the Denial of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and ſo thoſe that are for the obſervance of the Lords day, (for ſo I take leave now to call it) are really and conſequentially <hi>Ebionites,</hi> and <hi>Socinians;</hi> and ſo worſe then <hi>Arians:</hi> Which is either to tax them all as groſs <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> or at leaſt ignorant and inconſiderate Perſons, that do either not know, or not heed the direful and damning Conſequences of their own Doctrin. But I hope we ſhall ſee, that either the <hi>firſt Query</hi> is but little concerned in the <hi>ſecond;</hi> or that thoſe who are contrary to his Sentiments in <hi>this,</hi> are throughly Orthodox in <hi>that.</hi> To which, as 'tis propoſed, with a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97175:10"/>good and plain diſtinction, may be replyed both negatively and poſitively; that <hi>the Lord Jeſus Chriſt made the World,</hi> is <hi>Jehovah,</hi> &amp;c. and that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt was <hi>not</hi> Jehovah, made <hi>not</hi> the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that altogether according to the Scriptures; and ſo the very ſtreſs of his Argument enervated, and this Foundation of this Structure, ſuppoſed to be eternal and immutable, proved to be Sandy, Temporary and Human; which we ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to evince in its proper place.</p>
            <p>I ſhall purpoſely wave any Reflections upon his Four firſt Pages, (though Remarks might be made thereon) becauſe I ſuppoſe if there be any thing which he judges of moment in this Caſe, they are to be found in the following Diſcourſe; to which they are but an <hi>Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction:</hi> Only ſhall hint my Belief of his not having ſeen Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> of <hi>Colcheſter</hi>'s Book againſt <hi>Tillam;</hi> ſeeing he does not mention him, <hi>Page</hi> 4. among the Writers he there quotes for the Firſt-day-Sabbath. A moſt worthy Author who has ſo fully and convincingly confuted his Adverſary, that I am prone to believe, had Mr. <hi>B.</hi> peruſed, and duly ſtudyed him, he would not have troubled the World or the Church, with his Book; and were that Book commonly to be gotten, or a new Edition thereof to be Printed, there could need no other Reply to this; much leſs ſhould I have put Pen to Paper, being ſo far Inferiour to him: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, a Pygmy upon a Gyants Back, may ſee a little farther with his own Eyes.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:97175:11"/>
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>HE ſtates the <hi>firſt Queſtion,</hi> Page 5. <hi>Whether the World were made by Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> and that too, as affording help to his Sabbata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Notion; but rightly apprehended, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces nothing at all thereto: For Evidence whereof, we ſay that it may be orthodoxly denyed and aſſerted, that Jeſus Chriſt did not make the World, for the World was 4000 Years before ever Jeſus Chriſt was: For theſe two Names <hi>J. C.</hi> do neceſſarily imply, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude his <hi>Human Nature</hi> with his <hi>Divine:</hi> For his Divine Nature formally and abſtractly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, cannot be <hi>Christ,</hi> that is, not <hi>Annoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> not fitted nor qualifyed by any other, for any Offices, Imployments or Deſigns: It belongs to his <hi>Human Nature</hi> alone. Neither could his <hi>God-head</hi> ſo conſidered, be our <hi>Jeſus;</hi> for the God-head can neither obey the Law, nor bear the Curſe; both which were to be done by our Jeſus: And theſe appertain only to his Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, though his Divinity gives the Merit of our Salvation to his active and paſſive Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; ſo that <hi>actually</hi> and <hi>formally, Jeſus Christ</hi> could not be till his Incarnation: Though his Merits extended to all the Generations of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers from <hi>Adam,</hi> according to that, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8. For though an actual Exiſtence be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in <hi>Phyſical Cauſes,</hi> before they can be Cauſes and produce their Effects, yet 'tis not ſo in <hi>Moral;</hi> but their Effects may be before
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97175:11"/>the actual Exiſtence of the Cauſe; as Perſons may be redeemed and let looſe from Priſon, upon the foreſight of a Ranſom, or a Payment to be made, Months or Years after. And ſo God out of an Infallible Foreſight of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours paying the Debts, and laying down the Ranſom of the Elect in the fulneſs of time, and giving to himſelf a full meritorious Price, (<hi>even the Blood of God,</hi> Act. 20.28.) for all their ſpiritual and eternal Mercies, delivered, bleſſed and ſaved all the Saints and Believers, before our Lords being <hi>actually</hi> a meritorious Saviour, with an Eye and Regard thereto; and ſo he was not actually <hi>Jeſus,</hi> neither could he be, till he had <hi>actually</hi> done and ſuffered all theſe things for which they were Redeemed and Saved: And therefore here, as Jeſus Chriſt could not make the World, though as God, we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge he did.</p>
               <p>In the Old Teſtament Chriſt is Propheſied of, as to come, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.25, 26. How could he then create the World? And when he is born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> he is then pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Angel to be <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Luk. 2.11. as being then the Accompliſhment of <hi>Daniel</hi>'s and other ſuch Propheſies, that went before of his future Meſſiaſ-ſhip. And upon his <hi>Incarnation,</hi> he had the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> given him by God, <hi>Math.</hi> 1.21. How then could he as <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> create the World? I deſire that this might be duly conſidered by the Reader, becauſe 'tis of great weight to overthrow the chief Prop of his Sabbatarian Structure; and to prove them to be but of ill temper'd Mortar: For in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97175:12"/>this and the two following Queries, he builds upon a fallacious Compoſition, as though what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever <hi>God</hi> is, or did, that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> muſt be, and do; and ſo he muſt create the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God did ſo. Juſt as if we ſhould ſuppoſe the <hi>Platonick</hi> Exiſtence of Souls, Thouſands of Years Solitary, without Bodies, and impute what ever thoſe Souls Did, Thought, Reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in that Condition, to thoſe Men of whom they came in time to be an eſſential part; and ſay this Man ſo thought, and ſo reſolved, this would be a very improper Speech; for the Man was not, till the Soul came to be eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conjoyned to the Body: And therefore in Propriety, 'twas the Soul, and not the Man that was the Author of theſe Cogitations and Reſolutions; for they were Thouſands of Years before the <hi>Man</hi> was. So the God-head of Jeſus Chriſt made the World, but the <hi>God-head</hi> was throughout a beginning leſs Eternity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and therefore he could not be the Creator of the World. 'Tis ſomewhat ſtrange to me, that Mr. <hi>B.</hi> did not ſee this groſs Fallacy. All Scriptures therefore which he brings to prove this Aſſertion, muſt be thus underſtood, as for Example, <hi>Col.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 12, 13, 14. with <hi>v.</hi> 16. which Scripture confutes his Suggeſtion, and confirms our Aſſertion: For ſurely he cannot ſay that the <hi>Creator, as,</hi> and <hi>when</hi> Creator, had Blood: But Chriſt as ſuch, had Blood; and therefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>not</hi> Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, but his God-head. So muſt alſo, <hi>John</hi> 1.1, 3. where the Creator is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; which we tranſlate <hi>the Word;</hi> it might as well
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97175:12"/>have been tranſlated the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> which was eternally <hi>with God, in God,</hi> and <hi>is God;</hi> and ſo muſt be the Creator. But 'tis very obſervable, that St. <hi>John</hi> doth not call him <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> till <hi>v.</hi> 17. when he had before ſpoken of his <hi>Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, v.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>Juſt ſuch another is <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. where 'tis ſaid, that <hi>God made the Worlds,</hi> (taking them for the created Worlds, viſible and inviſible; though other excellent Divines interpret them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) <hi>by his Son,</hi> even his Co-eternal and Co-eſſential Son: But it is not here ſaid, that he made them by <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> but <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Son of God, <hi>ſpake to us in the laſt days;</hi> he did it in and by his <hi>Humanity,</hi> but ſo he created not the Creatures.</p>
               <p>In the laſt Proof, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.9. 'Tis indeed expreſly ſaid, That <hi>God created all things by Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> which if meant of the old and whole Creation, muſt be meant as above; and 'tis as much as if he had ſaid, God the Father created all things by God the Son; which Son is <hi>now Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Wherefore we conclude our Reply to this <hi>Query,</hi> by aſſerting that <hi>the God-head of the Lord Christ, created the World;</hi> but that Chriſt conſiſting of that God-head, and the Humanity hypoſtatically united to it, did not ſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97175:13"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p>HE aſſerts <hi>Page</hi> 9. that Propoſition which no Chriſtian ever denyed or queſtioned; and whoever does ſo, deſerves not the Name Chriſtian, <hi>viz. That the Lord Jeſus Christ is Jehovah:</hi> Which he proves at large, home to <hi>Page</hi> 22. which in theſe days might have been very ſeaſonable and commendable too, had it not been made a progreſſive Step toward the ſupremely intended Doctrin of the neceſſary Obligation of the Seventh-day-Sabbath. But yet I muſt ſay, that our Lord Chriſts Deity, or Jehovah-ſhip, has been more fully prov'd, and more methodically, and from more To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks, and all theſe demonſtrated and confirmed from Scripture, than here it is; and that by many Orthodox Divines. We acknowledging his Theſis to be good and orthodox; we hope he will acknowledge this to be ſo likewiſe, <hi>viz. That Jehovah was not always Christ: Chriſt</hi> is, and muſt be everlaſtingly <hi>Jehovah.</hi> But Jehovah was throughout a paſt Eternity, before there was ever any other Being, and in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of time, before there was a ſinful Being: And therefore neceſſarily before Chriſt Jeſus had a Being. For Chriſt Jeſus in an orthodox Notion, and according to Scriptural Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, does pre-ſuppoſe a created, and a faln ſinful Being. And ſo this orthodox Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will but contribute very little to that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which we deem heterodox. I ſhall make
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97175:13"/>no Reflections at all upon what he has written in all theſe Papers, ſave only upon that Medium which he uſes <hi>Page</hi> 12, and 13. which is <hi>Chriſts giving the Law;</hi> (for that's his Expreſſion) where again we urge, according to our former Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, that Chriſt properly apprehended, did not give the Law before his Incarnation, not being Chriſt before it: He gave it not to Man before the Fall. When the whole abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and primary Moral Law, was implanted by God on his Mind, to know all the Duties he ought to perform towards his God, according to his Excellencies and Attributes revealed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, according to his Works and his Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions laid upon him, and all his Duties to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward all his Fellow Creatures: In his <hi>Will,</hi> by a perfect and full Complyance with, and active and exact Conformity to all theſe moral Dict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates of his Underſtanding, in all the Inferiour Affections, Appetites, Inclinations, Motions, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Organs and Members of the Body; by a ready and compleat Subjection to the holy Will, and a moſt harmonious Obedience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Which the Apoſtle calls <hi>Knowledge, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> and <hi>true Holineſs,</hi> Col. 3.10. Eph. 4.24. Neither did Chriſt Jeſus give the Law juſt upon the Fall, as I ſuppoſe the Moral Law muſt be ſuppoſed to be given to <hi>Adam;</hi> ſeeing that by the Fall, he had greatly defac'd and blotted the former clear and perfect Edition of it, in his Heart and Soul. Neither did he give it in the Third Edition, when 'twas brought and delivered by the Hand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> from the Finger and Mouth of God, to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97175:14"/>
                  <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> For all theſe were long before Jeſus Chriſt came into, and ſo was in, the World: And St. <hi>John</hi> himſelf tells us, <hi>John</hi> 1.17. <hi>The Law was given by</hi> Moſes, <hi>but Grace and Truth came by Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> So that the Law was given long before Jeſus Chriſt came, and preached, and purchaſed the Grace and Truth of the Goſpel. But all this is made uſe of by this Author to inſinuate, that even <hi>Chriſt Jeſus, in the Fleſh, was the Author of all the Ten Commands,</hi> as they are <hi>verbatim</hi> recorded in <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Books, or were written upon the Tables of Stone; and ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of that very Clauſe in the Fourth Command; which is given as a reaſon of the Sanctification of the Seventh day to be the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, home to his own Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>But this we ſhall prove in the Sequel to be a very great Miſtake: The only Proof that he brings for this, which has not been ſufficiently anſwered already, or may not be ſo, by what has been formerly ſaid and proved, is <hi>John</hi> 14.15. <hi>If ye love me keep my Commands:</hi> And ſuch other like Paſſages. Here I would feign enquire, in what Senſe he underſtands the Commands to be <hi>Chriſt's Commands:</hi> Either as he is <hi>Jehovah;</hi> and ſo before his Incarnation: If ſo, then the <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial</hi> and <hi>Judicial Commands</hi> were his as well, and as much, as the <hi>Moral;</hi> for he gave the one as well as the other. And ſo by this arguing, and from this Topick, we are bound to keep the one as well as the other: If we would evince to our own Conſciences, or others Obſervations, that we ſincerely love Chriſt. If he underſtands them to be <hi>his,</hi> after his Incarnation, as taught,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97175:14"/>commanded and confirmed by his own bleſſed Mouth and Doctrin: So we confeſs that all the <hi>Moral Law</hi> was his, and that he taught it in the diſcharge of his Prophetical Office in the Fleſh. But then we affirm, and doubt not to prove, that in all his Doctrin, Diſcourſes and Commands, there is not one word that teaches or enjoyns the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath,</hi> but much to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: Or if there be only a perfect ſilence in this particular, without any thing ſpoken or done by Chriſt contrary to it, whilſt he parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly enjoyns and preſſes all thoſe other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, which are acknowledged by all to be <hi>Moral:</hi> I ſuppoſe this very Excluſion of it, out of all his Diſcourſes, carries more weight in it, to caſhire it from being any one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> than all his former En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to prove Chriſt to be the Maker of the World, to be <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and here to be the Giver of the Law, have of moment to prove the Morality, and ſo the neceſſary obſervance of the Seventh-day. I have been here a little the more large, becauſe I find the Author, <hi>Page</hi> 24. referring unto his having proved the Law to be given by Chriſt, as to that which highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces to his grand Deſign; but being duly weighed, we ſee that 'tis of little or no uſe at all thereto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:97175:15"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p>WE have a third Interrogation propoſed, Page 22. <hi>Whether after the Creation the Lord reſted on the Seventh day:</hi> And, <hi>Whether the Seventh-day-Sabbath was ſanctified and ſo inſtituted by him, and was obſerved by him who made the World?</hi> To the firſt Clauſe whereof we have ſufficiently anſwered, That it was not the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> that created the World and reſted, but it was indeed <hi>Jehovah;</hi> and though Chriſt be <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and the Maker of all things as ſuch; yet the ſame <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> is alſo the <hi>Son of Man,</hi> and made by <hi>Jehovah,</hi> as ſuch; And therefore as <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as <hi>God-man,</hi> he neither created the World, nor reſted from that Creation. Though in the Body of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, the Efficient of the Creation be only ſtiled <hi>Lord,</hi> by which may be equally underſtood the Son of God, before and after the Incarnation, yet in the Margin he interprets this by the word <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and therefore we have given a proper, a direct and ſufficient anſwer to that part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: And here it will be worth our obſerving, that in a proper and ſtrict Senſe, <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the Creator of the World, cannot be ſaid to <hi>reſt;</hi> becauſe it is impoſſible that he ſhould either admit of any Wearineſs, or Pain in himſelf; yea, or of any the leaſt new motion in himſelf; God being an Infinite, Perfect, Immutable, Act and Life, cannot poſſibly admit of any ſuch thing; and all the Changes that he makes, either
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97175:15"/>ſubſtantially of nothing into Being; or Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Qualities and Conditions of Being, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> without himſelf, are and muſt be without the leaſt Mutation, and Alteration within himſelf: And this the very Light of Nature, and Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks, will teach us, as well as the light of Scripture and Theology; as <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17. So that though God may properly be ſaid to conclude, or end his work of Creation, yet cannot he properly be ſaid to <hi>reſt</hi> from it, or after it; becauſe this, in its formal Notion, implies <hi>Motion,</hi> Activity and exerting of Power and Ability, with a <hi>Wearineſs</hi> thereby, which the Deity is infinitely free from: Which I deſire may be heeded, becauſe I perceive the Author would fain have every Clauſe in the Fourth Command to be <hi>Moral,</hi> and of neceſſary and perpetual Obſervance; and eſpecially this of <hi>Gods reſting on the Seventh day.</hi> Now that which is Moral, as to Motive and Obligation to the Humane Nature, is that which the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, right Reaſon, or (to go higher) the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly irradiated Mind of our firſt Parents, would have of its ſelf diſcerned and cloſed with, as a Motive and Engagement to Piety or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or any Duty: Which I think Gods <hi>reſting</hi> on the Seventh day may well be aſſerted not to be, becauſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Reaſon or the illuminated Mind of Man, could never ſuppoſe God to take after his work, any real Reſt or Refreſhment in himſelf, which he had not before. And Secondly, God's working in the maintaining of the Creation in its Being, Order and Operation, is altogether
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97175:16"/>as great, and as much, as it was in the Produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of it; and therefore the School-men ſay, That Preſervation is a continual Act of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe the ſame Word and Power is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erted in the one as in the other. Yea, if we reſpect the Work it ſelf, or the Term of it without God; we may well ſay that the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the World is a greater work than the Creation of it: Though as to the Act it ſelf in God, all is the ſame, (being the Act of the ſame infinite Power, Wiſdom and Godhead) becauſe of the contrary Qualities of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures mutually tending to each others Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but eſpecially becauſe of the Malice of Devils, and the ſinful wretched Depravity of Fallen Man; which without an infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Power exerted to the contrary, would ſoon bring all to Ruin, at leaſt it would do ſo by the Humane Nature, for which all other things of this World were made and are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued: And therefore this Motive to a Seventh-day-Sabbath, cannot be in, and of it ſelf Moral. And this our Saviour clearly ſhews, <hi>John</hi> 5.17. <hi>My Father worketh hitherto, and I work:</hi> Which he gives by way of Reply to thoſe, who in the former Context, taxed and condemned him for a Breach of the Sabbath. Grounding it ſeems (tacitely at leaſt) their Accuſation, from that Paſſage in the Fourth Command of God's reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on that day, as though it had been of a Moral and Perpetual Obligation: And therefore our Saviour here tells them, <hi>It was not ſo;</hi> for both he and his Father did work on the Seventh day, as well as on any other day of the week;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97175:16"/>from which 'tis clear this Clauſe in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, is <hi>not Moral,</hi> but <hi>Poſitive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Second Part of the Queſtion, <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Seventh-day-Sabbath was Sanctifyed, and ſo Inſtituted by him; and was obſerved by him who made the World.</hi> We anſwer, 'twas Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and Inſtituted by the Lord, <hi>as Jehovah,</hi> but not <hi>as Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> And then that 'twas obſerved by Jeſus Chriſt Incarnated, but <hi>not as Jehovah;</hi> becauſe the Obſervation of it, ſeems to import ſome dutiful Obligation upon its Obſerver, which cannot be ſuppoſed with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the <hi>God-head,</hi> but may be ſo with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Lord Chriſt, as <hi>Mediator</hi> in his Human Nature. But then this Obſervance makes no more for the keeping the Seventh-day-Sabbath, than for the Obſervance of <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> the <hi>Feaſt of Tabernacles,</hi> and other Ceremonial and Judicial Laws, under which our Lord Chriſt was, and which he obſerved in the days of his Fleſh; the Moſaical and the Ceremonial Adminiſtration being in force all the while he lived, and expired with his Death, and were buried in his Grave, as to their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Obligation: And ſo we aſſert the Seventh-day-Sabbath did alſo; which I hope we may evince in the progreſs of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>By what has been ſaid, we have a ſufficient Reply to his <hi>Three Proofs</hi> which follow his Querly, for it's Affirmative, and how they may be orthodoxly admitted, or elſe as Heterodox rejected. And here we may take notice that all the former Particulars which the Author makes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97175:17"/>uſe of, as Foundations to build his beloved No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon, do as equally militate and plead for the Obſervance of <hi>all the Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Laws,</hi> as for the Seventh-day-Sabbath; for the Creator of the World enjoyned <hi>them,</hi> as well as <hi>this.</hi> The great Jehovah impoſed <hi>them,</hi> as well as this. The Law-giver gave <hi>thoſe Laws,</hi> as well as <hi>this.</hi> And our Lord Inſtituted and Sanctifyed <hi>thoſe,</hi> as well as <hi>this,</hi> as he was <hi>God;</hi> and obſerved thoſe, as well as this, as <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> as God-man. 'Tis as Prejudice ſufficient againſt all thoſe (ſuppoſed) Achillean Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that if they prove what they are plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, <hi>We muſt all turn Jews.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But before I leave this Query, I muſt reflect upon one Paragraph or two, under it, <hi>Page</hi> 23. wherein we have him laying down all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer great <hi>Poſtulata's,</hi> that the Lord Chriſt made the World, reſted on the Seventh day, obſerved, bleſſed and ſanctifyed it: By which Repetition, we may ſee how much he depends upon theſe, for the carrying off his Deſign: But withal, we have formerly ſeen how little, yea, how not at all, they conduce thereto. But to theſe, he ſuperadds another grand <hi>Poſtulatum,</hi> as though 'twere a Particular, which either he had undeniably demonſtrated before, or were granted by his Adverſaries: Which is, <hi>that the Lord inſtituted this Seventh-day-Sabbath for,</hi> and <hi>impoſed it upon</hi> Adam, <hi>and in him, to all Mankind without distinction;</hi> and <hi>that before the Sin and Fall of</hi> Adam. And hence concludes that 'tis a Moral Law incumbent upon <hi>Adam,</hi> and all his Poſterity; which is a Concluſion, either
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97175:17"/>from rotten Premiſes, or from ſuch as will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver logically infer the Concluſion: Which we ſhall ſhew as briefly as we can; and what is ſpoken here, may leſſen ſome of our Work hereafter. 1. Hereby is implyed that this Command of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, was given to Man in the State of Innocency; which he can never prove. For though the Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, be inſerted in the beginning of the 2. of <hi>Geneſis</hi> yet 'tis clear, the Scripture doth not always keep a Chronical Order: We muſt not expect in our Bible, a conſtant <hi>Prius</hi> and <hi>Poſterius;</hi> (as they ſay) but the ſacred Hiſtory, admits of many <hi>hyſterons proterons;</hi> of many Miſplacings with reſpect to the order of time; relating thoſe thigns before, which were done after; and <hi>Vice Verſa:</hi> And 'tis moſt clear that 'tis ſo in this very place. For here the Sabbath is recorded before the Plantation of <hi>Paradice,</hi> v. 8. which was not ſpoken of before; yet was <hi>Paradice</hi> part of the Works of the Creation, and conſequently created before the Seventh day, though ſpoken of afterward; which proves that the order of the relation of the Sabbath, is no infallible proof that it was inſtituted before the Fall, but might be after it; though antecedently mentioned. And Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> brings many probable Arguments to prove that <hi>Adam</hi> fell before the Sabbath-day; and conſequently before the giving or declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that Precept; becauſe therein God's reſting on the Seventh-day, is propoſed as an <hi>Example</hi> and <hi>Motive</hi> to his keeping of it; which could not be done before the Seventh-day came:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97175:18"/>And ſo the Command muſt be given after the Fall. Which Arguments of his, ought to have been fairly debated, their Moment conſidered, and a due Anſwer and Solution given to them, before this had been ſo peremptorily aſſerted. But,</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> This ſeems to imply, that whatever In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction God gave to <hi>Adam</hi> before the Fall, was of things that are purely Moral, or ſo in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; or elſe it can never regularly be drawn from this Medium, that therefore the Seventh-day-Sabbath was ſo. But this we know was not ſo, for God prohibited him to eat of <hi>the Tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil;</hi> which was purely poſitive, and a Duty only reſulting from the Will of the Legiſlator. Again, if we ſhould take it for granted, that the Inſtitution and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the Seventh-day, was antecedent to the Fall, yet this would rather prove the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, than the Affirmative of its pure Morality. For whatever was purely Moral, and a Duty of its ſelf, reſulting from the Nature, Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Obligations of the rational Creature, <hi>Adam</hi> in the perfect Knowledge of that Nature, muſt know and diſcern, in and of himſelf; and conſequently would have known the Seventh-day to be ſo: And if he knew it, there needed no Inſtitution thereof, by God at all. Beſides, 'tis very obſervable, that from the Creation of our firſt Parents, till their Fall, we do not read of one <hi>Moral Duty</hi> enjoyned them, either of the Firſt or Second Table; (unleſs this be ſuppoſed to be ſo) and what reaſon can be given for it, but this, that it needed not; becauſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97175:18"/>they were all fully and diſtinctly implanted in Mans Soul. If therefore the Seventh-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, had been ſo <hi>Moral,</hi> 'twould not have need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſingular Inſtitution; much leſs ſuch Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to inforce its Obſervance upon perfectly wiſe, and holy <hi>Adam.</hi> From whence, in my Apprehenſion, a good Argument may be drawn againſt its Morality.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It implies, that all the Commands that were given to <hi>Adam</hi> in Innocency, are authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively incumbent upon all his Poſterity. The contrary whereto, is clear in the prohibition of the Tree in the midſt of the Garden; for that ceaſed both to himſelf and all his Poſterity upon his Fall: By all which, we ſee the weak reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of this Author.</p>
               <p>In the following Paragraph, he tells us that all thoſe things were recorded for the Glory of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; where as none of them do at all concern Jeſus Chriſt: For all thoſe things in the foregoing Paragraph by his own Doctrin, and according to his own Sentiments, were effected and agitated before the Fall of Man: In which time there could not be ſo much as any need or uſe of <hi>a Jeſus,</hi> or <hi>a Chriſt.</hi> Nor was there ſo much as the leaſt Hint of <hi>him</hi> given, by ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Propheſie or Promiſe; much leſs was he himſelf in being: And conſequently none of theſe things could conduce to his glory; for there can nothing appertain to that which is not. And thus theſe ſuppoſed unmoveable Foundations of this Tenent, are found not to be ſo much as Sandy: For they are found to be nothing at all, as he would have them refer to our Lord Chriſt.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97175:19"/>We acknowledge therefore that all theſe Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars which he named, are for the Glory of <hi>Jehovah;</hi> and that the Obſervance of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth-day-Sabbath, home to the Reſurrection of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt from the Dead, was to his Praiſe as Creator and Legiſlator. But withal, we hope to prove that the Change of it, and dedicating another day of the Week to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the ſame <hi>Jehovah,</hi> and ſpotleſs Son of the Virgin, does highly conduce to his Honour, as Lord and Glorious Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; as Conqueror of Hell and Death; as Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſher of that Great and Glorious Work of our merited Salvation. (A Work uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivably more glorious in it ſelf, and inſinitely more advantageous to us, and really laborious and grievous to himſelf) and as he entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his real Reſt on that day, even <hi>the firſt day,</hi> out of the Depths of his Humilitation. Here in the next Paragraph he quotes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.8. <hi>The Son of Man is Lord of the Sabbath,</hi> with that Gloſs or Interpretation which he puts upon it, which I doubt not, is very falſe, and has been already proved to be ſo: But becauſe he refers it to another Place, we ſhall attend him there, and then endeavour to give its true meaning. About the Fourhth Queſtion, <hi>Page</hi> 23. I ſhall not contend, for I verily believe the antient Patriarchs, did Obſerve and Sanctify the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth-day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97175:19"/>
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p>THE fifth Queſtion: <hi>Whether the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands were given by Chriſt to Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles?</hi> Page 24. He thinks he hath proved the Legiſlation of Chriſt from the Beginning: But how this is to be underſtood, and wherein he has taken falſe Meaſures, has been before ſhewn. Whether he gave them to <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that is, to all Mankind, he takes this for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed alſo, Which we alſo aſſert, even that all the Moral Law was given to the Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſo to all Mankind in <hi>Adam:</hi> But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, that the Seventh-day-Sabbath was no part of the Moral Law; no nor yet a ſeventh part of time to be Conſecrated and Sanctified to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip. (I mean <hi>not Primarily</hi> and <hi>in it ſelf Moral</hi>) which I ſhould endeavour here to prove; if I did not foreſee a more convenient Opportunity for it hereafter. Only let us here conſider what he himſelf here grants, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Moral Law was written upon Man's Heart; that it did conſiſt in <hi>Knowledge, Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Holineſs;</hi> wherefore the Seventh-day-Sabbath is no part of it; becauſe it was not written upon Man's Heart at firſt. 1. Becauſe God revealed it to Man after his Creation; which needed not, if it had been in him before. 2. Becauſe there are obſcure Remains of the Moral Law, in the Humane and Rational Creature, with reſpect to all the other Commands (as might be eaſily manifeſted by an Induction) but none as to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97175:20"/>
                  <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath.</hi> It is true, as to the Moral Subſtance of the Law, that is found in Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, even a Separation of time, and proper Seaſons for the Worſhip of God; but this is not: Nay, it is ſo rare, that not one among Ten thouſand does dream of it, or ſcarce one in an Age does ſo much as fancy it. 3. Becauſe by his own Orthodox Aſſertion in this very place, the Moral Law is reingraven, that is, more fully, clearly and diſtinctly, and in its Spiritual Senſe and Latitude upon the Hearts of thoſe that are revived by the Spirit of God, which is the Image of God, reinſtamped upon the Regenerate and Converted; as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.24. Now it is as clear as the Sun, that the Generality of the Called, inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſanctified, have not the Law of the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> written in their Hearts: Nay, they have an Averſion from it. Of all truly Religious ones, that ever I knew, Mr. <hi>B</hi>—is the Solitary Perſon of this Perſwaſion; whence it muſt neceſſarily follow, that it is no part of the Moral Law, or of that Image of God which was inſtamped upon Man plainly and fully at firſt; and remains imperfectly and obſcurely in all Men; and is reſtored to the Saints in their Regeneration, and is increaſed in them in their progreſſive Sanctification: Whence it is alſo clear, that this Command, thus ſtated, was not given by Chriſt to <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> in the Creation: And his proof for it is very weak and invalid; which is taken from thoſe expreſs Commands given by God to the Jews, of cauſing them that were either their Subſtance,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97175:20"/>(Slaves bought with their own Mony) or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes, Strangers by Nation, but yet joyning themſelves to them, and dwelling among them; and ſo were of their Body; who were bound, as he himſelf there acknowledges and proves, to be Circumciſed, to obſerve the Paſſover, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And now what Tendency hath this to prove, that the Seventh-day-Sabbath was given to <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles?</hi> When this proves only, that thoſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> were bound to keep it, who were within the Gates, and of their Body Politick: But has no reference to, nor does at all concern other <hi>Gentiles;</hi> ſome of which might never hear of the Name of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> or of any of their Laws and Sabbaths. It pities me to ſee ſuch weak and invalid Arguments; which if they have any force, it is to Judaize all the Chriſtian World.</p>
               <p>As to the ſecond part of the Queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the weekly Seventh-day-Sabbath were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ever after, during the Old Church: We acknowledge it was ſo ſtill among the Jewiſh Nation; and he needed not to have produced any proofs for it: But withall we ſay, <hi>never</hi> among any <hi>other Nations,</hi> nor any Footſtep of it, which is a ſure Proof againſt its proper Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. As to that Obſervation, <hi>Page</hi> 28. That the Seventh Day, throughout the Old and New Teſtament, was called the <hi>Sabbath day.</hi> It was fit it ſhould be ſo all along till our Saviour's Reſurrection; becauſe it was the Sabbath day till then: And afterward, if it be ſo called, it was in compliance with the Jews, who ſtill held it ſo to continue, or to uſe the Expreſſion which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97175:21"/>was in moſt common uſe, whereby the day might be known they ſpake of; (as we do of <hi>Sunday, Monday,</hi> &amp;c. only to declare what day of the Week we mean) or elſe to declare the Abolition thereof: And (if we remember it) we may make ſome uſe of that Aſſertion, that the <hi>Seventh day</hi> and <hi>Sabbath</hi> are Synonimous in the Language of the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>THis Queſtion he endeavours to prove Aſſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matively, <hi>Page</hi> 29. <hi>That Chriſt did in the Fleſh, confirm the Ten Commands, without any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the Fourth Commandment, or any part or tittle thereof.</hi> Which if we ſhould fully grant, without the leaſt Exception, it would make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for his Cauſe, nor againſt ours; for as long as Chriſt was in the World, ſo long we all agree, that the Seventh day of the Week was the injoyed Sabbath; and therefore ought to be obſerved; and ſo might have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Chriſt to be kept: And ſo we know he ratified the <hi>Ceremonial Law,</hi> by <hi>commanding the cleanſed Lepers to go and ſhew themſelves to the Prieſt, and offer the Gift which</hi> Moſes <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded for their cleanſing,</hi> Matt. 8.4. And ſo alſo the <hi>Judicial Law,</hi> by injoyning them to <hi>pay Tithe of all,</hi> even of <hi>Mint, Annis and Cummin,</hi> Matt. 23.23. (which I think few or none do hold to be purely Moral) and ſo the Brother's taking of his Childleſs Brother's Wife, he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97175:21"/>ſeems to confirm by a Tacit Approbation to the Sadducees, objecting that to him, to baffle and puzzle him about the Reſurrection, <hi>Matt.</hi> 22.23, 30. Yet nevertheleſs thoſe Laws were not permanent, but expired; the Ceremonial with himſelf, and the Judicial with the Judicial State and Polity. Withall we add, that our Saviour did for ever confirm the Moral Law, which is contained in the Ten Commandments: And ſo the Fourth, as far as Moral; and in all that it commands as ſuch: But withall we ſay, that ſome Paſſages of the Fourth Command are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Moral, nor yet commanded therein as ſuch; or of the Subſtance thereof: Whereof the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning of the laſt, the Seventh Day of the Week, to be the Sacred Reſt; is one: (which here is but nakedly aſſerted, but we defer the Proof) and ſuch as was to expire at his Reſurrection. Wherefore we ſay that that Paſſage, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Till Heaven and Earth paſs away, one jot or one tittle ſhall in no wiſe paſs away,</hi> muſt refer only to the Moral Law, <hi>Quatenus</hi> Moral; and as it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to, and obliges all Nations; which ſeveral Paſſages belonging to the Ten Commands do not; whereof this is one about the Seventh day; and I think th is may be cleared by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: That which neither our Saviour himſelf, nor any of his Apoſtles, did command or enjoyn to be followed by his, or their, Diſciples and Followers, cannot be Moral: But neither he nor they did ever enjoyn the Seventh-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, therefore it's not Moral. Our Saviour in none of his Diſcourſes (that I remember) did ever expreſly or particularly command the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97175:22"/>of the Sabbath-day; but ſpake and did things which ſeem to declare the Abolition of the Seventh day; neither do any of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, in any of their Writings, impoſe it upon, or command the Obſervance of it, from either <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to whom they write; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently we may conclude, that they never preached it (for we truly hold, that the Sum and Subſtance of all their Sermons is in their Books.) Yea, their Writings have ſeveral weighty Paſſages againſt the Seventh-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath. Now our Saviour in his Commiſſion which he gave his Apoſtles, after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, juſt as he was aſcending up to Heaven, expreſly commands them to <hi>teach all Nations to obſerve all things whatſoever he commandeth them,</hi> Matt. 28.19, 20. Wherefore ſeeing they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded not the Nations to obſerve the Seventh-day-Sabbath, Chriſt never taught them that Doctrin, nor injoyned them to do it; and therefore this cannot be one of thoſe Jots or Tittles of the Law, which in this Authors Senſe, was not to paſs from the Law; but only what was Moral in it. We acknowledge that the Lord Chriſt alſo confirmed the Moral Law, by commanding the Lawyer to <hi>love the Lord God,</hi> &amp;c. But withall, that whoever gives to God the ſeventh part of his time, though it be not the Seventh day of the week; does therein love God as to the Declaration, as to the Fruit and Effect of his Love, as much as if he did the Seventh day; becauſe it is as fully the Subſtance of that Command.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:97175:22"/>
               <p>The ſame anſwer will ſerve to <hi>Mark</hi> 12.28, 31. (<hi>Page</hi> 30.) with this Addition, That the change of the Seventh-day-Sabbath into that of the firſt day, is no more laying aſide of the Morality of the Fourth Command; than the change of Circumciſion, the Paſſover, and other Ceremonial Ordinances of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into Baptiſm, the Lords Supper, and other Evangelical Adminiſtrations under the New. Theſe being as really included in, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by, the ſecond Command at that time, as the Seventh-day-Sabbath is in and by the Fourth. And therefore as the change of thoſe Rites and Modes of Worſhip by our Lord Chriſt and his Apoſtles, was not the laying aſide of the ſecond Command, but rather a perfect Obedience thereto, and practical Confirmation thereof; ſo the change of the weekly-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was no Infringement, but rather an Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the Fourth Commandment.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Page he Inſinuates, that we take away thoſe words <hi>[The Seventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God]</hi> which yet we neither do in Letter, nor Senſe, for we leave the words in the Command, and obey them in their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and meaning: For they do not ſo much enjoyn the Seventh day in order, as in number, not ſo much the laſt day of the week, as one day of the week, to be obſerved and ſanctified by us (as I ſuppoſe we may have an opportunity to prove.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 31. He ſhews from Scripture that one great Article of the New Covenant, is Gods writing his Law upon the Hearts of his People,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97175:23"/>which he, with us, expreſly acknowledges to be the Moral Law: How then can the Seventh-day-Sabbath (as ſuch) be part of that Law, which is not written upon the Hearts of Thouſands, to one of Gods People. I judge this to be a clear Demonſtration againſt the Morality thereof.</p>
               <p>He could never have ſhewn, that the Seventh-day-Sabbath was a part of the Law of Nature in <hi>Adam,</hi>) though the ſubſtance of the Ten Commands was it) and therefore it was inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by God as before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 32. He ſhews us (for ſo I have a Belief he intends) that he had a mind to prove, that <hi>Set Forms of Prayers,</hi> or other parts of Worſhip under a Form, though never ſo Excellent, though in expreſs words of Scripture; are the <hi>Peſel</hi> or Graven Image, that is forbidden in the ſecond Command, which is a Notion, I am ſure, alien from the Reſentments of the moſt Grave, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, Learned and Experienced Chriſtians of former and Modern Ages, and very few of them have thought ſo uncharitably and rigor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly of them, as to brand them with the groſſeſt <hi>Idolatry;</hi> though many judge them fit to be lain aſide by them, to whom God hath given a good and competent Gift; but yet much rather to be u ſed, and that comfortably and profitably too, where ſuch a Gift may be denied. And I think by this Rule, that everly Man that joyns with another in Prayer is guilty of <hi>Idolatry</hi> againſt the ſecond Command; for he makes the words of the Miniſter, or private Chriſtian, to be the Set Form of his Prayer: And why a Prayer written <hi>as a Form,</hi> ſhould be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97175:23"/>more an <hi>Idol</hi> than a Prayer ſpoken as a <hi>Form,</hi> I do not yet underſtand.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Paragraph he alſo hints, that the Lords Prayer ought only to be uſed in ſecret and alone; not in publick, no, nor in private, with any others; becauſe of thoſe Expreſſions in <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.6, 9. <hi>When thou prayeſt, enter into thy Cloſet and ſhut thy Door and Pray,</hi> &amp;c. Whereas the Form of that Prayer in the plural Number, the very matter of that Prayer, being the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Concern of the Univerſal Church, and of every Congregation and Society of Chriſtians, as well as of every private Chriſtian; and our Saviour commanding his Diſciples to uſe it without any ſuch Limitation: Of a ſecret Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Retirement, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.2. are ſufficient proofs, that it may be as well uſed Socially as Solitarily; with others as lawfully and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently as by ones ſelf.</p>
               <p>In the following Paragraph he ſeems to be of the Opinion, that it would be better to have Mens or Miniſters own Inventions in ſinging of <hi>Pſalms,</hi> than the Divine Inſpirations of <hi>David</hi> and other Authors in Scripture. And when I can believe, that theirs can be better than thoſe in Scripture; or can be convinced that there is neither <hi>Pſalm</hi> nor <hi>Hymn</hi> in the Bible that can fit a preſent Condition, either for Prayer, or Praiſes, or Gratitude, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I will think ſo: but as to the former of theſe two, I hope I ſhall never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve; and as to the latter, I think it is not likely to fall out in my days. Theſe things ought as curiouſly to be replied, as the Author has ſtarted theſe Notions; and when he ſees fit
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97175:24"/>to endeavour a more large Explication and Vindication of them, then we may alſo ſee what may be diſcourſed agianſt them. And I heartily wiſh, he had but hinted this of his <hi>Seventh day;</hi> and ſo ſaved all this labour in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering of it; for it is juſt another ſuch Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as the former, and deſerved only to be mentioned: Indeed not to be mentioned at all, at leaſt not in Print, not in publick: But of this in the Preface.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p>IN the next Paragraph he tells us, he has much to do to recover the word <hi>[Seventh]</hi> of the Fourth Commandment: Whereas none, but the Deniers of the Morality of the Seventh, would wreſt it from him; for we all grant it to him, and acknowledge it to be of the very ſubſtance of the Command; that a Seventh day ſhould be ſet apart for an Holy Conſecrated Day to Divine Worſhip; only we ſay, that the Seventh day is ſo, as the ſeventh part of the Week; as one day of the ſeven, and not the ſeventh in order; or the laſt day of the Week: This we ſay is not expreſly commanded therein, and might be altered for another day of the Seven, upon very good and authentick Reaſons and Grounds; as it is from it to the firſt.</p>
               <p>In this ſame Page he returns to our Saviours Confirmation of the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> from <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17, 19. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.17. and then asks why
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97175:24"/>thoſe places confirm all the 10 Commands, and not the Seventh-day-Sabbath; and tells us that he can aſſign no other reaſon for it, but the marvelous Corruption of our Nature, which inclines us to be Gods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when yet he knows, that they that are for the change of the Seventh, into the Firſt-day-Sabbath, have given him many Reaſons and good ſcriptural Grounds and Arguments, which do amount (in their Eſteems) to a divine Authority for that Change; (though they do not produce an expreſs Command for it; (as that which he ſeems to require in this Paragraph yet, what amounts thereto) but it ſeems all theſe are not Reaſons to him; are not ſo much as Shews of Reaſons: But the only Reaſon is Man's Corruption, Pride and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion. Whereas he cannot but know, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of thoſe, who in Doctrin and Practice, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of this Change, are as free from theſe Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and have as much mortifyed them, as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and are as Eminent for Holineſs, and Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Obedience to God, as any <hi>Sabbatarian</hi> can pretend to be: And their Earneſtneſs for the <hi>Firſt day,</hi> does not ſpring from the Looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of others thereon, nor mainly and chiefly from their Education and Cuſtom: But becauſe they know 'tis <hi>not Moral,</hi> (as other Parts and Appendix's of the Ten Commandments are not) and therefore not confirmed by Chriſt in thoſe Expreſſions; with many other good and ſolid Grounds.</p>
               <p>And here I ſhall ask him by way of requital, if the Seventh-day-Sabbath were really and primarily <hi>Moral,</hi> and by Chriſt confirmed, as
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97175:25"/>well as all the other Commands, which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably ſo. Whence comes it to paſs, that in all his Sermons and Diſcourſes that he made to the <hi>Jews</hi> about the Moral Law, he did not ſo much as ever mention <hi>the Sabbath</hi> to his Hearer; either by way of Recommendation of it to them, or commending of them for their Zeal for it, and tthe ſtrict Obſervance of it; nor yet commanding of its Obſervance, or teaching them how they ſhould Keep and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy it according to its firſt Inſtitution? ſeeing 'tis clear, that he in his Diſcourſe, doth par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularize every other Duty of the Moral Law; and Exhorts, and Requires Obedience thereto. In all his moſt copious and glorious Sermon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Mount,</hi> where he Explains, Enlarges up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Injoyns the other Moral Duties, we have not a Word about <hi>their Sabbath;</hi> and when ever he enumerates Particulars of the Moral Law of the Decalogue, he never mentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, <hi>the Sabbath;</hi> nor when ſo many particular and expreſs Occaſions were given him by the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and captions <hi>Jews;</hi> (in their condemning him and his Diſciples, as Profaners of the Sabbath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) to expound the Duty of the Sabbath, and to ſhew them where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the due religious and acceptable Obſervance of the Seventh-day-Sabbath conſiſted; There is not the leaſt Word appertaining hereunto, ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by him; only a Vindication of his own, and his Diſciples Practices, from a Profanation thereof. If I may judge at the Reaſons, I think they may be ſuch as theſe.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:97175:25"/>
               <p n="1">1 Becauſe he knew that it was not of the ſame nature with the others, not Moral as they, nor neceſſary to be kept to Salvation as they. 2. Becauſe he ſaw the <hi>Jews</hi> too ſuperſtitiouſly and zealouſly affected towards their Seventh-day-Sabbath already. 3. Becauſe neither they nor we, neither <hi>Jews</hi> nor <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſhould have any thing from his Mouth that might have the leaſt colour of confirming that Sabbath-day. 4. Becauſe he deſigned its ſpeedy Abſolution as the Seventh day, and its Converſion into the Firſt day. 5. Becauſe as Place, Prieſthood, Mode, outward Ceremonies of Divine Worſhip, which were before his coming into the Fleſh; were to be altered by his Authority, as King of the Church, ſo was Time alſo; the day on which thoſe were chiefly and moſt ſlemnly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, into another day, wherein his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions were to be chiefly and generally practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by his Church: And for theſe and ſuch like Reaſons, he did not only particularly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and enjoyn, but did alſo ſpeak and do (as has been formerly hinted, and may be fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely evinced) ſuch words and things, as had a doctrinal and practical Tendency towards its Expiration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 33. He imputes the Obſervation of the Firſt day, but to a good Intention; which has been the cauſe of all manner of groſs Superſtitious Errors, Bloody Wars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As though this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Opinion and Practice of the Univerſal Church all along, ſince the days of our Lord Chriſt, had no other Foundation, but in the deluded Brain of ſilly Zealots, and not the leaſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97175:26"/>Footing for it in the Word of God. An unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Suggeſtion, and a moſt invidious Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and ſuch as very ill becomes a Man of his profeſſed Candor and Reading.</p>
               <p>'Tis ſtrange that a Man ſhould fancy that <hi>Commenius,</hi> when he exhorts to a Reformation of the Government, Doctrin, Worſhip and Practice of the Church; according to the Word of God, and the Patern in the <hi>Mount,</hi> ſhould mean as one, if not the chieſt of thoſe Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, the removal of the Firſt-day-Sabbath, and the reverſion of the ſeventh day in lieu there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: When he knows that all the Divines and Doctors that are orthodox, and his Adverſaries in this Opinion, preſcribe the ſame rule for the Reformation, and call upon thoſe in Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to ſubſerviate all their own Laws Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtial and Civil, to an Obſervance of the Laws of God and of Chriſt: And <hi>Commenius</hi> himſelf, in his Practice and in his own Church, was an Obſerver and Sanctifier of the Firſt-day-Sabbath, (as he here acknowledgeth) ſo a Diſowner and Rejector of the Seventh day: And therefore queſtionleſs did not eſteem the Seventh-day-Sabbath to be any part of that rule, according to which he would have all Churches regulated. But here we ſee what a ſtrong fancy can do; it can transfigure into its ſelf thoſe things that are quite diſſonant, if not directly contrary thereto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:97175:26"/>
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p>HE gives us his Opinion <hi>Page</hi> 34. of <hi>abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating the Ceremonial Laws:</hi> But why does he not bring us an Expreſs Command for their Abrogation, as he requires us to do, for not the Abrogation, but only the Mutation of the Sabbath, from one Day of the Week to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other? For I aſſert, and can prove it, that ſome part of the Ceremonial Law was more confirmed by the Mouth of Chriſt, than <hi>his Seventh-day-Sabbath.</hi> I take leave to call it <hi>his,</hi> becauſe though 'twas Gods day before the Reſurrection of Chriſt, yet now 'tis not ſo; but Men will be favourably to themſelves and their own Opinions, while they are rigorous towards others, and their more Orthodox and Scriptural Reſentments.</p>
               <p>In the ſame <hi>Page</hi> he gives us a Caution of not incurring the Threats of infringing the Laws of Chriſt, even the <hi>leaſt</hi> of them; and by way of a charitable Requital, we warn him to be cautious leſt he build again that which Chriſt hath deſtroyed, and repair the raſed Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue.</p>
               <p>Here we have alſo his Notion of what is Moral, telling us that many call the Ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments <hi>the Moral Law:</hi> I think all ſlid Divines do call them ſo; but none that I know, do ſay that every Clauſe and Word in them, or belonging to them, (by this laſt Expreſſion, I mean part of the Preface to them) is Moral;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97175:27"/>and particularly not the Seventh-day-Sabbath, or that Clauſe appertaining thereto in the Fourth Commandment; no, nor yet the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Part of Time therein expreſly command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and perpetually too, (that is not primari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nor abſolutely, and of its ſelf ſo.) As to his Notion of what is Moral, I cannot call it either a Definition, or a Deſcription of the thing; but only an Interpretation of the Word <hi>Moral,</hi> viz. pertaining to <hi>Manners.</hi> We uſually in ſuch Diſcourſes, put <hi>Moral,</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to what is <hi>poſitive;</hi> whether it be Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial, or Judicial: But this is ſuch a Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as includes all Laws whatever, even Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man as well as Divine, and of Divine, all of them of what ſort or kind ſoever; for they all apertain to <hi>Manners:</hi> Yea, to Thoughts, Words and Actions; yea, and are included in the Love of God, becauſe whoever loves God truely, will, and muſt yield Obedience to all his Laws of what ſort ſoever; whether Moral or Poſitive. But ſuch a lax Interpretation of the Moral Law, ſerved to the Deſign of the Seventh Day, becauſe it includes it will all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poſitive Laws; but had he given us a true Notion of what is <hi>Moral in its ſelf,</hi> or in its own Nature, it would neceſſarily have been exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: As may be evinced by ſome Properties of what is truly Moral.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Moral Law is inward, and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated with the rational Creature; and does need no external Revelation, or Divine Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution; eſpecially in the State of human Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity before the Fall; but ſuch was not the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97175:27"/>day: For 'twas Inſtituted by God, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Mans Creation. 2. The Moral Law yet remains in ſome Footſteps and Degrees there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in the Human Nature, and ſo in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Mankind, the Heathens themſelves not excepted; (as might be eaſily proved by their Laws and Writings) but the Notion of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day,</hi> is Univerſally excluded; and the Generality of Mankind totally deſtitute there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. If it be here objected, That the Heathen did ſeparate a Seventh-day to their Religious Service: To this may be applyed, That 'twas but ſome of them, and but for ſome time; not Univerſally and Perpetually. That they did it by Tradition from the <hi>Jews,</hi> or by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> Inſtitution and Injunction, who in his curſed Pride, affects to have his Votaries ſerve him, as the Acknowledgers of <hi>Jehovah</hi> do him. 3. All Moral Laws are clearly and diſtinctly ingraven upon the Minds and Hearts of thoſe that are enlightned and ſanctifyed by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God: But not a Tittle or <hi>punctum</hi> of his Seventh-day is ſeen in the Generality of them. 4. Man was made for Moral Duty, that is, to Glorify and Honour God in all Acts of Internal and External Piety; to profit and comfort his Neighbour by all Acts of Charity; to poſſeſs his own Veſſel in Sanctification and Honour. And by ſo doing, he lives up to the end for which he was made: But now <hi>Man was not made for the Sabbath</hi> and for its Obſervance, but the Sabbath was made for Man, and for his Good, <hi>Mark</hi> 2.27. 5. Moral Duties are ſuch, as a Man cannot change them, or neglect
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97175:28"/>them, or do any thing beſide them, without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honouring and ſinning againſt God. But now it is certain, That as to the Nature of the thing its ſelf, (ſeparated form a poſitive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution) that a Man may as fully Glorify and Honour God, and as compleatly ſerve him, by appropriating and imploying another day of the Week to, and in his Workſhip and Service, as the Seventh; provided he do dedicate ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day in Seven, to that Service, the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is the ſame; and the proportion of time the ſame: and ſo God as much and as long ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as upon the laſt day of the Week. Let him denominate any other Propriety of what is <hi>Moral;</hi> and I will undertake to evince, That it belongs not to his Seventh-day-Sabbath. To what purpoſe then to urge and inſiſt ſo much, and ſo long, upon the Moral Law, when the Seventh-day-Sabbath, is no part at all of the Morality thereof?</p>
               <p>Thoſe Paſſages before mentioned, That <hi>Chriſt came not to deſtroy, but to fulfil the Law; that the Breaker of the leaſt of Gods Commands, ſhall be leaſt in the Kingdom of God,</hi> &amp;c. And theſe Page 35. <hi>He that will enter into Life, muſt keep the Commandments: It is eaſier for Heaven and Earth to paſs away, than one tittle of the Law, to fail;</hi> do not only concern the Moral Law (though if they did, we have ſufficiently ſhewn that the Sabbath is not concerned in them) but alſo the Poſitive; even the Ceremonial Law. For while they were in Force, as they all were throughout the days of our Saviour's <hi>Animal Life;</hi> (which I ſo call, to diſtinguiſh it from
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97175:28"/>the <hi>Glorious Life</hi> of his Humanity upon Earth after his <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>) They that would enter into Life (at leaſt of the Jews and their Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes, to whom only they were Laws and Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory) were bound to keep them. And if they did willfully and perſeveringly diſobey them, they would as certainly be Damned, as if they had lived in a Contradiction to any of the Moral Laws: Becauſe ſuch a Refuſal to obſerve and keep the Ceremonial Laws, is directly and ultimately a Diſobedience to the Moral; and that too, to the very Soul and Foundation of all the Commandments: Even the Firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, by being a Renunciation of Gods Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in refuſing a Conformity to his revealed Will. Again it was a direct and immediate Sin againſt the Second Command; by being a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal to worſhip him according to his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Worſhip: So Chriſt came not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the Ceremonial Law, but to fulfil it. Which he did by being the End and Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation thereof; by being the Subſtance of thoſe Figures, and the Body of thoſe Shadows, and no Law is deſtroyed which continues in its Force as long as the Legiſlator intended, and produces all thoſe Ends for which he deſigned it. Now the Ceremonial was intended by God to be no longer a Law, than till our Lords Death, or Reſurrection, or Miſſion of the Holy Ghoſt; and it was deſigned only to typiſie the Lord Chriſt, and to lead Believers to him, as to the End and Subſtance thereof; which our Lord, being he was ſo far from deſtroying it, that he perfectly fulfilled it, though he abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97175:29"/>its future legal Authority: And ſo not one tittle of the Ceremonial Law did fail, for all had its Accompliſhment on Chriſt, no more than a tittle of the Moral Law cannot: So that we have granted him his deſire, in ſhewing him what Law Chriſt meant in ſuch Paſſages, even the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> as well as the <hi>Moral;</hi> for they were the Object of the Superſtitious Jews greateſt Zeal, and they perſecuted him and his Diſciples, as the Overthrowers of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial Laws; and therefore Chriſt tells them, <hi>He came not to deſtroy, but to fulfil them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>By all that hath been already ſaid, is fully ſhewn, the Impertinency of thoſe Quotations (<hi>Page</hi> 35. 38.) where our Saviour makes uſe of an confirms the <hi>Moral Law:</hi> For there is not one word of his Sabbath in them all. In our Saviour's Carriage and Language he vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates the Sanctity of the Temple, <hi>John</hi> 2.13, 17. ſo he does Circumciſion, and Authorizes its Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations upon the Sabbath day, and derives it from a more Auguſt Antiquity than <hi>Moſes, John</hi> 7.22, 23. If our Author had any ſuch Expreſſion from our Saviour's Mouth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Sabbath; how would he have triumphed therein, and have fetch'd its everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eſtabliſhment therefrom? But there is not one ſuch Syllable concerning it. Theſe have a greater ſhew for their Authority from our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Diſcourſes than the Seventh-day-Sabbath; yet I doubt not but he looks on them as no longer in Force, and of no Obligation in theſe latter and Evangelical days.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:97175:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 37. He produces the Church of <hi>England</hi> Articles, the Presbyterian Confeſſion, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependants Declaration of Faith, for the Rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the Moral Law; who yet are all for the Excluſion of the laſt day of the Week from being the <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath;</hi> and thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their Rejection of it from being any part thereof: And thus all the Authority, both Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Humane, that he produceth, makes nothing at all for him, but very much rather againſt him: With which this queſtion is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <p>HE propoſes the Queſtion, <hi>Page</hi> 38. <hi>Whether Chriſt in his own Perſon did not obſerve the Seventh Week-day-Sabbath, and no other during his Life.</hi> To which we anſwer affirmatively with him, that he did ſo, that he was bound to do it, that it was part of his Righteouſneſs which he was to fulfil; for he was born under the Authority and Obligation of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Adminiſtrations; even of the Ceremonial ones, and therefore was Circumciſed the eighth day; went up to <hi>Jereuſalem</hi> with his Mother in his Childhood to keep the Annual Feaſts; and in his Manhood was a Conſtant, Conſcientious and obedient Attender upon, and obſerver of the Paſſover; as we read in the Hiſtory of his Life, after his Baptiſm, and manifeſting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the World, home to his Death, or juſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97175:30"/>before his Sufferings; and ſo doubtleſs did by all the other <hi>Ceremonial Laws,</hi> according to Gods Injunction of them, and was an Obſerver of all other poſitive Divine Laws; and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently muſt he be of this; for neither all the former, nor this particular, were to be abrogated and lain aſide, as to their Authority, till he himſelf was lain aſide and buried in the Grave. Without doubt he alſo dutifully kept and practiſed all the <hi>Judicial Laws;</hi> being born a Member of their State, as well as of their Church, as far as their Roman Lords would permit; for the Authority of theſe Laws laſted as long as the Judicial Polity; and with it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined and perfectly expired. Will this Pleader for the Seventh day, contend for the Authority of all thoſe Ceremonial and Judicial Laws home to our days, becauſe our Bleſſed Lord obſerved and kept them? He muſt do ſo, if this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be of any weight. And it has been the Fate of all his Arguments hitherto, to militate as much for all the Ceremonies (except that of the Sabbaths being given in Innnocency) of the Jews, as for the Seventh day. Enough for their own Confutation.</p>
               <p>Juſt another ſuch Medium is cunningly inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated, <hi>Page</hi> 39. to prove the Goodneſs of the Obſervation of this Sabbath, <hi>viz. Its Antiquity,</hi> having been the Sabbath of the Church for four thouſand Years; which will introduce Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices into the Worſhip of God, a Bloody Offering up of Beaſts, for they are as ancient within a day or two (as 'tis probable) for God taught <hi>Adam</hi> to offer up ſuch Sacrifices as the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97175:30"/>Types of the Seed of the Woman who was to have his Heel bruiſed by the Serpent, his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature murthered by the Devil and his Agents; but then ſacrificed and offered up to God, as the Expiratory Victim for the ſins of Fallen Man: And 'tis probable that thoſe Skins which God made Coats of for <hi>Adam,</hi> might be of ſuch ſacrificed Beaſts: And <hi>Adam</hi> taught his Sons to Sacrifice to God: And we read <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4. <hi>That</hi> Abel <hi>brought to God the Firſtlings of his Flock, and the Fat thereof.</hi> Will he therefore plead that their venerable Antiquity muſt ſtill give them a place in the Evangelical Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, now that that Grand and All-ſufficient Sacrifice, the ſubſtance of thoſe Shadows, is offered up? I trow not: So neither can the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of the former Sabbath, till our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's days, and through his days, be any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for its Admiſſion and Authority now; ſeeing by our Saviours coming, we have <hi>the new Heaven and the new Earth,</hi> which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets foretold, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.17. &amp; 66.22. and a more glorious and bleſſed Work accompliſhed, than that of the Creation; which doth much more deſerve a Sanctification and Separation of that day, whereon its Compleater reſted from all his former Labours, and a new external Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration was introduced; and a new day and conſecrated time ſuitably alſo inſtituted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:97175:31"/>
               <head>SECT. IX.</head>
               <p>IT is demanded <hi>Page</hi> 40. <hi>Whether Chriſt did reſt the Seventh-day-Sabbath when he was in the Grave.</hi> And it is affirmatively reſolved, that his Soul reſted in Heaven, and his Body reſted in the Grave that day. All as a Proof that our Lord Chriſt himſelf, did in his ſtate of Death, confirm that Seventh-day-Sabbath, as well as by his Practice and Doctrin in Life; and ſo recommended it to the Obſervance of all the future Churches: Which Notion, if it could be proved, would do more for the Seventh-day-Sabbath, than all the Arguments he hath yet brought. If he could rationally demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that the bleſſed Redeemer did reſt on the Seventh day from all his Humiliation and Sufferings; he would then defeat the great ground on which all the Churches, ſince our Lords coming and conſummating the work of Redemption, have built upon for the Change of the Seventh day, into the Firſt-day-Sabbath. For they ſay, they do it, becauſe on the firſt day our Lord Jeſus God-man, reſted from that more Wonderful, Glorious, Gracious, Profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and Raviſhing Work, than that of the Creation and more laborious and difficult work to himſelf; being really and dreadfully ſo to his Humane Nature. But indeed this Notion is a very ſtrange and an uncouth one; becauſe the <hi>Reſt</hi> of the Mediator in this Senſe, cannot be thought to be any other than a happy and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97175:31"/>Complacential Reflection upon the work of our Redemption, merited by all his Active and Paſſive Obedience; which could not be until he had waded through all the Degrees of his Abaſement, and begun his Exaltation, and ſo in his Bleſſed and Glorious Eſtate, delighting himſelf in his Conqueſt of the Devil, the World, Death and the Grave; and his having per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly ſatisfied Juſtice, and purchaſed Grace and Glory for Loſt Sinners; which could not be till the Reſurrection of his Body. Can the State of Death with any probability be thought the <hi>Mediator's Reſt?</hi> Or his lying in the Grave, be deemed the end of all his Abaſements, when Death was the worſt thing his Enemies could bring upon him in their Rage and Fury; when they triumphed over him in the Grave; and concluded that now they had compleatly van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed him, and proved him to be a Grand Deceiver, <hi>Matt.</hi> 27.62, 64. when it was that which was eſpecially required as the utmoſt of his Sufferings for the Expiation of our Sins; being that which was denounced, at firſt againſt Sin, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. and as the conſummate Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof, and is the proper Wages of Sin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. and therefore ſo to be undergone and lain under by the Sinners Surety; ſtanding in his ſtead, and bearing his Puniſhment, and being made that Curſe for him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. which was the loweſt Deſcent of his Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which ſaddened the Hearts of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and filled them with fear, whoſe hopes almoſt expired at his Death, and were buried in his Grave; in which Eſtate if he had abode,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97175:32"/>the Devil and his Enemies would have gotten a compleat Victory over him, and we could never have been juſtified nor ſaved.</p>
               <p>Moreover our Saviour's Body and Soul reſted as much upon the Croſs after his Death, as they did in the Grave after his Burial; And ſo the <hi>Muchammediſts</hi> have as fair a Plea for their Sixth-day-Sabbath, becauſe on that day the Dead Body of our Saviour felt no pain on the Tree, and his Soul enjoyed all Bliſs in Heaven. And ſo in this ſenſe reſted on their day of Worſhip.</p>
               <p>How unreaſonable and unſcriptural to call this the Reſt of our Redeemer! Beſides it was impoſſible that as <hi>Redeemer</hi> he ſhould reſt in the State of Death, and in the Grave; for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer muſt be God-man; his Deity could not declaratively reſt, till it had raiſed its own Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity out of the Grave, and rent in ſunder the Bonds of Death: And his Humanity could not really do ſo; becauſe <hi>it was not,</hi> during that Condition; for we know that Death is the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Soul from the Body: Now the Soul ſeparated from the Body, is a Spirit and not a Man; the Body ſeparated from the Soul, is a Corps not a Man; both Soul and Body ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated are not <hi>Man;</hi> but eſſentially conjoyned they make the Man. Wherefore though both Body and Soul in their mutual Separation were united to the Deity; and ſo he was always God, and had the eſſential parts of Man; yet being divided, he was not Man; for by Death they being diſſolved, his Humanity was deſtroyed, and continued ſo, as long as Death had power
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97175:32"/>over him. So that 'tis againſt all Reaſon and common Senſe, to aſſert that the <hi>Mediator,</hi> who muſt be <hi>God-man,</hi> reſted in the Grave; ſeeing in this true ſenſe he could not be Man there. No, no, <hi>This was no part of his Reſt,</hi> but his Reſurrection from the Grave; the re-uniting of his Body and Soul, was the firſt entrance into it: For as the Father, Son and Holy Spirit, <hi>Jehovah,</hi> is not ſaid to reſt, till he had fully compleated his ſix days work of Creation; and then with infinite Complacency viewed all he had compleated on the Seventh: So <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, God-man,</hi> cannot be ſaid to reſt from the Work of our Redemption, till he had fully compleated and ended all his <hi>Humiliation;</hi> till he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered all his and our Enemies; which could not poſſibly be while he lay in the Grave on the Seventh day; but it was when he roſe from thence on the Firſt; when indeed he had a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and Bleſſed ſatisfaction in himſelf, when he reflected upon all he had done, and all the Sufferings he waded through, and all the Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation he was ſunk into, and had happily and triumphingly concluded, with all thoſe ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Bleſſings that ſhould accrue to the Church, and that infinite Glory that would redound to God thereby: And therefore as God's Reſting on the Seventh day from his work of Creation, was propoſed as the Example and Motive to the Old Church before Chriſt's coming, for the keeping the Seventh for their <hi>Sabbath:</hi> So likewiſe our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s <hi>Reſting</hi> from his work of our <hi>Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> on the Firſt day of the Week, may wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily be, and we ſay really is, propoſed as a
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97175:33"/>Motive and Example to the Churches, ſince his coming, for their conſecrating of that day for their Weekly Sabbath. I am ſorry that ſuch Paſſages of the Author, ſhould occaſion ſo much Tediouſneſs to the Reader, and inforce ſuch Enlargedneſs from the Writer. As to that place, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.20. which he tells us he will improve hereafter to his own Advantage, we ſhall attend his Motions, and meet him there.</p>
               <p>To his Query <hi>Page</hi> 41. we grant that the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Believers, did keep the Seventh-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, while our Saviours Body was in the Grave; and that they ought to do ſo, becauſe as yet, <hi>the Firſt day</hi> by our Lords Reſurrection, was not Conſecrated to be obſerved as the day of the Redeemers Reſt. And withal, that they were obliged during this time, to obſerve <hi>the unleavened Bread-Feaſt;</hi> and (ſuppoſing it to be the Eighth day from their Birth, to Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their Children) yet I hope this is no Plea for the everlaſting Permanency of theſe: So neither can it be for that of the Seventh-day-Sabbath.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. X.</head>
               <p>WE have his Conjecture <hi>Page</hi> 43. about the Week-day of <hi>our Lord's Aſcenſion;</hi> which he would fain ſuppoſe to be <hi>on the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth:</hi> But if we may believe St. <hi>Luke,</hi> Act. 1.3. that he tarried on Earth Forty Days, and ſo was viſible to his Diſciples all that time, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97175:33"/>converſed with them as oft as he ſaw fit, and about what was moſt neceſſary and profitable for their Knowledge; and <hi>then</hi> aſcended into Heaven: If we look on this as an Hiſtorical Account of his Abode on Earth after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, (as it lays a fairer Foundation for it, than all Human Conjectures can be) then if we reckon from the <hi>Firſt day</hi> of the Week, to the Fortieth day, and both the Firſt and Laſt inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, then the day of his Aſcenſion, was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Fifth day of the Week; which is our <hi>Thurſday,</hi> (as the Church of <hi>England</hi> obſerves it) If we exclude either the Firſt or Laſt day only, 'twill be upon the Sixth day of the Week, our <hi>Fryday,</hi> (if I miſtake not;) but if we exclude both the Firſt and Laſt Days, (I mean the day of his Reſurrection, and the day of his Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) from the number of Forty days, then 'twill fall out upon the Seventh day of the Week our <hi>Saturday;</hi> which he conjectures to be the day of the Week of our Saviours Aſcenſion: But here we muſt conſider that we have two to one againſt him in this Conjecture: And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Conjecture, and the uſual Phraſe of Scripture, our Saviour would have conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued Forty Two days upon Earth: For the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the number of Days, does uſually in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude both <hi>the Firſt</hi> and <hi>Laſt day.</hi> As in calling the <hi>laſt</hi> day of the Week the <hi>Seventh,</hi> it takes into the Number, both <hi>it,</hi> and the <hi>Firſt</hi> day of the Week; for there are but Seven in all: And ſo when it ſaith that our Saviour roſe <hi>the Third day</hi> from the Dead, it includes the <hi>Firſt</hi> and <hi>Laſt</hi> days of the Three; and therefore having
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97175:34"/>the ſcriptural uſual Phraſe on our ſide, and the Tradition of the Churches, we have very good Ground to conclude, that he aſcended upon <hi>Thurſday;</hi> and he has no Ground but his own Conjecture, for his Opinion of his Aſcenſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Saturday.</hi> But every little Surmiſe is made uſe of, to exalt the Seventh above all the days of the Week; and eſpecially above <hi>the Lords day</hi> in this Controverſie. As to that Fancy of our Saviours coming to Judgment on the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, I leave it as a Pure Fancy.</p>
               <p>Here alſo he takes it for granted, that our Saviour after his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> appeared to his Diſciples upon the Seventh day, (or at leaſt he ſuppoſes it may well be granted) becauſe they were then aſſembled, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But he knows they met together on other days, and particularly upon <hi>the Firſt day,</hi> on which our Lord appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto them. And that Aſſembly in the Firſt of the <hi>Acts,</hi> if 'twere on the Aſcenſion day, was according to Scripture numbering of days, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Thurſday.</hi> But ſeeing he would make uſe of (if we would grant) our Lords appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Diſciples once on the Seventh day, what an Advantage may we juſtly take for the Firſt day, from our Saviour's appearing ſo <hi>oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en</hi> unto them on the ſame? ſo that there is <hi>no other day</hi> of the Week named, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Saviour manifeſted himſelf unto them <hi>after the Reſurrection,</hi> but this Firſt day: 'Tis not ſaid that he appeared unto them on the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond or Third, nor at all on the Seventh; and 'tis very probable, that all the Appearances of our Saviour, (which were not a few) were <hi>on
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97175:34"/>the Firſt day:</hi> Except only that on his <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> day. 'Tis worth our ſerious Obſervance, that as our Saviour would not grace the Seventh day, with one particular expreſs word of his Mouth about it, during his Life-time, ſo he would not honour it with one Appearance of his Human Nature to his Diſciples, throughout all the Forty days after his Reſurrection: Which to me, ſeems plainly to ſignify, that he would have a perpetual <hi>Silence</hi> thereof, in his future Churches; and that he had buried it in his Grave, and would have it lye dormant there for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XI.</head>
               <p>HAving done with this Conjecture, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the Author's Queſtion in the ſame Page, <hi>Whether the Seventh-day-Sabbath was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved after the Reſurrection and Aſcenſion of Chriſt:</hi> Whereof he thinks he demonſtrates the Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative: But is far enough from it by thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances which he brings from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and eſpecially and moſtly from St. <hi>Paul;</hi> yea, only from him. For though we take it for granted, that many of the newly Proſelyted <hi>Jews</hi> to the Doctrin and Faith of the Lord Jeſus, (the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and common ſort of them) did continue to obſerve the Seventh-day-Sabbath, out of an Erroneous Conſcience toward God, and a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion of the perpetual Obligation of the Fourth Command, as to this Seventh day, as
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97175:35"/>they did alſo <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Moſaical Rites, and Conſecrated Times (for all which, St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſtles to the <hi>Galatians</hi> and <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> does clearly and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely reprove them.) Yet we ſay that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> themſelves never did ſo, much leſs St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the great Doctor of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the great Vindicator of their Freedom from the Rites and Days of the Old Teſtament-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration: For they were otherwiſe, and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taught by their Lord, and inſtructed by the Holy Ghoſt; for they went indeed, (I mean <hi>Paul</hi> and his Companions) into the Synagogues on the <hi>Sabbath-day,</hi> I mean here the Seventh-day; though it deſerves not now that Name. But 'twas not in any Obſervance of <hi>that day,</hi> as more <hi>Holy</hi> than another; as 'twas not in any Obſervance or Deference to the Synagogue, as a more Holy Place than another, that he went into it. But 'twas becauſe that <hi>then</hi> and <hi>there,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> were aſſembled in great Numbers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that was the time, and that the place of their Solemn and Numerous Aſſociations for their Divine Worſhip: And he could not find ſo fit an Opportunity any other day, nor ſo convenient a Room in any other place to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with them, to Preach the Goſpel to them, to prove <hi>the Lord Jeſus</hi> to be Gods promiſed, and their expected <hi>Meſſiah;</hi> to Convince them hereof, and to Exhort them to Believe on him, and Embrace him as ſuch, which his Zeal for Chriſts Glory, and his Love to their Souls, ſtrongly conſtrained him to. And this we aſſert, was <hi>the only cauſe</hi> of his ſo often, and ſo unuſal
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97175:35"/>going into their Synagogue on <hi>the Seventh day,</hi> without any Difference as to Time and Place; as if it were <hi>more holy</hi> than any other. We know how ardently he longed after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion and Salvation of his own Countrymen and Kinsfolk, according to the Fleſh; how fervently he panted after our Lord Chriſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acknowledged by them; as that which would be their greateſt Good, and his greateſt Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the World: For ſo his Enemies would become his Friends; his Baſphemers of him, as the worſt of Deceivers, would be turned to be his Praiſers, Adorers and Relyers on him; as the Son of God, the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Saviour of the World: And therefore this conſtrained him to apply himſelf to them in <hi>every Place,</hi> and at <hi>every Time,</hi> where he might diſcourſe with moſt of them, and with greateſt Freedom and Advantage. And if the <hi>Jews</hi> had convened on other Days, in other Places, in as great Crowds; he could doubtleſs then and there, have applyed himſelf unto them: And had they accuſtomed their Aſſemblies at any other time, or in any other place, he would have made it his Cuſtom and uſual Manner, to have aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them. The Reaſon that the Holy Ghoſt gives us of <hi>Paul</hi>'s going into the <hi>Jews</hi> Synagogues on the Seventh day, and making it his uſual Cuſtom, is no where ſaid, as I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>that he might Worſhip with them;</hi> much leſs, <hi>that he might obſerve the day</hi> with them; but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that he might <hi>Preach the Goſpel to them,</hi> and prove the Lord Chriſt to be their Meſſiah: Wherefore ſeeing the Holy Ghoſt tells us every
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97175:36"/>where, that this was his great Deſign, and this his great Work in their Synagogue: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it hence follows, That if he could not have had ſuch Advantages for this Work among them, he would never then nor there, have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with them: So far was he from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Reſpect, either to <hi>Time</hi> or <hi>Place,</hi> in this his Cuſtom, that he only made uſe of them, in a Subſerviency to his farther Deſign: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis very remarkable, and worthy our moſt diligent Obſervance, that when the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> had ſound the <hi>Jews</hi> given up ſo far to their curſed Blindneſs and Prejudice againſt the Lord Chriſt, that all his Pains he took with them, all the Affections he ſhewed he had for them, all the undeniable Demonſtrations from Scripture he produced before them, could prevail nothing with them, but rather they contradicted and blaſphemed. <hi>He forſook them and their Society, and turned to the Gentiles,</hi> Act. 13.45, 46. and doubtleſs, went into their Synagogues no more on the Seventh day. In other Places he did go into the <hi>Jews Synagogues</hi> after this, on the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day, as long as he had any hope of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in his Preaching the Lord Chriſt to them; but when he ſaw that they were gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally hardned, and took Advantage to ſpeak Evil of the Lord Chriſt, and his Doctrin be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore others, (the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) he turned away quite from them, and forſook their Synagogue; and made the School of a Heatheniſh Philoſopher, one <hi>Tyrannus,</hi> the common Meeting-place of his Auditors, <hi>Act.</hi> 19.8, 9. and ſo queſtionleſs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Day,</hi> as well as the <hi>Place</hi> of
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97175:36"/>his Preaching, and the Meeting of his Auditors: <hi>For</hi> after this, throughout all the remaining Book of the <hi>Acts,</hi> throughout the remaining part of <hi>this Chapter,</hi> and all the other <hi>Nine,</hi> you find not the leaſt Mention of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Preaching or Praying, or Aſſociating with any others <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Seventh day;</hi> neither could this Author produce, becauſe he could not find any ſuch Paſſage after this <hi>Eighth Verſe</hi> of this <hi>Nineteenth Chapter:</hi> Wherefore that Word of Mr. <hi>B.</hi> Pag. 45. Line 15. <hi>Continually,</hi> might well be omitted; for he did not continually go into the <hi>Jews</hi> Synogogue, on the Seventh day, but ceaſed from it, when his great Deſign thereof was fruſtrated; and never is ſaid more to do it, after this time: No, not at <hi>Rome,</hi> where he lived Two whole Years in a hired Houſe of his own, and might have appointed what day he would for the Collection of his Diſciples and Hearers. Is he ever ſaid to have called them together <hi>on the Seventh day?</hi> which I aſſert to be a clear Proof that he never did it before out of any Regard to <hi>that day,</hi> as more <hi>holy</hi> than other: And therefore this Diſcourſe of Two or Three <hi>Pages,</hi> and the particular Remarks which he makes upon this Practice of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in ſome few of the Chapters of the <hi>Acts,</hi> and the great Advantages he thinks he has for the Seventh day from them, are dwindled and vaniſhed into nothing. If he would have gotten any thing for his Cauſe, from this Practice of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> he ſhould have ſhewn theſe, or ſuch like Particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That St. <hi>Paul</hi> called his Auditors together upon that day; which he cannot do, for the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97175:37"/>Jews aſſembled themſelves thereon. 2. That he aſſociated himſelf with the Gentiles, and made their Religious Aſſemblies upon that day; but this he never reads. 3. That he did this perſeveringly, even when he turned from the Jews; but this he can never ſhew, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all this ſhew is but a ſhew. Beſides, we know St. <hi>Paul</hi> preached where-ever and whenever he found a convenient Auditory, in the School of <hi>Tyrannus, Acts</hi> 19.9. in the Market-place, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.17. on <hi>Mars-hill,</hi> v. 22. at the High Prieſts Bar, and before <hi>Feſtus</hi> and <hi>Agrippa;</hi> and as he made no diſtinction of places, ſo none of days, as to the preaching of the Goſpel (though as to the Churches ſolemn ſtated Worſhip he did, though not the Seventh day) and ſo theſe days and times have as much to plead for their Sanctity from the Apoſtles preaching on them, as the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth hath. But I ſuppoſe I have ſaid enough of this, to ſatisfie any unprejudiced conſidering Perſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 46. To his Queſtion we grant, that the Holy Scriptures do call no other day of the Week a <hi>Sabbath</hi> but the Seventh (though Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> ſhews, that one day of the Year is called a <hi>Sabbath day,</hi> whenever it falls out upon any other day of the Week, <hi>viz. Pentecoſt</hi>) and do not begrudge him all the Advantage he can take from hence. Thus (I hope) by Gods Aſſiſtance and Guidance, I have ran through all this Author's Arguments for his <hi>Sabbatarian Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> and if I deceive not my ſelf, have proved them to be very weak and ineffectual, as to the Edifying and Eſtabliſhment of it: And now I muſt proceed to try his Skill in plucking down,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97175:37"/>and to ſee if he be more Dextrous and Succeſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in defeating our Arguments againſt the <hi>Seventh day,</hi> and for the Sanctification of the <hi>Firſt day</hi> (which from henceforth I will take liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to call the <hi>Lords day</hi>) which he judges to be moſt weak and empty, even the Conjectural Miſtakes of the meaning of ſome Paſſages in Scripture; let us ſee whether he can prove them to be ſuch.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XII.</head>
               <p>THe firſt Objection againſt the <hi>Seventh day,</hi> and Argument for the <hi>Lords day,</hi> is <hi>Page</hi> 47. from the <hi>Reſurrection of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt upon that day,</hi> &amp;c. Againſt which he has nothing directly and particularly, but only hints the Differences of Opinions about the changing of the day; but all (ſave one) do agree, that it is changed, and reaſon would judge, that their univerſal concurrent Suffrages, ſhould weigh more for its Mutation, than their Differences about the Circumſtances thereof, ſhould againſt the Change of it. He anſwers, there is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Alteration of the <hi>Seventh</hi> into the <hi>First-day-Sabbath:</hi> And he expreſſes his meaning to be, not by any <hi>expreſs Precept;</hi> but we ſay there are other ways of Abrogating and Eſtabliſhing things in Scripture, than by expreſs Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or poſitive Injunctions; even by genuine Conſequences from Doctrins, from Examples of thoſe that are propoſed to our Imitation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And that the Sanctification of the <hi>Seventh day</hi> is as much abrogated in the Goſpel, and the <hi>Lords
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97175:38"/>day</hi> eſtabliſhed in its ſtead, as any of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Old Adminiſtration are. And I think we may challenge him to produce any one expreſs Command for the Aboliſhing of any one of the Jewiſh Ceremonies, or of all of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junctly; which becauſe we cannot find, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently we muſt ſtill look upon them to be in force, and keep them alive in the Chriſtian Churches, and theſe days of Reformation. I do verily believe, if my Judgment were ſway'd with ſuch Arguments againſt the <hi>Lords day,</hi> and for the <hi>Seventh,</hi> they would lead me back to all the Jewiſh Religious Worſhip, becauſe they were all as really commanded by the <hi>Second Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> (even all inſtituted Worſhip) as the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day</hi> is by the <hi>Fourth,</hi> both which are in themſelves <hi>poſitive,</hi> though referred to, and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually contained in the Moral Commands; yet he acknowledges the Abolition of <hi>theſe</hi> without an expreſs Command, and why not of this? Let him bring his Arguments from Scripture for the Abrogation of any of them, and I do verily believe we ſhall be able to uſe the very ſame for the Excluſion of the <hi>Seventh day.</hi> I know not any one particular Rite of the Old Teſtament, more particularly ſpoken of in the New Teſtament by the Apoſtle towards its Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion from the Chriſtian Church, than <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion;</hi> yet there is no expreſs Command againſt it that I know of: And I aſſert, that let him bring what Argument he can from theſe Epiſtles againſt it, I will produce the ſame againſt the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath,</hi> and ſo they muſt either ſtand or fall upon the ſame Ground, and ſo
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97175:38"/>muſt the other Ceremonies that are not ſo much as mentioned in the Books of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Again, here he recurs to the Danger and Preſumption of Indulging to <hi>Conjectures</hi> and <hi>Humane Fancies</hi> in the things of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any warrant from Scripture, or againſt the Commands thereof, under a pretence of honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God and Chriſt thereby, and unworthily applies all this to the Aſſertors of the <hi>Lords-day.</hi> But to this we have anſwered already, and doubt not but to be as Innocent in this Reſpect as himſelf; and this is the ſumm of all his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to this Argument for the <hi>Firſt-day-Sabbath.</hi> But we muſt not ſo leave it, but ſpeak what (I hope) God will direct to the Vindication of it: And here we muſt know, that this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not the ſolitary Proof that we bring for the <hi>Lords-day</hi>'s Holy Obſervation; for then it might ſeem to carry no great weight with it. But,</p>
               <p>Firſt, We undertake to prove <hi>an Abolition of the Seventh day</hi> from the Word, and then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>Firſt day,</hi> as bidding faireſt of all the other Week-days for it; becauſe we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge one day of the Seven to be the ſubſtance of the <hi>Fourth Commandment,</hi> and to be poſitively and ſecondarily Moral in it; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there lies ſtill an Obligation upon all the Churches unto the end of the World, to keep one day in ſeven Holy unto the Lord (at leaſt all who may have the Commands intirely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to them, and duly taught them, for there may be a caſe of Exemption in this particular, as we may ſee in the progreſs) and we ſay the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97175:39"/>Seventh day being caſhiered, the firſt day ought to be its ſucceſſor; and that becauſe of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Privileges of this day above all others of the Week; whereof this of our <hi>Lords Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> from the Dead is chief, becauſe this was the day of God the <hi>Redeemer</hi>'s entring into his <hi>Reſt.</hi> And our Argument for the Lords day is both <hi>a Pari &amp; a Majori;</hi> from Equality and Eminence; Equality with, and Eminency to, the Reſt of God the <hi>Creator</hi> upon the <hi>Seventh day;</hi> for as the Creators having finiſhed the Sixth days work and reſted the Seventh, was made a poſitive Motive for the Obſervance of that day for a religious Reſt, during all the time that <hi>Jehovah</hi> reſted from no other more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent work of his: So we ſay in like manner, the Reſt of God the Redeemer from that his greater work of Redemption on the firſt day, may be as good a Motive for the Conſecrating thereof to a religious Reſt; for here we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Seventh day excluded: Yea we argue <hi>a fortiori,</hi> and ſay it may much more upon this account challenges its Holy Obſervation. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Reſt of <hi>Jehovah</hi> after the works of the Creation, was no proper Reſt (as has been proved) but now his Reſt after the work of Redemption, was a real and proper one, from the Labours, Sufferings and Humiliation of his humane Nature. 2. The Work of Creation coſt God but ſix words of his Mouth; but the work of Redemption coſt him his Incarnation, and in his Manhood, his mean and contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Birth, his poor, obſcure, laborious Life, for
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97175:39"/>thirty Years together in his reputed Fathers Houſe, and probably at his Trade too; and after that his itinerant, weariſom, tempted, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached, perſecuted and ſad Life, for 3 or 4 Years before his Sufferings, and his compleat, voluntary and ſinleſs Obedience to his Fathers Will, all his days; and his fearful Sufferings, and moſt dreadful, ſhameful, painful, lingring and accurſed Death. 3. By the work of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion God brought all things out of nothing, and ſo could not poſſibly meet with any oppoſition thereto; but in the work of our Redemption he waded through and overcame all Oppoſition, all the Temptations of Men and Devils; all the Rage and Malice, the Revilings, horrible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, falſe Accuſations, unjuſt Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Men; all the Rage, Fury and Cruelty, of Earth and Hell, of Men and Devils: Yea, all the Wrath and Vengeance of his Father (which was infinitely worſe than all the former) and at laſt Death and the Grave. 4. By the Creation God brought our Nature out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; but by Redemption, from Satan, from Sin, from Death, from Hell, from the Wrath of God, and from the Grave. 5. By the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation God made us perfectly Holy and Happy; planted Paradiſe for us; gave us an Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and Abilities, and Inclinations, and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Obligations, ſo to remain for ever; but not the effectual Grace (for we ſpeedily fell) and an animal Life (for we were to eat and drink and ſleep in Innocency, to recruit the Decays of Nature) but by <hi>Redemption</hi> God brings us again into a perfect and more glorious State of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97175:40"/>Holineſs and Happineſs, conveys us into the third Heaven, gives us an eternal Security there, and makes us like the Angels for ever and ever; and doubtleſs our Condition in the third Heaven, where Redemption conveys and lodges us, will be as far more Noble, Glorious, Bleſſed and Happy, than our Condition in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, where Creation made and ſtated us, as that is in Situation above this. 6. God glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied his Power, Wiſdom and Goodneſs in the work of Creation; but much more all theſe in the work of Redemption (as might eaſily be diſplayed to the Reader) and withall, his Pity, his Grace, his Juſtice, his Holineſs, his Truth, his Jealouſie for his own Glory; more of Gods Glory ſhining forth in one Line of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemers Face, than in all the Creation both viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inviſible. Wherefore ſeeing this work of <hi>Redemption</hi> does ſo unconceivably ſurpaſs that of Creation, both as to <hi>Excellency,</hi> as wrought out by God; and as to its <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility</hi> to us, as wrought out for us; we ſay (with Reverence and without Offence) that the firſt day hath more to ſhew upon this account for its Holy Separation from, and Exaltation above, the reſt of the Week-days, than ever the Seventh had, or can pretend unto: And we ſay withall, that it is very Congruous, that God the Redeemer ſhould have one day of the Week conſecrated to his Reſt for 2000 Years in the latter days of the World; as well as God the Creator have a day throughout 4000 Years conſecrated to his Reſt: Eſpecially ſeeing that the Honour and Glory of the Redeemer herein, is the Glory and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97175:40"/>Honour of God the Creator, for both are the ſame <hi>Jehovah;</hi> whereas the Glory of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor herein, is not the Glory of the Redeemer; for the Redeemer was not when the Creation was produced, neither ſhould ever have been, had the Creation ſtood in that Eſtate wherein God created it, and reſted in his works: So that 'tis clear from hence, that 'tis not a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to honour the Lord Chriſt, that is pleaded for the firſt day; but 'tis <hi>really an Honour,</hi> a great Honour to the Redeemer, that it ſhould be dedicated to a holy Commemoration of his Reſt. That the Firſt-day-Sabbath hath the ſame Argument and Motive in this particular that the Seventh hath, even God's Reſting from his work; and herein a ſtronger, as far as the Glory and Profit of Redemption, excels that of Creation. I have been ſomewhat long here, and the Subject is very Glorious, Delightful and Profitable; and the Argument, with others, weighty and convincing, and ought not to be ſlightly paſſed over, how little ſoever is ſaid againſt it; the Author ſeeming to fancy he could blow it out of door with a puff.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIII.</head>
               <p>HE propoſes <hi>Page</hi> 49. our Argument from our Saviour's appearing to his Diſciples on the firſt day of the Week, for its being the day of Chriſtian and ſolemn Worſhip from <hi>John</hi> 20. to 26. To which he anſwers, all this
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97175:41"/>amounts not to an <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> but with other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, it bids fairly for it, and ſhews the Honour our Saviour put upon this day beyond all others. As to his other, 'tis replied, that 'tis probable, that firſt day ſpoken of in <hi>v.</hi> 19. here, may be the ſame with that ſpoken of <hi>Luke</hi> 24.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and 'tis probable 'tis not ſo, for our Lord appeared to his Diſciples on ſeveral Lord-days. But fairly to grant what he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get: Suppoſe it were ſo, could the two Diſciples, travelling to <hi>Emaus,</hi> and our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's coming to them, walking and converſing with them, any way diſparage this day, or weaken this Argument? Not at all. For 1. Theſe Diſciples were yet Unbelievers of Chriſt's Reſurrection, and ſo could have no thoughts of keeping a Firſt-day-Sabbath to the Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration thereof. 2. Their Journey to <hi>Emaus</hi> might be but a Sabbath-days Journey; It might be for religious Ends, and we know many among us do go and ride, or have gone or rid, ſeveral Miles to hear Sermons and receive Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments; and yet not be adjudged as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faners of the Lords day: And our Lord, by ſeveral Diſcourſes of his about, and Actions of his upon, the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> might well take them off from too ſcrupulous and nice Obſervation of the Lords day. 3. The Journey ſeems not to be ſo great, nor the diſtance between <hi>Emaus</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſo many Miles, as <hi>Geographers</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late: And therefore <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith (as Mr. <hi>Warren</hi> informs me) that they were miſtaken: And there ſeems a great probability thereof, becauſe 'tis ſaid, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.33. <hi>That they roſe up the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97175:41"/>ſame hour, and went to</hi> Jeruſalem; and came to the Congregation of the Eleven, and the other Diſciples, before ever they were diſmiſſed: And therefore 'tis very improbable that it ſhould be ſeven Miles and a half from that City, and much more probable that it was but a <hi>Sabbath-days Journey.</hi> 4. Our Saviour being riſen and entred into his Glory (at leaſt the firſt degree thereof) was now no longer ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Sabbath Obſervance, neither could he be a Profaner thereof, whatever he did thereon: And beſide, having a glorified Body, he might be with them in an inſtant upon the way, and ſo in a very ſmall particle of time return to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and all his Diſcourſe to them was moſt proper for the Holy Sabbath; opening to them the Scriptures, reproving them for their Unbelief, and making their Hearts to burn with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them: So that our Saviour's Diſcourſes and walking with them, do rather ſerve to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Firſt-days-Sabbath; and their going to <hi>Emaus</hi> no way to infringe it.</p>
               <p>As to that which is produced, <hi>Page</hi> 50. from <hi>John</hi> 20.26. he replies, that they might not be gathered together for <hi>religious Worſhip:</hi> For what elſe then? For fear of the Jews. A very probable Conjecture indeed! For if it had been only for fear, it had been ſafer to have been divided, and every one have hid and concealed himſelf in ſome Friends Houſe, or unſuſpected and ſafe place or other. But to be all aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled together in a ſuſpected Houſe (for the Text plainly hints, that was either in a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples Houſe, or ſome other uſual meeting place)
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97175:42"/>would be rather to expoſe themſelves; and to do this without any deſign of religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, would argue them very indiſcreet: But now 'twas their duty to meet together to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, though with hazard; and this they did, and ſhut the doors upon them, that they might not be diſturbed by the Jews. His denial of this ſecond Appearing to be on the Lords day, is taken from a Criticiſm about a Greek Prepoſition, which we tranſlate <hi>after:</hi> Now all that know any thing of that Language, know that their Prepoſitions are very <hi>Polyſemous,</hi> and admit of divers Interpretations, or include many of ours; and that two joyned to one Caſe of the following Noun, as this <hi>Meta</hi> does; for it might be rendred before the Accuſative, <hi>in, within,</hi> as well as <hi>after;</hi> and it might have been ſo tranſlated here, but they would render it by <hi>after;</hi> well knowing that even ſo rendred, it would no way alter the Senſe of the Holy Ghoſt; but according to Scripture Phraſe, ſtill intend the firſt day of the week following, according to the Expreſſion in <hi>Mark</hi> 8.31. <hi>After three days the Son of Man ſhall riſe again:</hi> Three days after he was killed he ſhould riſe again; for ſo the Text ſays expreſly, where the meaning muſt needs be upon the third day; and the Engliſh Tranſlation of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> render this place, <hi>within three days he ſhall riſe again</hi> And thought it well rendred according to the purport of <hi>Meta;</hi> which the Criticks tell us is uſually written and ſpoken by the <hi>Grecians</hi> in the meaning of <hi>in</hi> or <hi>upon:</hi> Other Tranſlation render <hi>Meta</hi> by an Adverb, and not by a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97175:42"/>as afterward in three days; and ſo in <hi>John,</hi> afterward in eight days; in which eight days are compriſed the firſt Lords day and the ſecond, as compleating the number; and ſo this ſecond meeting of Chriſt, and his Diſciples, was on the firſt day, as his Circumciſion was on the eighth day, which the Scripture expreſſes by another ſuch like Phraſe as this, <hi>When eight days were accompliſhed for the Circumciſion of the Child,</hi> Luke 2.21. As for his Evaſion of that paſſage in <hi>Mark,</hi> by telling us the ſame Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors think, that <hi>Mark</hi> reckons the time from his firſt being betrayed and apprehended. This no way helps him, for ſuppoſe he do ſo, yet his <hi>after</hi> muſt ſignifie <hi>upon,</hi> or on the third day, for 'tis clear that he was betrayed in the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing late of the ſixth day; for St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>chap.</hi> 18.3. that they came with Lanthorns and Torches to take him; and 'tis very probable, that that young Man who followed him with only a Linnen Cloth upon his Body, as he was immediately upon his Apprehenſion led to the High Prieſts Palace, <hi>Mark</hi> 14.51. was one ſtartled out of his Sleep and Bed by the rude Violence of the Souldiers, haling him through the Streets: Therefore this muſt be the former part of the ſixth day; in the latter part where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was Crucified, and laid in the Grave, in which he continued throughout the ſeventh, and out of which he roſe very early in the Morning of the firſt day: And ſo it could not be <hi>after,</hi> as he would fain have it, but <hi>upon</hi> the third day: And therefore without any danger of ſhaking the third days Reſurrection, our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97175:43"/>according to the uſe of Scripture, do thus interpret this Paſſage, and this Prepoſition: (See another expreſs place for this, where, <hi>after three days,</hi> is ſaid to be upon the third day, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 3.5, 12.) And becauſe it was our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's uſe to appear to them upon that day, even the firſt day: 'Tis ſtrange that he ſhould herein go againſt all the Criticks of that Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and againſt all the Senſe of all the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors that I can ſee, to ſerve his own Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis. 'Tis without doubt, that it was not upon the Seventh day that our Lord did now appear to his Diſciples; unleſs we will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it thus, after four or five days, after the eighth day he appeared to them: And thus he ſlily evades this other Argument for the Lords days Obſervance, even his Appearance to his Diſciples, when gathered together for religious Worſhip, which as I have ſhewed formerly, was not <hi>once</hi> only, but <hi>ſeveral times</hi> after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: And 'tis the only day of the Week which is named by all the four Evangeliſts, upon which our Saviour appeared to them, and graciouſly diſcourſed with them; no other day ſo much as mentioned, nor the Seventh ſo much as hinted, to be the day of his Perſonal Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of himſelf unto them; which is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther high Honour and Prerogative our Lord, and the King of the Church, has beſtowed upon this firſt day of the Week, and ſeems to be a practical and exemplary laying aſide of the Seventh day from being the weekly Sabbath-day, and ſubſtituting the firſt day to be that day conſecrated to the publick and ſolemn Worſhip
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97175:43"/>of God; and an Aſſurance that he will be in the midſt of his People aſſembling themſelves upon this his day; and will come and Bleſs them; which has been, and is, according to the Experiences of his People in their religious Devotions and publick Congregations, for there have they met, and do they ſtill meet him, in thoſe his Galleries: Then he brings them into his Wine-Cellar, and his Banner over them is Love: Then he gives them the raviſhing Kiſſes of his Mouth: Then they behold his Beauty in his Sanctuary, apprehend his Glory, Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence his gracious Power in and upon their Souls: Then they are abundantly ſatisfied with the Fatneſs of his Houſe, and drink delicious Draughts of the Rivers of Spiritual Pleaſures that flow therein: Then they experience that that firſt day of the Week in Gods Houſe, is inconceivably better to them, than all the days of the Week any where elſe, or about any other Imployment whatever. Wherefore we have juſt cauſe to hope, that our People will not, and perſuade them that they do not, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the Sanctification of the firſt day of the week, and their Aſſembling themſelves together on that Holy day. Seeing herein they follow the Examples of the Apoſtles themſelves, and the other Chriſtians in their days; and experience the Gracious Spiritual Preſence of our Lord in the midſt of them (as they did both his Carnal and Spiritual Preſence then) and turn aſide after the novel and ſingular Opinion of this Author, being alſo poorly grounded, as we have ſeen.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97175:44"/>
               <p>He proceeds <hi>Page</hi> 51. againſt that which ſome bring from <hi>John</hi> 8.56. <hi>Abraham ſaw my day,</hi> &amp;c. as the day of Chriſt's Reſurrection; and ſo the Firſt day of the Week: He ſays ſome would have it meant of his Birth-day, for the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of <hi>Chriſtmas;</hi> others all the days of his Fleſh; and the things which he did ſpeak and ſuffered, and our Redemption thereby, which I think to be a true Notion: But then to be ſure he muſt foreſee his Reſurrection, and ſo a day thereof; and this was the great Cauſe of his Joy and Gladneſs: Becauſe without this, there could be no cauſe of Gladneſs in all the reſt. For his Birth, Life and Death, could have brought no Glory to him, if he had ſtill layen in the Grave; nor Good, nor Profit to us, if he had not roſe out of it; but he would have been conquered by his Enemies, and we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever undone. But now his Reſurrection is for his own greateſt Glory, his Enemies Confuſion, and our Comfort and Triumph: This was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly <hi>our Lords day.</hi> He calls the day and time of his Sufferings, Luk. 22.53. <hi>the hour of his Enemies, and the power of Darkneſs:</hi> Becauſe then they inſulted over him, and he was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered into their Hands. But the time of his <hi>Reſurrection</hi> was <hi>his own day;</hi> becauſe he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Triumphed over all his Enemies, and had perfectly vanquiſhed them; and therefore this day muſt chiefly be intended by <hi>Abraham;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'twas the chief day of his, and all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Joy and Gladneſs: Though Mr. <hi>B.</hi> does not ſo much as once mention it in all thoſe Particulars he reckons up, under this Head.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:97175:44"/>
               <p>Moreover, <hi>Page</hi> 52.53. he mentions thoſe Texts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.22, 24. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.1, 11. where <hi>the day</hi> the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks of, <hi>which God hath made,</hi> ſome do interpret of the <hi>Reſurrection-day;</hi> and that therefore upon that day of the Week, Chriſtians or the Churches, ſhould go into the Houſes of Worſhip; and there praiſe the Lord, and adore him: And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.7. where the day of God's begetting his Son, is interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the day of <hi>Reſurrection:</hi> And there is very good reaſon, nay, there is Divine Authority for it; for it's applyed and appropiated to that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.33. So that the Text in the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> which ſpeaks of a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> beſides the Seventh day from the Creation; and that Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath or Reſt, which <hi>Jehovah</hi> brought <hi>Iſrael</hi> into, in the Land of <hi>Canaan;</hi> (which was to ſucceed, and as it were, to antiquate, and exclude the others) is by good and excellent Authors, underſtood of <hi>the Lords day;</hi> the Sabbath of the Firſt day. Who bring many excellent Arguments, for this their Interpretation and Opinion: Which Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſhould have Produced, Anſwered and Invalidated; and not put them off only by a bare Denial, or Calling them Shifts and Wind-laces: As though his only Rejection of theſe Paſſages, were enough to Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballance all the Arguments, and rational and ſcriptural Diſcourſes, which many good Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, Divines and Holy Men do draw from them, and give us upon them: And therefore ſeeing he ſaith nothing to Confute what they have ſaid, and I deſire to ſtudy Brevity, I ſhall ſpeak nothing more here, but only refer the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97175:45"/>to theſe Orthodox Authors themſelves; and Particularly to Mr. <hi>Warren,</hi> in whom he ſhall find very good Improvement of theſe Paſſages for the Lords day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 54. He mentions <hi>Act.</hi> 20.7. as an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection againſt the Authority of the Seventh day, and for that of the <hi>Firſt;</hi> and well he may: For 'tis an eminent one, and ſuch an one as he will find very difficult to anſwer; but yet we muſt expect the utmoſt of his Efforts to do it: I ſhall track his Endeavours. 1. He ſays we gueſs that he Firſt day of the Week, was that day we call <hi>Sunday;</hi> as though this were but a bare Gueſs: (as a Blind Man ſhoots the Mark, or catches the Hare; as the other Three Gueſſes, he ſays we make in the very next Paragraph.) But yet 'tis ſuch a Gueſs as he will not controvert; and we think 'tis be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cannot gain-ſay it: But yet this great Condeſcenſion to us, muſt be with a Grant from us to him, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a Keeper of the Seventh day, and an Obſerver of it as a Sabbath; and ſo for his granting us what he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, we muſt grant him what he can never prove; Yea, what we have denyed and ſtill do, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> was a Keeper of the <hi>Old Sabbath-day.</hi> We grant indeed (as before) that he Preached on that day uſually to the <hi>Jews</hi> in their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, becauſe he could have no other ſuch convenient Time and Place for it: But that he kept <hi>that</hi> Sabbath, we utterly deny. For then he would have done it among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as well as among the <hi>Jews;</hi> which yet we never read he did: Or if he ſaith he did, let him
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97175:45"/>prove it; which we are ſure from Scripture, he can never do: Nor after the former Chapter, that ever he did go ſo much as to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Synagogue (for this is all the Proof of his keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it) upon the Seventh day. But here we find that the Diſciples came together uon the Firſt day, and <hi>Paul</hi> came to them, and aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with them in Religious Duties: And why is the Firſt day now named, and the Seventh never after, as the Solemn, Dedicated Day to their Worſhip; but becauſe it was never ſo from that time? But yet this is not all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition upon which he will be ſo exceedingly kind to us, as to grant the Firſt day of the Week, to be Sunday or our Lords day; but it muſt be bought with another Information, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on what part of the Sunday 'twas that this Aſſembly was, and St. <hi>Pauls</hi> aſſociating in them; which he takes for granted, (and I am ſure does but gueſs that his Opponents do) that 'twas in the <hi>Evening</hi> after the Seventh day: Which he takes for the beginning of the Firſt day, and ſo <hi>Paul</hi> Preached till the <hi>Midnight;</hi> and brake Bread, and diſcourſed only till the Light of the Firſt day; but performed no Religious Duty upon the Morning of that day at all; but as ſoon as ever the firſt Day-light began to dawn, he betook himſelf to what was Profane, and Travelled. Which I think is a begging of the Queſtion; and in a ſcriptural Senſe, is to ſay, that he performed no Religious Duties at all thereon; for 'twas the <hi>Light</hi> that <hi>God called day,</hi> and the <hi>dakneſs he called night,</hi> Gen. 1.5 and ſo to contradict the expreſs words of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97175:46"/>Text. Beſides, I would fain know of him which is the chiefeſt part of a natural Day, either the dark part of it, which we with Scripture call Night, or the light part of it, which with it we call Day: If the light part (as I think an unprejudiced Mind will grant) why ſhould he ſuppoſe that all the Religious Duties of that Day, ſhould be done in the Dark thereof; and not in the Light?</p>
               <p>Again, we think that the Lords day did not begin at Even, but rather in the Morning, when our Lord roſe out of the Grave; that being the great occaſion of its Sanctification to ſacred Duties, and its being imployed therein by thoſe Diſciples and <hi>Paul.</hi> And for this we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Scripture, (I mean for the Firſt day of the Weeks beginning in the Morning) as <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.1. <hi>in the end of the Sabbath, as it began to dawn towards the Firſt day of the Week;</hi> where the Scripture determines the Sabbath to end with the Darkneſs of the Night, before the Firſt-day Morning; and the Lords day to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the dawning of the Morning of the Firſt day: So far is it from Truth, that the Evening and Night before the Morning of it, were part of that day; (at leaſt in this Scripture Phraſe) and hence we ſay that <hi>Paul</hi> began to Preach to them in the light part of that Day, as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning thereof; and continued with them till the following Midnight. Yea, throughout that Night, and ſo the next Morning being the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond day, on <hi>Monday</hi> took his Journy, as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per day for it: And now we have another of our Gueſſes, which is, that <hi>the breaking of bread</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:97175:46"/>here ſpoken of, was <hi>the Lords Supper;</hi> and we would fain know what other breaking of Bread ſhould be meant. Can it be imagined that all the Diſciples ſhould come together to Feaſt it with <hi>Paul,</hi> and that too in the Night-ſeaſon, as he would fain have it? They had Houſes of their own to Eat and Drink in, and they would doubtleſs rather chooſe to receive the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Bread from the Apoſtle, that day being the laſt he was to tarry with them; having as 'tis probable, no other Apoſtle, or Evangeliſt, or Paſtor with them at that time; than to eat common Bread, which they could do when they pleaſed in his Abſence: And the Sacrament is more ſuitable to the Society of Diſciples as ſuch, to the Preaching of the Word of God by the Apoſtle, than the feeding their Bodies. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſay, that ſeeing 'tis clearly here impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Diſciples gathered themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether uon this day, as upon the uſual time, and the Apoſtle miniſterially ſerved them then; 'tis very probable, (and more than a bare Gueſs) that this day was the uſual day; and ſo to be the future day of their Solemn and Religious Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Dedicated thereunto. As to what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the other Paragraph about Preaching and Reaſoning, we may with good reaſon paſs it over, ſeeing we can ſee in it but little to the preſent Caſe.</p>
               <p>Next by way of Conceſſion, he tells us that though this were a Religious Aſſembly, and <hi>the breaking of Bread was the Lords Supper,</hi> yet then all this is but <hi>once.</hi> But this is <hi>ſuch an once,</hi> as leaves the Seventh day for ever out of mention
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97175:47"/>from being the day of Aſſociation: <hi>Such an once,</hi> as clearly ſeems to imply the Cuſtom of the Diſciples, to be their Convention on the Firſt day: <hi>Such an once,</hi> as the Holy Ghoſt is pleaſed here, ſo particularly to mention, after he had ſhewed us before, that 'twas the uſual day of the Diſciples Religious Aſſociation, and our Saviours perſonal Preſence with them, and his gracious Diſcourſe to them: <hi>Such an once,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed now, (as no Meeting can be but once at a time) as with the former, makes more than once; and ſuch an once, as with what hath been ſaid, and what may be ſaid, will be of force e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough not to repeal a Law, or the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but only to alter a Circumſtance and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive therein; the whole Subſtance thereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in its full Vigour and Authority. <hi>Once</hi> he ſaith, occaſioned by <hi>Paul</hi>'s being to depart to Morrow. Which very Circumſtance, ſeems to me to be of ſome Moment againſt the Seventh, or for the Firſt day. For we may well ſuppoſe, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> had determined ſome days before the very day of his Departure; and therefore ſeeing he intended the Second day of the Week to be it, he might with much more Convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy have Met and Preached, and Adminiſtred the Lords Supper to the Diſciples on the Seventh day: If that had been now the Conſecrated day of the Week, and ſo have had more Time and Leiſure with them for his Work, and not have ſo ſtraitned himſelf, or incommoded them throughout a whole Night: But becauſt the Lords day was the ſacred day of the Week to be obſerved and kept, therefore he would defer it
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97175:47"/>till then; though to his own and their great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Inconvenience. Here we have a Conjecture ſomewhat ſtrange, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Apoſtle kept the Seventh day at <hi>Troas.</hi> What, was it alone by himſelf, and without any other with him? as a private Perſon, and not as an Apoſtle? and then would keep the Firſt day of the Week as an Apoſtle, and with the Aſſembly of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers? Doubtleſs St. <hi>Paul</hi> was no ſuch Diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler on one hand, nor Superſticious Bigot on the other; to obſerve Two Sabbaths in the Week, one by himſelf, and another with the Church; when God commands but one only. But he ſeems to do all he can to turn the Firſt day into the Seventh, and to perſuade us that the Aſſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Diſciples, was begun on the laſt day of the Week; and continued ſome time of the Firſt: Whereas the Text expreſly tells us, they came together on the Firſt day, and ſo continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together the Firſt day, till its Concluſion in the Second days Morning. Here he takes no notice at all, or to no purpoſe, that the Holy Ghoſt tells us expreſly, that <hi>Paul</hi> abode Seven days at <hi>Troas;</hi> of which one muſt neceſſarily be the laſt day, the Seventh day in order of the Week: And yet never tells us that the Diſciples met on that day, or <hi>Paul</hi> with them; but <hi>only on the Firſt day.</hi> And why ſhould this be (if for any reaſon) but to ſhew us that the Lords day was the day of their Religious Conventions; and the Seventh day antiquated and no more to be mentioned, and obſerved among Chriſtians as ſuch a day? What follows has been (if I miſtake not) ſatisfactorily anſwered already.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:97175:48"/>
               <p>'Tis well he recedes from and ſtands not much upon the Greek word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be interpeted <hi>one,</hi> for he knows that in both the Sacred Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, the Numerical word is frequently uſed for the Ordinal; and if we ſhould render this word here <hi>one,</hi> it would make the Language of the Scripture very Impertinent and Uncertain: It would be Impertinent and Superfluous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if it were upon any day, it muſt be upon one day of the Week, for there is no day that is not <hi>one</hi> of the Week; and what need the Holy Ghoſt to tell us that was, which we are ſure could not but be. And it would be uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and dubious, for according to this mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we could never know what day of the Week this religious Congregation met, whether on the firſt, or ſecond, or third, or fourth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Expreſſion ſeems to hint, that the Holy Ghoſt would acquaint us with the particular day thereof. But ſuch an uncertain Tranſlation would greatly befriend this Author, for then he might more confidently ſuppoſe it to be the <hi>Seventh day.</hi> Seeing that now when the Spirit clearly aſſerts it was upon the <hi>Firſt day,</hi> he does perſwade himſelf, and would perſwade us, that it was upon the <hi>Seventh.</hi> What fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows after, being Conjectures and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences drawn from his former weak Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, I ſhall ſay nothing more to them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:97175:48"/>
               <head>SECT. XIV.</head>
               <p>HE next propoſes, <hi>Page</hi> 58. the Objection againſt his Sabbath, and Argument for our Lords day, which is in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1, 2. which is taken (as we ſay) from the Collections for the Poor made in the publick Congregations <hi>on the firſt day of the Week,</hi> and does what he can to enervate it: Let us ſee how ſucceſsfully.</p>
               <p n="1">1. He tells us he knows not what the order to the Church of <hi>Galatia</hi> was: But St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells him plainly, that in this particular it was to collect Mony for the Poor on the Lords-day. 2. That he does not find written, that this order to that Church ſhould oblige all others. The like may be ſaid of all the other Orders and Directions given in Scripture, to all particular Churches therein mentioned and written to: For 'tis not there ſaid, that they are intended for all other Churches to the end of the World: Yet I hope he looks upon the Doctrins taught them, the Ordinance and Diſcipline eſtabliſhed amongſt them, to be Obligatory upon the Churches now. And we may well ſuppoſe, the Apoſtles being inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt in theſe Matters, in all their Conſtitutions of their prime Primitive Churches, to lay the Platform for all ſucceeding ones; except there may be ſome particular Circumſtance which may neceſſitate or allow a Deviation therefrom; which in this matter of Collection cannot well be pretended. 3. That it was a general order
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97175:49"/>for a charitable Sepoſition, but no order to obſerve the firſt day: True indeed, but it does imply the Obſervance of that day, elſe why ſhould it be enjoyned on that day more than on another, but becauſe thereon publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies met? 4. 'Tis an Order, he tells us, for a profane Employment, as to caſt up their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts on that day, and to tell their Mony they have got, and to reckon up how much their Stock is increaſed; for he here ſuppoſes a Man muſt on this day look over all his Stock, caſt up all his Charges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But certainly this is a pretty far fetch'd Invention, for they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded only to lay up by them on the Lords-day, what God had graciouſly enabled them to give to the Poor, by his Succeſs on their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and his providential Bleſſing on them, as to Earthly things; which they might very well enquire into the day before, even the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth; and having then diſcovered how God had ſucceeded them, the next day, even the Lords-day, to ſeparate that charitable Portion from the reſt, and carry it unto the publick Aſſembly, and ſo caſt it into the Poors Box. And I think 'tis clear, that the Text neceſſarily implies a former Inquiſition into their Stock, before this Sepoſition; but where it implies it muſt be done on that day, no Man can ſee. Wherefore we ſay, that a former Examination being had of theſe Matters, this day that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated part was taken, carried to the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and put into the common Stock; that ſo the Apoſtle, when he came amongſt them, might not be forced to go from Houſe to Houſe
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97175:49"/>to gather, but find it all ready in the publick Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Treaſure. I am ſure he can bring no Demonſtration from the Text for his, or againſt my Interpretation: But then I have the Teſtimony of the moſt ancient Fathers, that on the firſt day they publickly aſſembled; and then they made Collection for the Poor in theſe Aſſemblies. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, If the Apoſtle here enjoyned ſuch a profane or worldly Task as he ſuppoſes; why does he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn them to do it on the <hi>Firſt days,</hi> ſeeing it might have been done as well n every day of the Week, and better on the <hi>Sixth day?</hi> If the <hi>Seventh</hi> were then their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> that ſo they might know, at the end of the common days, what they might well and gratefully ſpare of that weeks Gains, and ſo lay it up againſt the enſuing <hi>Sabbath</hi> for the Poors Stock. Whence we ſee that this ſuppoſed Solution to this Argument, has no ground at all from the Text, and to be ſure from no other Topick: And therefore conclude, that the General Collections, and ſo Aſſociations of the <hi>Galatian</hi> Church, being on the <hi>Firſt day;</hi> And the Appoſtle commanding the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> to make the ſame Collections on that day in Imitation of them, or as they did; is, with the former, a very good Evidence, that that day was the inſtituted day for Worſhip, and ſo conſequently the <hi>Seventh</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 60. That Proof for the <hi>Firſt-day-Sabbath</hi> in <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.9, 10. where that day which St. <hi>John</hi> calls the <hi>Lords-day,</hi> we ſay was that day of the week, which we will by no means grant; but tells us what the Opinions of ſome ſingular Perſons were concerning it; that it was Annual, not a
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97175:50"/>weekly day; either the day of <hi>Chriſt's Birth,</hi> or of his <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> either <hi>Chriſtmas-day</hi> or <hi>Eaſter:</hi> Others ſay 'tis a great providential day to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate his Kingly Authority; and others, the laſt day of his coming; but how this day, whereon St. <hi>John</hi> was in the Spirit, ſhould be a <hi>future</hi> day, can hardly be conjectured; but every thing muſt be hinted, that may ſeem to ſerve to an Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of the <hi>Firſt day</hi> of the week from being the day of this glorious Viſion. But at length it is granted, that ſome take this <hi>Lords-day</hi> to be a weekly day: But then again theſe ſome are crum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled into a Sub-diviſion, and ſome of them aſſert it to be the <hi>Firſt day,</hi> and ſome the <hi>Seventh day</hi> thereof; and this is written, as though the Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the <hi>Firſt day</hi> were as ſmall a ſome, as thoſe of the former annual Opinion, of a future day to <hi>John</hi>'s Viſion, and of the laſt day of the Week: Whereas I dare to ſay, put them all together, they will not amount to the hundredth part of thoſe ſolid and learned Authors, which underſtand it of the <hi>Firſt day</hi> of the week; but withall theſe ſome for the <hi>Seventh day,</hi> as inconſiderable for number as they are, in compariſon of the other, yet they are far better founded, and proceed upon more certain and undeniable Grounds than the <hi>Firſt-day-Men</hi> do; for they proceed upon <hi>Scripture,</hi> but theſe have only <hi>Tradition,</hi> if they have that for their Opinion. Now the Tradition which is pleaded for the <hi>Firſt day</hi> to be the <hi>Lords-day,</hi> is conſtant, uninterrupted, and univerſal, from the days of the Apoſtles: The Generality of Chriſtians acknowledging the Dominical day to be the Firſt day, whatever Opinion they had
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97175:50"/>of the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> till of late Years, ſome <hi>Sabbata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> have thought fit to queſtion it, and virtually (if not expreſly) to deny it. Which is ſuch a Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as upon which their very Scriptural Proofs are grounded; for 'tis from Tradition that they know the meaning of the very words of the Scripture. Whether the Original Languages carry the Senſe they are interpreted in; and whether we have the genuine and proper Significations of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals, can be known by nothing but Humane Tradition; for either it muſt be had from Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations, or Lexicons, or oral Traditions: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the <hi>Sabbatarians</hi> will renounce here ſuch a Tradition as is pleaded; they muſt withall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their own Scriptural Authority, which courſe will make wild work in the Church.</p>
               <p>He very well denies it to be <hi>Chriſtmas-day,</hi> or any annual one; but the great Query is, <hi>What day of the Week this was;</hi> and here in the entrance of his Diſcourſe, he endeavours to invalidate the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Tradition of the Churches for 1600 Years, by an Induction of other unlawful Traditions; as that of <hi>Polygamy</hi> among the Patriarchs; of whom the Scripture mentions but a few parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars; and what is that to the Univerſality of Chriſtians? And which was condemned by our Saviour as alien from the firſt Inſtitution of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage:</hi> And how does this reſemble the <hi>Firſt days</hi> being the <hi>Lords-day,</hi> which was never blamed by him? The like he mentions in the Omiſſion of the Feaſt of Booths; and the Cuſtom of the Profana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Seventh-days-Sabbath</hi> before the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity: But theſe were againſt expreſs Injunctions and Commands, ſtill in force and obliging; which
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97175:51"/>we deny the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> to be; and avouch, and may yet more prove its Abolition, as of other poſitive and ceremonial Commands, without any expreſs or literal Prohibition of them in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. What therefore he ſaith, in the following Paragraph, would be very cogent and undeniable; If he could prove the Seventh day of the week to be ſtill enjoyned by the Fourth Command, which he hath not yet done by his poſitive Proofs for his own Opinion, (as we have ſeen) nor by his Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, in denying of ours, (as has been in ſome meaſure ſeen already, and may be more hereafter.) At length he comes to give us his own Judgment concerning this <hi>Lords-day,</hi> what day of the Week it was; and if he had not told us, we ſhould have preſumed that it determined for the <hi>Seventh-day,</hi> (which in all things till the end of the World muſt have the Preheminence according to his thoughts) but withall 'tis grounded upon Scripture, which we will candidly and fairly weigh and examine. 1. That the Lord Chriſt inſtituted the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> juſt after the Creation, he means too before the Fall, quoting <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. begin. which we utterly deny, becauſe <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> then was not, nor could be, (we ſpeak of his <hi>Exiſtence,</hi> not Gods Foreſight and Decree) for then Man was Guiltleſs and Sinleſs, and ſo needed no <hi>Jeſus,</hi> nor could have had one: But in all theſe Old Teſtament Proofs he runs upon that former <hi>Fallacy</hi> of <hi>Ill Compoſition;</hi> taking for granted that whatever <hi>Jehovah</hi> did, the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> did. <hi>Jehovah,</hi> the Godhead of our Saviour, did create and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath,</hi> but not Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; which neceſſarily includes both the Godhead
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97175:51"/>and the Manhood: And therefore the Premiſes being falſe, the Concluſion cannot be true; nor the conſequential Diſcourſe thereupon of any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. His ſecond and third Arguments laboring under the ſame Miſtake, admit of the ſame An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: Beſides, we know that the poſitive and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial Precepts of <hi>Jehovah</hi> before his Incarnation, were to be aboliſhed by himſelf after his Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that is, by our <hi>Lord Jeſus;</hi> and others more Eaſie, Clear and Effectual, introduced in their room, (whereof we aſſert the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> to be, which he can never prove to be Moral, and ſo was to be excluded with them) and a new Time, as well as new Rites, inſtituted by the King of the Church.</p>
               <p>His next Argument to prove his Aſſertion, is from thoſe Paſſages, wherein 'tis ſaid, <hi>The Son of Man is Lord even of the Sabbath-day,</hi> Matt. 12.8. Mark 2.28. Luke 6.5. A Proof which we make uſe of to prove our Doctrin of the <hi>First-day-Sabbath,</hi> and he thinks makes clearly and ſtrongly for his. Though there may be ſome ground for the Opinion of ordinary Men, being meant by the <hi>Son of Man</hi> in theſe Texts; becauſe 'tis the Appellation which the Holy Ghoſt uſually gives them, calling them <hi>Sons of Men;</hi> and when he ſpeaks to <hi>Ezekiel</hi> particularly, his uſual Expreſſion is <hi>Son of Man:</hi> And St. <hi>Mark</hi> relating the ſame Hiſtory, of the Diſciples gathering Ears of Corn on the <hi>Sabbath-day;</hi> and the Phariſees being ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalized thereat, and complaining to our Lord Chriſt that they did that which was not Lawful; as the occaſion of this ſaying of our <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> (which the other Evangeliſts relate alſo, and no other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97175:52"/>of it is recorded in them, neither do we find that he uſed it at any other time) ſeems to carry it in this Senſe; for he ſaith <hi>Mark</hi> 2.27, 28. that Chriſt ſaid unto theſe Cenſurers, <hi>The Sabbath was made for Man, and not Man for the Sabbath:</hi> And then immediately adds this Sentence with an Illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <hi>Therefore the Son of Man is Lord alſo of the Sabbath.</hi> I ſuppoſe no Man will deny but that the firſt Verſe is meant of ordinary (I mean) meer, Men; for 'tis brought by our Lord Chriſt as a Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Diſciples action, who were meer Men; and not of any one of his own, who was God as well as Man. Withall I believe that we cannot find in all the Scripture, that appellative <hi>Man,</hi> thus <hi>abſtractly</hi> and <hi>abſolutely</hi> uſed, without any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction or Limitation, antecedent or conſequent to it; underſtood of any but of <hi>meer Men,</hi> which being granted the Illative <hi>therefore,</hi> ſeems to carry the next Sentence for the ſame Subject, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that <hi>Man,</hi> common Man, is <hi>Lord of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath;</hi> not an authoritative Lord to diſpoſe of it as he pleaſes, and do on it as he liſts; but ſo far a <hi>Lord,</hi> as to be <hi>the end of the Sabbath;</hi> for whoſe Profit and Comfort it was ordained. As a Son may be ſaid to be Lord of that Houſe that is built for him; and in which he dwells and uſes for his Convenience and Delight; though his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obliges him not to ſell or alienate it; and the Laws of the Land not to burn it.</p>
               <p>Though therefore this Interpretation of the <hi>Son of Man</hi> be no way Heterodox, nor any way ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, from this Text; neither do we by this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, give a <hi>meer Man</hi> a Lordſhip over the Moral Law, as he ſuppoſes, (for his taking for
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97175:52"/>granted, that the <hi>Laſt-day-Sabbath</hi> is Moral; I look upon as his Fundamental Error; and the great cauſe of his Miſtaken Confidence in all this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe:) We ſay that in no reſpect Man is <hi>Lord</hi> over any of the <hi>Moral Law;</hi> not in this that we ſpeak of; for Man was made for the Moral Law, that is, to perform all the Duties thereof; but now Man is <hi>Lord over the Sabbath</hi> (as our Lord avouches) in this reſpect, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was made <hi>for him,</hi> and therefore cannot be Moral, (as before,) But yet I ſay let it be granted, that 'tis ſpoken preciſely of our <hi>Lord Chriſt:</hi> Likewiſe we grant that the <hi>Sabbath</hi> ſpoken of in theſe Texts was the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath,</hi> and that our <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> as <hi>the Son of Man,</hi> that is, ſuch a Son of Man as is alſo the Son of God; is <hi>Lord of the Sabbath;</hi> (we ſhould have obſerved before to eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate all his Proofs drawn from the Old Teſtament, to prove the Seventh day of the Week to be the <hi>Lord's day</hi> here ſpoken of; that <hi>he,</hi> who is here called the <hi>Lord of the Sabbath,</hi> is ſaid to be the Son of Man, which he was not <hi>then.</hi>) Wherefore being ſuch an one, it cannot be denied but that he is an <hi>Abſolute Lord</hi> of the Sabbath, without Limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſo hath power to alter and change the day (which is no way Moral, I mean not the Seventh day at all) and ſo to make that to be lawful on the Seventh day, which before was not; even all ſorts of honeſt Imployments of our particular Callings, as well as charitable Actions; for when the day ceaſes to be Holy, and another advanced to that Honour by his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; then being a common day, common works are proper for it, which may ſeem to be the proper Intention of this Expreſſion to the Jews; for when
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97175:53"/>they blamed him as a Tolerator of the Profanation of the Sabbath by his Diſciples, he takes a <hi>double Medium</hi> to refute their Slander; the one as a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor and Prophet of the Church; and ſo he teaches them, that that charitable Action of theirs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward their own Nature, was no Breach, but an allowed work of that day; and proves it by a Scriptural Preſident; and ſo vindicates his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Action from Sin: Wherefore ſuppoſing (as this Author does) that our Saviour had no other deſign but to vindicate his Diſciples, this had been abundantly enough, and he needed not to recur to his own Anthority over that day; which he does, and ſo uſes <hi>another Medium;</hi> as a Lord and King of the Church, and ſo of all the Inſtitutions, and particularly of the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath,</hi> (for which they were as Zealous as the Author, as neceſſary and permanent) and ſays he himſelf, is <hi>Lord of the Sabbath;</hi> and ſo had Authority to abrogate that day, or eſtabliſh it as he pleaſed; which ſeems to imply this much: You are ever and anon carping at my Diſciples, and eſpecially at me, as though their, and mine, Actions, were Profanations of the Sabbath: But I would have you to know, that I have a Sovereignty over it, and can diſpoſe of it as I pleaſe; and make things that are not Lawful on the Seventh to be Legitimate: Which we look upon as a hint of its Abrogation ſhortly after.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially conſidering what Chriſt did, or cauſed to be done on that day in another place, <hi>viz. John</hi> 5.8. where having cured the impotent Man at the Pool of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> he commands him to riſe, <hi>to take up his Bed, and walk:</hi> Now we know that <hi>bearing of Burdens on the Sabbath day,</hi> is expreſly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97175:53"/>forbid, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.21, 22, 24, 27. and there are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes made unto them, that would obey that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and bear no Burdens; and Threats de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt them that ſhould contradict it; ſerving to conſirm the Defence of bearing Burdens on that day. Accordingly <hi>Nebemiah</hi> was ſtrict in its Obſervance, <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.19. and the Jews them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were very nice in this particular, and very ſevere in their Puniſhment of ſuch Bearers, by Whipping and by Death, (as that great Hebraick Critick Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi> informs us.) Yet here our Lord expreſly commands the Healed Perſon to take up his Bed and walk, that is, to carry it either to his own Houſe, or to ſome other convenient place; for ſo he did in obedience to this Command, <hi>v.</hi> 10. Whereat the Jews were very highly offended, and condemned it as an unlawful Act, and ſought to perſecute and kill Chriſt for enjoyning of it, <hi>v.</hi> 16. Now we would enquire, to what end our Lord Chriſt did enjoyn this Perſon to carry ſuch a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den on the Sabbath? If it be ſaid, it was to try his Faith and Obedience, or clearly to evince the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his miraculous Cure, or both of theſe: 'Tis replied, that theſe things could be as well done <hi>without the carriage of his Bed:</hi> He might have gone every where, and proclaimed his Cure, and his Reſtorer; he might have done it by leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, dancing and praiſing God; as the Cripple in <hi>Acts</hi> 3. Wherefore 'tis probably apprehended by learned Men, that it was a practical Proof of his being Supream Lord of the Sabbath, and of his Authority to change the old day into another of his own appointment, and this was a real blow begun to be given to it.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:97175:54"/>
               <p>Beſides all that was ſaid againſt theſe his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the Seventh day, to be <hi>the Lords day</hi> meant in the <hi>Revelation:</hi> 'Tis obſervable that the Greek word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is uſed but once more in the New Teſtament; and that is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. where the Sacrament of our Saviours Body and Blood is called <hi>the Lords Supper;</hi> in which it is clear, it ſignifies both his <hi>Authoritative</hi> Inſtitution thereof, and that his own Death is ſignified thereby: The Lord is both the Inſtitutor thereof, and his Death the thing commemorated thereby: And therefore Reaſon, and comparing Scripture with Scripture, would require that it ſhould be ſo underſtood here alſo; even as <hi>a day of his own Inſtitution,</hi> as the <hi>Son of Man:</hi> For ſo he appeared to <hi>John</hi> to be in the Viſion. And ſo St. <hi>John</hi> calls him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.13. and ſo a day for his own Commemoration, even of his <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> viz. <hi>the Firſt day of the Week;</hi> which none deny to be that day. And 'twas on that day whereon the Author of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> ſaw <hi>the Lord Jeſus walking in the midſt of the Golden Candleſticks, with the Seven Stars in his Right Hand;</hi> that is, with his Orthodox and Zealous Miniſters, receiving their Light and Heat from him, the Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; And then diffuſing it abroad in the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or in the midſt of the Congregations; which we know the Orthodox Fathers, throughout all Ages of the Church, have principally done upon <hi>the Firſt day of the Week,</hi> the day of the <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection:</hi> And ſo the future Practice of the Church, proves <hi>the Lords day</hi> to be the Firſt day of the Week. Again, St. <hi>John</hi> calls <hi>this</hi> the Lords day, <hi>after his Reſurrection;</hi> and our Saviour tells him Verſe 18. <hi>I am he that liveth and was dead,</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97175:54"/>I live forevermore:</hi> Implying, that as after his Incarnation, Obedience, Death, Reſurrection, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion, Seſſion on the Right Hand of God, and Miſſion of the Holy Ghoſt; all the former carnal and ceremonial Adminiſtrations vaniſhed, and a new <hi>Government,</hi> new external Modes of Worſhip, were introduced, which were properly <hi>the Lords</hi> and bear the Stamp of his Authority, <hi>as Mediator,</hi> as God-Man, over the Church and all her Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances: So <hi>this was alſo the Day of his own Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> after his Humiliation and Exaltation, for the Celebration of his new Inſtitutions; the other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing excluded with the former Appendixes thereto. What follows under this Head, being what has been ſpoken to before, and is frequently inculca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as of great Moment for him) as the Moral Law, as the now changing of the Sabbath; meer Pretences of the other party, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as being but a little better than the begging the Queſtion, and taking that for granted, which we utterly deny: Theſe I tacitly paſs by, and leave the Judicious Reader to judge, if after all has been ſaid, it be not far more probable that <hi>the Lords day,</hi> ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelations,</hi> is the Firſt day of the Week; (as all Schollars and Churches almoſt, have hitherto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved) than the Seventh day thereof, which a very few, ſcarce deſerving the Title of Number, have pitched upon, as a Prop to their tottering Seventh-day-Sabbath.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:97175:55"/>
               <head>SECT. XV.</head>
               <p>THere are other Texts which he produces, <hi>Page</hi> 69.70. as <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5, 6. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.9, 10, 11. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16, 17. from whence we hold and contend <hi>the Seventh day,</hi> to be everlaſtingly <hi>excluded</hi> from the Chriſtian future Sabbath; the chief being the Two latter of theſe. We ſay in <hi>Gal.</hi> by <hi>Days</hi> are meant the Jewiſh <hi>Seventh day;</hi> becauſe the Apoſtle mentions their <hi>Months,</hi> that is, their Obſervance of the New-Moon Feſtivals; <hi>Times:</hi> Which ſome apply to <hi>Eaſter, Pentecoſt, Feaſt of Tabernacles,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Years;</hi> which ſome think is meant of the year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Feaſt of Atonement and Expiation. Or it may be underſtood of the year of <hi>Jubilee,</hi> (if not <hi>the Great Jubilee</hi> every Fiftieth year, yet the leſs of every Seventh year;) which St. <hi>Paul</hi> probably ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved them very Superſtitious in: But whatever the Difference may be in the particular Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of theſe Terms, yet they generally hold, <hi>the more rare or ſeldom Jewiſh Feſtivals</hi> to be meant; and by <hi>Days</hi> then, what other Feſtival of the <hi>Jews</hi> can be underſtood, but <hi>the Seventh day?</hi> If he do not mean their Weekly Sabbath by <hi>Days,</hi> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well be conceived what it ſhould be: We doubt not but by the latter Three Expreſſions, <hi>Months, Times</hi> and <hi>Years,</hi> are meant Jewiſh Feſtivals: And why Days ſhould not ſignify the ſame, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well be imagined. Beſides, we find that theſe <hi>Galatians</hi> were greatly infected with the falſe Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Judaical Doctors, who taught them to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> &amp;c. as is ſeen clearly by the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:97175:55"/>Epiſtle, and ſeems to be the chief occaſion of Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it; to turn them from, and ſortify them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, ſuch falſe Doctrins, and dangerous Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances. And therefore hence we conclude St. <hi>Paul</hi> condemns the <hi>Galatian</hi> Church, for keeping <hi>the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth-day-Sabbath,</hi> as well as other Judaical Rites and Feſtivals; and tells them <hi>he is afraid he had beſtowed his labour in vain upon them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In that Text to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> we have the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of <hi>Sabbaths</hi> expreſly ſpken of; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by St. <hi>Paul</hi> diſcarded from their Obſervance, as <hi>Shadows,</hi> which were to <hi>vaniſh</hi> when <hi>Chriſt the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> was come: By which we contend, is meant <hi>the Weekly-Sabbath;</hi> becauſe that in the Scripture, is Chiefly, Moſtly, if not Solitarily the Acceptation thereof: And we have heard him again and again, aſſerting that 'tis the Intent of this Word <hi>every where.</hi> And I believe ſo, whenever it ſtands <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely,</hi> as here without ſome Annexion or other to alter its Signification. And what Reaſon can be given why here it ſhould not ſo be underſtood? that <hi>only here,</hi> and no place elſe in the Bible, it ſhould not be taken for <hi>the Weekly-Seventh-day?</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, here the Apoſtle ſeems plainly to intend their <hi>Annual, Monthly,</hi> and <hi>Weekly Feſtivals;</hi> their <hi>Annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,</hi> by <hi>Holy days;</hi> their <hi>Monthly,</hi> by <hi>New Moons;</hi> and ſo their <hi>Weekly,</hi> by <hi>Sabbaths:</hi> And there was no Weekly Feſtival, but the Seventh-day-Sabbath. Or if by <hi>Holydays</hi> we apprehend the <hi>Generality of Jewiſh Feſtivals,</hi> becauſe they were all Holydays as long as their Firſt Inſtitution laſted; yet then he condeſcends to ſome Particulars of them, as the <hi>Monthly</hi> and <hi>Weekly,</hi> which then muſt neceſſarily include the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> becauſe <hi>that</hi> was <hi>a Jewiſh Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:97175:56"/>Yet again, If we ſhould grant, that under the laſt word <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> any other Feſtivals may be included or meant: Yet certainly <hi>the Weekly-Sabbath</hi> cannot be <hi>excluded,</hi> being the <hi>most famous Analogate</hi> comprehended under it; and therefore in ſuch an Expreſſion, cannot be excepted; though ſometimes the moſt famous Analogate be only meant, and excludes all others; yet never is it it ſelf not intended in ſuch Propoſitions. Withal, as we ſaid before of <hi>the Galatian</hi> Church, ſo we do of the <hi>Coloſſian;</hi> 'twas infected by falſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that would make <hi>a Mixture of the Jewiſ,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> and would have <hi>Moſes's Rites</hi> to be kept with <hi>Chriſt's Ordinances:</hi> And they know well enough, that by Sabbaths was meant the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day; ſeeing 'tis always ſo accepted. Whence we may well conclude, that here is an expreſs exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Seventh-day-Sabbath out of the Church of Church. Heretofore we were called upon to ſhew one Text <hi>in which the Seventh-day-Sabbath was abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated,</hi> and now we bring an expreſs literal one; yet it will not do, but many Objections are brought in againſt it: Which we ſhall ſucceſſively conſider and traverſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some think it muſt be underſtood of <hi>Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial</hi> Sabbaths only; becauſe elſe 'twould reach the Firſt-day-Sabbath, as well as the Seventh. But there is no fear of that, for <hi>the Firſt day is never called Sabbath in the Scripture;</hi> and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be meant; and wee ſay the Seventh-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, was both poſitive and ceremonial, for he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf allows it to ſignify the eternal Reſt above. 2. He Objects that one place names no Sabbath, but only <hi>Days;</hi> the other indeed names <hi>Sabbaths,</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:97175:56"/>(which he would have interpreted <hi>Weeks,</hi> for which I can ſee no Reaſon; but much againſt it; and therefore ſhall ſay nothing till he produce his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for it.) And all the weight of this Argument is but a ſilly Conjecture of the meaning of the word Sabbaths: But we have ſeen before, that this is not a ſilly Conjecture, but grounded upon the very uſual Acceptation of the Word, upon the Connection of the adjoyned things, upon the State of the Churches unto whom he writ; and upon the deſign of his Epiſtles to them. But I am ſure what follows, is not ſo much as a Conjecture, but a very great Overſight; for he tells us, that he finds the word <hi>(Sabbaths)</hi> in the Plural Number, <hi>no where</hi> in the New Teſtament aſcribed to <hi>the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day.</hi> It was then becauſe he would not be at the pains to ſind it; for 'tis in all theſe places, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.5, 10, 12. <hi>Mark</hi> 3.4. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.31. and 6.2, 9. In all theſe places he will find it ſo; and in the Original Greek, the word is <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> without a Verbal Superaddition of <hi>days;</hi> which he himſelf muſt be inforced to acknowledge, ſpoke of this day.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Seventh day he faith was never in Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in any of theſe Epiſtles, and if there be no ſuch Queſtion about altering it, how can ſuch a Senſe be impoſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Juſt ſo I may ſay the <hi>New-Moon</hi> Obſervation, and the <hi>Annual Feſtivals,</hi> are no where queſtioned in theſe Epiſtles; (nor any where elſe that I remember, expreſly to be lain aſide) How therefore can ſuch a Meaning be put upon <hi>Years</hi> and <hi>Months,</hi> as to include the Judaical? ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sabbaths are as plain and clear for the Seventh days, as any of the former, for what they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97175:57"/>here. We have ſtill the Thred-beaten Plea of the <hi>Moral Law</hi> introduced and improved; when I aſſert, that neither he nor all the World can ever prove the Seventh-day-Sabbath to be part of the Moral Law, <hi>Quatenus Moral.</hi> His Fourth Anſwer plainly confounds <hi>Sabbaths</hi> with <hi>Years</hi> and <hi>New-Moons;</hi> which the Apoſtle clearly diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and of all the reſt I may truly ſay, they are but meer ungrounded Conjectures, to baffle an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Text of Scripture: But here he has a very ſtrange Fancy, That by <hi>Days</hi> may be meant <hi>the Firſt day;</hi> becauſe the Heathen worſhiped the Sun on that day: And ſo then <hi>every day;</hi> becauſe the Heathen worſhiped diſtinct Idols every day: And ſo we ſhould have no Conſecrated day at all, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Firſt</hi> nor Seventh, nor any other. All the reſt that follows here, are but (as he expreſſes) <hi>his own Thoughts,</hi> and as well grounded, as that Thought of his, <hi>That the Firſt day was not obſerved by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians:</hi> When yet we have found them ſeveral times aſſociated on that day; and Chriſt appearing ſeveral times in the midſt of them; and at <hi>Troas</hi> Aſſembled on that day; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> Preaching and Adminiſtring the Lords Supper to them, and therein to Harmonize with the Church of <hi>Galatia;</hi> (which I ſuppoſe proved againſt Objections) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which can be ſaid concerning the Seventh day: Only there were Aſſemblies of the Jews on that day; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> took the Advantage on theſe days to Preach to them. But what is this to Chriſts Diſciples and Followers? We may therefore (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own Rule, <hi>That which appears not, is not at all</hi>) conclude, that <hi>the Seventh day was never obſerved by the Diſciples and Followers of Chriſt, after his
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:97175:57"/>Reſurrection, as a day conſecrated to Publick Worſhip;</hi> becauſe we never read in the Scripture, that they did ſo meet. Whereas the contrary is ſeen by <hi>the Firſt day.</hi> So I diſmiſs this Thought, and the others as no more likely.</p>
               <p n="5">5. He farther ſaith that 'tis <hi>uncertain,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>as ſuch,</hi> I or'e look it. 6. He ſaith from <hi>Paul</hi>'s conſtant keeping the Seventh-day-Sabbath, that he cannot be ſuppoſed to condemn his own conſtant Practice: But how he did this, we have already ſeen; and therefore ſhall not ſtop here. 7. That St. <hi>Paul</hi> commends the <hi>Whole Moral Law, as Juſt, Holy and Good;</hi> and therefore can never be thought to condemn it here. Here we have anew theatri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed the Moral Law, which we acknowledge the Apoſtle doth ſtrenuouſly urge, and never oppoſed any one Tittle thereof. But yet he here decries <hi>the Seventh-day-Sabbath,</hi> as very conſiſtent with, and agreeing to all his Zeal for <hi>the Moral Law;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that was never of the Subſtance of it: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it either Holy or Juſt, or Good: (I mean not in, and of it ſelf; as all that is truly and <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Moral</hi> is; but by Gods commanding it: We acknowledge it to be <hi>poſitively</hi> Moral.)</p>
               <p n="8">8. The laſt Anſwer, is from <hi>Math.</hi> 24.20. <hi>Pray you that your Flight be not in the Winter, nor on the Sabbath-day.</hi> Upon which place he lays ſo great a Streſs, as to ſuppoſe it a ſufficient Proof for the Obſervation of the Seventh day, as our bounden Duty. For here he takes for granted, that this Sabbath here ſpoken of, is <hi>the Seventh day;</hi> that the Flight here ſpoken of, is that (at neareſt) of the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the Temple, about Forty Years after Chriſt: And therefore
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97175:58"/>our Saviour knowing what a great Trouble of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit 'twould be to gracious and devout Souls, to be forced to flee for their Lives on that day, whereon they ſhould have been Glorifying their God, and Refreſhing their own Souls in Religious Duties, and Holy Communion with the Father and the Son; He exhorts them to Pray againſt ſuch an Evil, thereby implying (as he would have it) the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of that Sabbath; and his own Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof till then, and ſo forever. Wherein (I think) I have (I am ſure I intended to have) given all the ſtrength of what he hath written from hence, and not concealed or leſſened any whit of it. Unto which I proceed to anſwer that,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Some underſtand this to be <hi>a proverbial kind of Speech,</hi> to expreſs the Difficulty and Irkſomneſs of a thing; that 'twill be as tedious as a Journy in a Cold, Snowy, Dirty Winter; or as a Flight to a ſuperſtitious Jew upon a Sabbath-day. 2. Others apprehend it to be ſpoken to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in this Senſe, Pray that your Flight may not be on the Seventh-day-Sabbath; Becauſe thereby you will greatly offend <hi>the ſuperſtitious Jews,</hi> who will deem you as Profaners of that day hereby, and ſo will be ſo far from Pitying and Relieving you, that they will hate and michief you all they can: As we know the Jews were great Enemies to them, becauſe they were ſo to their Ceremonial Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (as they deemed them) and to their <hi>Sabbaths</hi> too; and hence were ſo far from ſheltring them from, that they betrayed them to, and delivered them up into the Hands of Heatheniſh Perſecutors. 3. It may well be interpreted <hi>ſpecifically</hi> of a Sabbath, and not <hi>numerically</hi> of the Seventh day only: And
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:97175:58"/>ſo 'tis as if our Lord had ſaid, pray that on what ever day your Solemn Reſt for Religious Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Divine Service ſhall be; that on that day your Flight may not be; for 'twill then be very grievous, and more intolerable, than on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny day of the Week: And ſo includes, yea, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily intends <hi>the Firſt day,</hi> the Dominical day. But 4. To be as fair as we can with him, and to grant all that he does deſire, we will ſuppoſe that our Saviour did mean by his words, what they, 'tis moſt probable, did underſtand by them, even <hi>the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day,</hi> to be <hi>that Sabbath</hi> on which they were to deprecate their Flight: Yet this will be alſo far e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from ſo clear a Proof for him as he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines. For we know 'tis uſual in the Holy Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to ſpeak of <hi>Evangelical days,</hi> and of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God in them, under <hi>Legal Metaphors;</hi> to wit, by Sacrifices, by erecting of Altars, by coming up to the Temple, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as all that know the Stile of the Prophets, cannot but be acquainted with; becauſe theſe were then the Services which that People performed, and they knew no other; and probably would not have endured the mentioning of any other. So here, our Saviour ſpeaks indeed literally of the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath,</hi> becauſe the Jews and his Diſciples (who were Jews) knew yet of no other, neither were prepared to hear of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſubſtituting of another day in its place. Yet this does no more confirm <hi>the Seventh day</hi> to be the <hi>future Sabbath,</hi> than thoſe other Scriptural Sayings, do <hi>the Ceremonial Rites</hi> to be the <hi>Evangelical Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> or the external Modes of ſerving God in the times of Reformation, and when the Body and Subſtance of theſe Signs and Figures were exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:97175:59"/>
               <p>Beſides, we ſay our Saviour did very well fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee that many of his Diſciples (as we know the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> and <hi>Coloſſe;</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> with <hi>James</hi> did) would many years after his Deceaſe, dote upon the judaical Ceremonies, and would reverence them out of Conſcience to God, their Author and Impoſer; And ſo alſo on <hi>the judaical day.</hi> And therefore our Lord fore-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending this, bids them to deprecate their Flight on ſuch a day, which their own Conceits and falſe Apphrehenſions of things, would make more grievous and burdenſom to themſelves; not his Injunctions, or the real Obligation of the day. And there is nothing more common than this way of ſpeaking <hi>according to Mens Apprehenſion of things,</hi> without any the leaſt Approbation of that Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion. So we find our Saviour ſpeaking in his Diſcourſes of the Jews <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendably and honourably; yet I hope this did not confirm it for the future. But here it may be objected, But he did not Propheſie of its future Obſervance, or require any thing of them, upon a Suppoſition of its Continuance afterwards; and therefore this is nothing to the purpoſe. But we know he could not but foreſee that they would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, and keep it up in the Churches after his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from them and its Abrogation; and ſo theſe Speeches of his would then be upon Record, and probably made a Plea for its Uſe: (eſpecially ſeeing he never did, as I remember, ſpeak any thing againſt it, or expreſly of its future Extruſion out of the Churches) Which Speeches of his cannot Authorize their future Practice Neither can our Saviours foreſight of their ſuperſtitions and miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:97175:59"/>Obſervance of the Seventh day, and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for their Eaſe-ſake upon that Previſion, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize the Continuance thereof. Therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there are ſo many Solutions given to this Plea, againſt the Apoſtles meaning of the Seventh day; when he condemns them for their Obſervance of Days and Sabbaths; (whereof ſome one may be deemed ſufficient; but much more all together:) It cannot by any impartial, judicious Perſon, be thought of any Prevalency to evade an expreſs Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition of the Apoſtle, of the Obſervance of that day; which we contend his Prohibition of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths to be; <hi>the Seventh being the moſt famous of all Sabbaths:</hi> Being that which is moſtly, if not only intended by that Expreſſion in Scripture, and in that very word, whereby the Holy Ghoſt in the New Teſtament, intends and means the Seventh-day-Sabbath.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVI.</head>
               <p>HE begins <hi>Page</hi> 75. to betake himſelf to <hi>the Command it ſelf,</hi> and would from thence collect <hi>an abſolute Neceſſity of the perpetual Obſervance of the laſt day of the Week;</hi> aſſerting the <hi>Morality</hi> of the whole Command, and endeavouring from ſome Paſſages and Letters of that Law, to ratify his own Opinion herein. Therefore I ſhall take leave with as much Brevity and Plainneſs as I can, to give my weak Thoughts about it; and leave it to the Learned and Judicious to determine. Here we muſt premiſe a Diſtinction or two: 1. Between
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97175:60"/>
                  <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Poſitive;</hi> between that which is <hi>Good, Juſt</hi> and <hi>Holy in it ſelf;</hi> which emerges from the right Conſtitution of the rational Creature, and ſo would be a Duty, if 'twere never externally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by God; And that which has no ſuch <hi>innate Goodneſs,</hi> neither would have been performed as a Duty by Man, were it not impoſed by a ſuperadded Precept. 2. Between that which is <hi>Purely, Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally</hi> and <hi>Abſolutely Moral</hi> in it ſelf, and that which is <hi>Secondarily, Reſpectively</hi> and <hi>Poſitively Moral:</hi> The <hi>former</hi> is that ſpoken of above; the <hi>latter</hi> is that which, though the rational Creature could not of it ſelf have judged a Duty, yet when 'tis once im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by Command, and ſo revealed to be the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlator's Pleaſure, there is diſcerned in the thing it ſelf, a very great Equity, Goodneſs and Suit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs to Gods Glory, or the Creatures Good, or both: As in the caſe of <hi>Tithes,</hi> or the Tenth of every Mans Eſtate to be devoted to Pious Uſes, for the Maintenance of the Worſhip of God, and of thoſe that are by him called thereto, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed therein: Though the Light of Nature could not primarily, and from it ſelf, have diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and devoted <hi>this very preciſe proportion</hi> to the immediate Service of God as abſolutely neceſſary; Yet when God does once require it, it muſt needs cloſe with it, as very reaſonable and juſt, that God, who gives all, and whoſe all is, ſhould have the Tenth part devoted and ſeparated to his own Service: So that the Goodneſs of this, does not only ariſe from the Will of the Legiſlator, but alſo from the Nature of what is required, when 'tis once diſcerned to be the Legiſlator's Pleaſure. So that it is neither <hi>purely poſitive,</hi> nor yet <hi>primari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:97175:60"/>Moral,</hi> diſcovered only by the Promulgation of the Legiſlator; and then embraced at, and acknowledged to be moſt juſt and good by the Creature, from whom 'tis required: Whereas, what is purely poſitive, has nothing juſt or good in it ſelf; nor diſcernable after its Impoſition. 3. In the Fourth Command we muſt diſtinguiſh between; 1. The Duty commanded; 2. the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Duty; and 3. the Arguments and Motives thereto. And ſo, without any more nice Diſtinctions we proceed by God's Aſſiſtance to our Apprehenſions about this Matter.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Duty Commanded, or <hi>the Subſtance of the Fourth Command,</hi> which is in the firſt Words of that Command, <hi>Remember the Sabbath-day,</hi> (or the Day of the Sabbath,) <hi>to keep it holy,</hi> (or to ſanctify it:) Where we acknowledge the Reſt, or <hi>the holy Reſt,</hi> to be <hi>primarily</hi> and <hi>abſolutely Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> which this right Judgment of the rational Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature dictates, directs to, as that which it ows to its <hi>Creatour, Preſerver,</hi> and <hi>Benefactor;</hi> even a ſet and ſolemn Time ſeparated and devoted to the immediate Service, Praiſes and Adoration of God; who, becauſe of his own Infinite and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Excellencies, deſerves all their Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Adoration; and becauſe of their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable and ineſtimable Benefits received from him, merits all their Love and Obſervance: Which Imployment, the rational Creature would acknowledge to be the moſt noble and excellent, the moſt happy and bleſſed that it can be imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, being the Imploying of the moſt noble Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of the Soul, in their moſt excellent Acts, about the moſt raiſed and glorious Object: This,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:97175:61"/>I ſay, the true Light of Nature would direct un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and ſo is <hi>purely moral:</hi> But whether it would have directed to a Separation of a whole intire Day thereto, I cannot reſolve: Though this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo may be moſt probable; being a Time ſo limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, meaſured and diſtinguiſhed, by the antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ſubſequent Darkneſs; or by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, Light and Motion of the Sun in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphere. But here, I believe, we may take for granted, that the rational Creature in its Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, would have actually conſecrated to ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, and imployed in divine Worſhip, all that Time that could have been duly and conveniently ſpared from the Refreſhment of the Body, and thoſe due Preparations, which muſt be made for his decaying outward Man; ſo that <hi>Adam</hi> would have ſubſerviated, (had he ſtood in his Innocence) all his tilling of the Garden, all his eating, drinking and ſleeping; all the Recruits of his Body, to the ſolemn Manner, as that which was the End of his being; the due of his God from him, and the higheſt and moſt bleſſed Imployment of himſelf. <hi>This,</hi> I ſay, <hi>would have been,</hi> had he beenleft to the Dictates of his own Knowledge, which was given him of God, of himſelf, and of his Ingagements to the Author of his being, and well-being; and not been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by a Precept from his Lord and Sovereign. But however, this all muſt acknowledge, that <hi>a Time of Reſt,</hi> (For that's the engliſh of <hi>Sabbath</hi>) to be <hi>ſet apart</hi> and <hi>ſanctified</hi> to the immediate Service of the moſt high and muniſicent <hi>God,</hi> is <hi>purely moral:</hi> And it may be alſo thought, that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:97175:61"/>
                  <hi>an intire Day</hi> may bid fairly for it. And this, I ſay, is the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of this Precept, and really moral.</p>
               <p>But here, before I proceed, I muſt obviate a little Criticiſm, which the Author here ſeems to lay a great Streſs upon; and that is about ה <hi>(hè)</hi> in the Original, which he would fain have to be very <hi>emphatical,</hi> and to ſignifie, <hi>That,</hi> by way of Eminency here in this Verſe, the beginning of the Command, the Words are <hi>Remember the Day of Reſt. (Eth Jom Hasſhabbath.</hi>) I would enquire of him, whether this rendring of theſe Words, be not as proper, as any he can render it by: Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>the Day of Reſt,</hi> be not ſo proper, as <hi>the Day of a Reſt,</hi> or the Day of <hi>that Reſt.</hi> For every one that hath but peeped into the Hebrew Bible, very well knows that that Letter ה, ſerves many times, if not moſt times, only for a Letter and Ornament of writing, without any Signification whatever: And, whether I render it by an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Particle or no, he cannot blame me; if I will, he hath no Reaſon to quarrel me, if I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it <hi>A</hi> or <hi>The;</hi> nor I, much, to quarrel him, though he chuſes to tranſlate it <hi>That.</hi> For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>A,</hi> nor <hi>The,</hi> nor <hi>That,</hi> are found in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal; but are only Engliſh Particles: And, I would fain know what <hi>Emphaſis</hi> the ſame Hebrew Particle hath before [<hi>Shamajim, Aretz,</hi> and <hi>I am</hi>] <hi>Heaven, Earth</hi> and <hi>Sea;</hi> and whether the Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion either without a Particle, or with that which carries no Emphaſis, be not far better than the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation with an Emphatical one: As for Example, <hi>the Lord made Heaven and Earth and Sea,</hi> or the Lord made <hi>the</hi> Heaven, <hi>the</hi> Earth and <hi>the</hi> Sea, are not better than, the Lord made <hi>that</hi> Heaven, <hi>that</hi>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:97175:62"/>Earth and <hi>that</hi> Sea; for if we take this Particle <hi>That,</hi> Emphatically, it ſeems to ſignifie, that there are <hi>more</hi> Heavens (for we ſuppoſe the viſible Heaven or inferiour one, is here meant) and Earths and Seas, than <hi>One;</hi> and that 'tis Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically and Eminently meant of thoſe in the in Command, beyond the others; whereas there is <hi>no other</hi> Heaven, Earth, or Sea, but what is meant in the Command; and therefore would be very impertinently rendred by an Emphatical <hi>That.</hi> From whence I would ask this Gentleman; what reaſon there is why ה before <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and <hi>Shebigni,</hi> ſhould be more Emphatical, than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe other Words in the ſame Command: Sure that Opinion wants ſolid and deep Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, that muſt be upheld by ſuch ſuperfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and weak ones. Thus much for the firſt part of the Command, the Subſtance and unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly moral Part thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We have the <hi>Explication</hi> of that Part of the Command in its following Words. <hi>Six Days ſhalt thou labour and do all thy Work; and the Day, the Seventh, a Sabbath to the Lord thy God;</hi> (<hi>is</hi> or <hi>ſhall be,</hi> or <hi>both</hi>) <hi>a Sabbath to the Lord,</hi> that is dedicted to the Worſhip and Service of Him. <hi>Thou ſhalt do no Work; thou nor thy Son, nor thy Daughter,</hi> &amp;c. Where we have one Day in Seven, or of Seven, declared and ſignified to be <hi>that Day of Reſt,</hi> or Holy Sabbath, which was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnded in the Beginning. And here our Authors contend, and worthily, that <hi>this Seventh Day</hi> in this Peace, is not an <hi>Ordinal</hi> Seventh Day, that is, the next Day after the former Six Days: But rather a <hi>Proportional</hi> (If I may ſo expreſs it) Day,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:97175:62"/>or a diſtributed part of the Seven; that is, that <hi>of Seven days God will have one entire day to be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to him and his Service,</hi> without ſpecifying what day of the Seven it ſhould be. And I am ſure he has no reaſon nor ground from the Command hitherto, to except againſt this underſtanding of the Seventh day. In this Explication of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand we have two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Portion of Time, or the Part of the days that God will have ſanctified to an Holy Reſt; the Seventh. 2. How he will have the Reſt obſerved: By an Abſtinence of all ſorts of Perſons from earthly and worldly Employments, (except ſuch as do not interfere with its due Sanctification) that they may be wholly in Body and Soul buſied in his Service; as is clearly enjoyned in that word in the Subſtance of the Command, <hi>(to Sanctifie it.)</hi> As to this Seventh part of time ſo ſanctified and ſeparated to Divine Service, this is not <hi>Primarily</hi> and <hi>Purely Moral;</hi> though we acknowledge it to be <hi>Secondarily</hi> and <hi>Poſitively</hi> ſo: Not ſuch a meaſure of Time as the Wiſdom of Man in Innocency would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely ſeparated to Divine Worſhip; and not one day more, nor one day leſs, of all the Week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days. I think I have ſhewn before, that the light of Nature would have ſeparated and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated all to the ſolemn Service of God; all the time that it could ſpare from the due Recruits of Nature; Which I doubt not but in an Eſtate of Innocency, would have been a greater Meaſure and part of Time than the <hi>Seventh:</hi> For <hi>now</hi> we find by Experience, that even after the Fall, ſince that the Earth is curſed for our Sins, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:97175:63"/>requires a great deal more Labour and Time to be lain out upon it, for the Production of our neceſſary Suſtinence, than before the Fall: <hi>Now</hi> that our weak, craſie and diſtempered Bodies call for a great deal more Care and Time for their Suſtentation, their Recruits and Reparation, than when they had a perfect Temperature, were compleatly Healthy, Strong and Immortal, in Innocency; and many other Civil, Domeſtick Affairs take up, and muſt have, a great deal of our time, which would have exacted none of it in Innocencency: And yet we experience (I ſay) that ſix in ſeven allotted us for theſe things, are ſufficient enough; and we can very well ſpare a <hi>Seventh day</hi> for the ſolemn Service of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Detriment to our Bodies, or our civil Concerns: Yea, and have many other Seaſons and good Opportunities given us to ſerve God in: And doubtleſs had God ſeen fit to have required the ſixth part of our time; it would have been ſo alſo. Wherefore I conclude, that the ſeventh part of the Week, or one day of the Seven, is not <hi>primarily Moral;</hi> becauſe the light of Nature could not have preciſely dictated it to us: Which methinks I could demonſtrate by this Suppoſition; Suppoſe a Perſon that is againſt the Morality of the Sabbath, that judgeth no day of the week more Holy than another, ſhould by Providence be thrown among <hi>Mahonietans</hi> or <hi>Heathens,</hi> and preaching the Goſpel to them, ſhould be Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental to convert any of them to the Chriſtian Faith: I aſſert, that in ſuch a caſe (and he would certainly be horribly uncharitable that ſhould judge the contrary) if they did keep all the reſt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:97175:63"/>of the Moral Precepts with a ſound Faith in Chriſt they would infallibly be ſaved, though they never ſeparated one day of the week intirely to Gods Worſhip and Service: But now if they did allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly live in any Breaches of the other Commands; (yea ſuppoſing ſome of them ſhould never have been expreſly taught them by their Converter) as if they did not acknowledge the only true God in their Souls; if they did worſhip Idols; if they did Swear Falſly or Vainly; if they were Rebellious and Undutiful to Parents and Magiſtrates; if they lived in Hatred, and were Cruel; if in Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and were Laſcivious; in Theft, and Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenage; or were Oppreſſing, in Lying, Slandering, and Falſe Witneſſing; or in an inward Love and Delight in any of theſe Sins, they ſhould certainly Periſh: And why? But becauſe all the other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are <hi>primarily Moral;</hi> and this of the ſeventh part of time is not ſo: Yea in, keeping the other Commands, they keep the Morality of this alſo; Commands, they muſt ſeparate time to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that Divine Service, which is the prime Morality of the fourth Precept. Thus I think 'tis clear, that the Sanctification of one <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth day</hi> of the week, is not abſolutely and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily Moral; but yet it may alſo be concluded, to be <hi>ſecondarily</hi> and <hi>poſitively</hi> ſo; that is, that upon the Revelation of the Will of the Legiſlator and his Injunction, the rational Creature cloſes with it, as that which is Holy, Juſt and Good; as that which is infinitely reaſonable; for what can be more ſo, than that <hi>is ſeventh part of time</hi> ſhould be devoted to his Service, whoſe <hi>all</hi> our time is;
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:97175:64"/>eſpecially when it is alſo for the Creature's chief good.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We have the <hi>Reaſons</hi> to inculcate its Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: 1. The Legiſlator's own Example, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was <hi>ſix days</hi> in creating the World, and ceaſed from thoſe works <hi>on the Seventh day,</hi> reſted on the Seventh day: and 'tis hence only, in all this Command, that they can have any ſhew or ground to plead for the laſt day, or the Seventh day of the week, to be the Sabbath or Reſt that God did command; which is no way cogent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may be meant a Seventh day, by way of part or portion, and not the Seventh day of order nor in number of the week. And it may be thus underſtood, <hi>Becauſe I was ſix dyas in making the World, and then reſted; ſo ſhall you be ſix days buſie in your common lawful Imployments; and then a Seventh you ſhall conſecrate to me and my Worſhip.</hi> So that in this Senſe it doth not injoyn the laſt day, the Seventh day of the week in order, but a Seventh day in proportion of time: For which we have this to lead, That ſeeing <hi>Gods Example</hi> is made the great Fundamental Argument of the Seven-day-Reſt, it ſhould hence follow, that if <hi>Adam</hi> had exactly followed the Pattern, then the <hi>Sixth day</hi> of the week would bid faireſt for the day of Reſt of all the Seven, becauſe then <hi>Adam</hi> muſt have worked ſix days before his Holy Reſt, as God did; and then being created, as we may ſuppoſe, about the latter end of the ſixth day of the Creation, he muſt have wrought the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing (which is the Seventh) and ſo the five other days following, and reſted upon <hi>the Sixth day as his firſt Sabbath;</hi> for that would have been the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:97175:64"/>day after his ſix days Labour or Work: For 'tis clear, that the Seventh day after the beginning of the Creation, (though it were ſo with reſpect to Gods Works; yet) 'twas the very next day after <hi>Adam</hi> was; and could not but be within a very few hours <hi>(if hours)</hi> after his Creation; ſeeing it begun in the <hi>Evening:</hi> And ſo <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> were ſo far from an exact Imitation of God in the Obſervance of the firſt Sabbath, that in his parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular they were contrary thereto; for God wrought ſix days firſt, and then reſted the Seventh; but <hi>Adam reſted his firſt day,</hi> and then wrought the <hi>ſix days</hi> following: <hi>God's Reſt</hi> was in the <hi>Concluſion</hi> of <hi>his Work;</hi> and <hi>Man's Reſt</hi> was in the <hi>beginning</hi> of <hi>his Work,</hi> in his firſt ſeven days; which I think ſomewhat enervates this ſolitary Plea they have here for the laſt <hi>Week-day-Sabbath.</hi> But yet we will Suppoſe that in this Clauſe, God did there injoyn <hi>the laſt day</hi> of the Creation-week to be the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> but then we ſay this is purely <hi>Poſitive,</hi> and no way <hi>Moral</hi> at all, neither Primarily nor Secondarily; for it is were ſo, the Morality thereof muſt ariſe from the <hi>Reaſon</hi> that is given for it, <hi>viz. Gods Example;</hi> even becauſe he made his work of Creation in ſix days, and reſted on the Seventh: But this is no way cogent, or (rather) <hi>Moral,</hi> not ſuch a thing as the light of Nature would engaged us to: For 1. God is not to be imitated by us in all that he does; neither could the rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conclude upon Gods Revelation of his having ended his work on the Seventh day, that <hi>therefore</hi> he muſt work ſix, and reſt the Seventh, without an expreſs Injunction; which therefore God gave here. 2. If we could ſuppoſe, that ſuch a Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:97175:65"/>of imitating God, could have been appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by Man, without Relevation; then the <hi>Sixth day</hi> of the week, would by him be pitched upon for <hi>his own Sabbath of Reſt;</hi> becauſe the Sixth day of the following week would have been his Seventh day after his Six days working, as before. 3. Gods making of the World, <hi>in ſix days,</hi> was <hi>a pure Revelation;</hi> for Man could never have known it of himſelf; no not in the Eſtate of his pure Knowledge: Becauſe, for ought he could know, God might have made the World ſimultaneouſly, <hi>all at once,</hi> or by one word ſpeaking; for he knew he might ſo have done, if he had pleaſed; he could not know that God did gradually, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſively make the Creatures; much leſs that he took up ſix days for it, neither more nor leſs: Indeed the Order, and Method, the Time and Duration of the work of Creation, muſt be by Revelation to Man, ſeeing he was created the laſt of all the Creatures: So that in this reſpect 'tis not Moral; neither could it ever be the Dictate of Man's Mind. 4. God cannot properly <hi>Reſt,</hi> becauſe he cannot be ſaid properly to <hi>Labour: Reſt</hi> properly is a Refreſhment after Wearineſs, Iſa. 40.28. <hi>The everlaſting God, the Creator of the Ends of the Earth, fainteth not, neither is weary.</hi> Conſequently neither reſteth; for he does all he does with an infinite Facility, and perfect Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; and takes no more pains in creating the World, than in creating a Fly; that is, <hi>none</hi> at all. And beſides, as before, God works ſtill in his works of Preſervation and Providence, which are altogether as Great and Glorious, and ſome of them more Great Glorious, than were the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:97175:65"/>works of <hi>Creation:</hi> So that in this reſpect this Argument is not <hi>Moral;</hi> not ſuch a Motive as could have been found out by the Mind of Man. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> If this were ſuch a cogent Reaſon in it ſelf, or a Moral Motive for the Sanctification of the Seventh day, in the Repetition of the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, why is it not ſo much as mentioned? For <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.13-15. there is not a word concerning it; but whereas in the other Commands all the Motives that were uſed, and adjoyned to them in their firſt Edition, are here again repeated; yet <hi>this is</hi> quite and clean <hi>left out</hi> in this ſecond Edition of the Fourth Command; and in lieu thereof, their mighty and wonderful Deliverance out of the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> is inſerted, that 'twas therefore becauſe he ſaved them, that he commanded them to keep the <hi>Sabbath-day.</hi> What this ſhould ſignifie I cannot well ſee, unleſs God would hereby teach us, that <hi>the Salvation of his Church is a far more great and glorious work in it ſelf, and far more bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial and happy to us, than that of the Creation,</hi> (for the Deliverance of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt</hi> by the hand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> was a Type of the Deliverance of the univerſal Church from the Devil, from Sin, from Hell, from the Curſe, from Death and the Grave; by our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi>) and that when this ſhall be compleated (as we know 'twas at our <hi>Savour's Reſurrection,</hi> it being the Concluſion of his Eſtate of Humiliation by which he purchaſed our Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and an entrance into his Glorification, where he would procure it, apply, and effect it) then the Reaſon annexed to the Fourth Command from the ceaſing the Works of Creation, ſhould (in a ſenſe) be lain by; and that of the Redemption of
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:97175:66"/>the Church be ſubſtituted in its place: And ſo conſequently as the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in Commemoration of the works of <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> until a more admirable work of God ſhould be accompliſhed; ſo <hi>the firſt day</hi> ever after ſhould be the <hi>Holy Reſt;</hi> when that Supream of all the works of God, our <hi>Redemption,</hi> ſhould be reſted from on that day. I do verily believe Gods neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the works of Creation, and ſubſtituting that of the Churches Redemption, as the gread Foundation and Reaſon of keeping the Holy Reſt, here in <hi>Deut.</hi> declares this unto us.</p>
               <p>But I refer it to wiſer Heads: Only from what has been here ſpoken, I will conclude, that this part is purely <hi>Poſitive;</hi> both the <hi>Seventh Week-day-Sabbath,</hi> and this Motive upon which 'tis grounded, God's working ſix days and reſting the Seventh, which is a Motive to us to obſerve it, as well as it ſeems a Reaſon in God to require it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here I would fain demand of this Gentleman, why he ſhould be ſo exceedingly Zealous for the <hi>Perpetuity of the Seventh-day-Sabbath,</hi> when 'tis both a <hi>Ceremonial and Poſitive Precept: Ceremonial,</hi> as it ſignifies Gods own Reſt from his Works paſt; and as it ſignifies our future Reſt in Heaven from all our Labours in this preſent Life: And <hi>purely Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive,</hi> ſeeing all the former Ceremonial and Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Precepts concerning Worſhip, are aboliſhed by the coming of Chriſt: Why ſhould this then ſolitarily be excluded, and ſtand in its Strength and Vigour, when all its other Companions are thrown to the Ground and vaniſh? I know no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but <hi>becauſe this was written by the ſinger of God upon ſtone.</hi> But this altereth not the nature of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:97175:66"/>the Command it ſelf; neither can it from hence plead a greater Privilege; for all the former had God for their Author as well as this, and <hi>God's Mouth</hi> is as <hi>Authoritative</hi> as his <hi>Finger:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may well conclude, that ſeeing there is no reaſon can be given, why the <hi>Seventh-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> ſhould not recede and give place, as well as all other Ceremonial and Poſitive Precepts to our <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> at his coming, and his new, and more glorious Adminiſtrations; that it is, and ought to be, excluded with them, and give place to a more glorious day, in Commemoration of a more glorious work, and Gods reſting from it: Even <hi>the firſt day, our Lords glorious triumphing day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other two reaſons of this Fourth Command follow, which are <hi>Gods Bleſſing the Sabbath day, and Hallowing it.</hi> Where 'tis worthy our Obſervance (though this Author deems it a Triffe) that <hi>'tis the Sabbath day, not the Seventh day of the Week, that is here bleſſed and hallowed:</hi> As if God would hint, that the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> upon what day ſoever (of his own Appointment) ſhould be Bleſſed; even the <hi>firſt</hi> as well as the <hi>Seventh day</hi> of the Week, when in the latter days his Sons glorious Reſt ſhould Authorize that day; and as it ſhould alter all other Ceremonial and poſitive Ordinances of his own Appointment, ſo alſo this <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Poſitive day,</hi> into that other, which with all the other Ordinances and Inſtitutions of the Bleſſed Redeemer, ſhould laſt to the end of the World. From which Diſcourſe concerning the Nature of the <hi>Fourth Command,</hi> all that follows in his third or fourth Pages after, is ſufficiently anſwered, and ſo his next anſwer to another Objection againſt his Opinion, <hi>P.</hi> 82.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:97175:67"/>
               <head>SECT. XVII.</head>
               <p>THUS by God's Help, and (I hope) his Guidance, I have conſidered all his <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> that he urges for his <hi>Sabbatarian Opinion;</hi> and have ſhewen their Invalidity and Weakneſs: And all the Solutions that he brings to diſannul all our Proofs for the <hi>Dominical</hi> Tenet; and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that I have vindicated ours from all his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, and ſhewen how they remain ſolid and ſubſtantial. Other things which follow, being but Appendixes to this Diſcourſe, and not of ſo great Moment, I ſhall but touch upon them. As <hi>Page</hi> 83. about the <hi>Beginning</hi> of the Sabbath. He would have it to begin at <hi>Even;</hi> and we willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grant him, that the Seventh-day-Sabbath did ſo; for it began when God had ended his Works of Creation, which was the Evening before the Sun-riſing of the Seventh Day. But, I judge that now the beſt Time to begin <hi>our Lord's Day</hi> with, is in the <hi>Morning;</hi> becauſe, 1. 'Twas on that Time of the Day, early in the Morning, about Break of day, that our Lord Jeſus reſted from his Work of Redemption: Wherefore, if the foregoing Evening of the Old Teſtament-Sabbath, was its moſt convenient Beginning; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>then</hi> God ended his Work of Creation, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted then: So he Morning-Light of the Firſt Day, is the moſt convenient Time for its Beginning; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>then</hi> God reſted from his much more Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and really (in his Humanity) Laborious Work of our Redemption. 2. Becauſe the Holy
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:97175:67"/>Scripture expreſly begins it thus, placing the Concluſion of the Seventh Day at the beginning of the Morning of the Firſt Day, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.1. <hi>In the End of the Sabbath as it began to dawn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Firſt Day of the Week;</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then that Day began. 3. Becauſe 'tis the moſt <hi>convenient</hi> Time; becauſe <hi>moſt obſervable,</hi> leſs ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Prophanations, upon the account of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes; and ſo to turbulent Spirits, leſs obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but this is not ſo ſubſtantial a Diſpute. Let every Perſon give up and conſecrate the whole Lords-day to the Service of God; I mean, <hi>the whole Artificial Day;</hi> or rather the whole light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Part thereof; and then let him begin ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at Even or Morning; I doubt not, but if it be conſcientiouſly done in the Name of Chriſt, God will accept him. But, there he muſt not ſcandalize others by doing <hi>Common</hi> or <hi>Mechanick</hi> Works upon the following Evening of that Day; which the Generality of Chriſtians, among whom he lives, account as <hi>Sacred.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He ſeems <hi>Page</hi> 84. to imply, that there ſhould be Morning and Evening religious Service every Day in publick: But there is ſcarcely any preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſter can have ſo much Leiſure, beſide his own perſonal and domeſtical Devotions: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide our People will not attend it every day; and then the proper publick Duty of the Sabbath, to be but <hi>once,</hi> and begin about <hi>Noon.</hi> I, for my Part, believe the Times of publick Worſhip on the Lord's-day are moſt conveniently ordered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: Twice, once in the Morning about Nine; and ſo in the Evening about Two. An Interval being for the Refreſhment of the outward Man,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:97175:68"/>and Recruits of the Spirit, for a more vigorous and enlarged ſerving of God in the Evening: Beſide, we know in the Country, 'tis convenient to keep ſome Perſons at home; or one Perſon, when Houſes are ſolitary and lyable to Injury, by thoſe who ſhould know them totally deſtitute of an Inhabitant; and in Country and City, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies that have Children, which muſt be kept at home, either through Weakneſs, or ſuch as would diſturb the Congregation by their Preſence, muſt have ſome one or other to take care of them: Now in ſuch Caſes, one Servant or Perſon, may be at home in the Morning, and another in the Evening; and ſo all partake of the publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip every Lord's-day; which could not ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently be done by one ſingle aſſembling the Congregation: But however to meddle herein, would be very impertinent, and would rather ſavour of a reſtleſs Fancy (to ſay no worſe) than of a peaceable and prudent Spirit.</p>
               <p>The other Pages home to the 90th. I overlook; becauſe in them I find, either ſuch things as do not belong to the Sabbath, nor to this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſy at all: Or if they do, they are ſuch as are written already, (at leaſt the Subſtance) and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVIII.</head>
               <p>HE produces, <hi>Page,</hi> 90. the Argument of <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> from the Apoſtles in the univerſal Church theſe 1600 Years, for the Obſervance of
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:97175:68"/>the <hi>Lord's-day.</hi> Whereto his Anſwer is, that no Tradition can add to, take from, lay aſide, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter any Word of Chriſt, or Duty of Man. But, yet ſuch a perpetualand epidemical Tradition may ſerve for a good ſubſervient Proof for that which is founded upon, and deduced from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; as the caſe is here; for we have proved by many Arguments from Scripture, the Abolition of the Seventh-Day-Sabbath, and the ratification of the Lord's-Day.</p>
               <p>He anſwers to ſuch a general and laſting Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition for the Sanctification of the Lord's-day: That he has already proved that the Seventh Day is the Lord's-day ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10. But I think, I have diſproved that Proof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Page</hi> 91: He himſelf recurs to Tradition, and undertakes to prove that throughout ſeveral Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies there have been Churches, who aſſembled themſelves themſelves for religious Worſhip on the Seventh Day. And, ſo this is ſet as a Bar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and a Counterplea to that <hi>Prime, Primitive</hi> and <hi>univerſal Tradition</hi> for the Lords-day: To which, I anſwer in general: 1. That a few Exceptions againſt a general Rule, do rather confirm than weaken it. 2. Every Antiquity or Tradition will not, cannot, ſerve to prove either Practice or Doctrin to be commendable or ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, nor derogate from what is ſo. For, the Denyal of the Deity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is as ancient as the Apoſtles Days; in which <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthus</hi> was ſuch an Heretick; and the <hi>Ebionites, Photinians</hi> and <hi>Arains</hi> have handed down that damning Doctrin to our <hi>Socinians.</hi> 3. Scarce any Church, ſince the Apoſtles Days, have been with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:97175:69"/>out their Flaws, in Doctrin or Worſhip or both; and we doubt not, but this hath been one of them, if it can be proved to be practiſed. 4. In ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Churches, where they did obſerve the Seventh-day, as a Day of publick Aſſemblies; yet in them <hi>the Lord's-day</hi> was <hi>alſo</hi> kept and obſerved; and that too, as <hi>the chief Day:</hi> For on the <hi>Lord's-day</hi> all, in general, were ingaged to wait upon God's publick Worſhip, not ſo on Saturdays. On the <hi>Lord's-day</hi> all the Ordinances of the Goſpel were adminiſtred, not ſo on Saturdays: And ſo ſtill the <hi>Lords-day</hi> had the <hi>Preheminence</hi> even in thoſe very Churches: Which general Anſwers may be enough to ſtop the Mouths of all his ancient Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: Yet, I will take a little Pains, and imploy a little Time, to inquire into the Particulars; for I think they neither deſerve nor require much of either. As to his <hi>firſt Inſtance,</hi> if all the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be ſuch, I am ſure they are ſtark naught; yea, they are not at all. For, he aſſerts, that in the Apoſtles times <hi>the Seventh Day</hi> was obſerved as the publick Day of divine Worſhip: Here he muſt meau by <hi>Chriſtins,</hi> or elſe he trifles: But he can never find in all the Scripture, that in the Apoſtles Days there was ever one Society of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Seventh Day: Indeed, St. <hi>Paul</hi> did go on that Day into the Aſſemblies of the <hi>Jews,</hi> to preach the Goſpel to many of them, which he could not conveniently do on any other Day: But never did he invite any to keep that Day, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did he aſſemble afterward on that Day; when he was ſeparated from their Synagogues finding them imperſwaſible and obſtinate. But, now we can produce ſeveral <hi>Chriſtian-Aſſemblies</hi> on the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:97175:69"/>Firſt day, the Lords day, after our Saviours Reſurrection, in which our Lord appeared to them: And 'twas then their Cuſtom to Aſſemble, and bring their Publick Alms to the Publick Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; wherefore I cannot but marvel at this bold Aſſertion.</p>
               <p>The Baſis of traditionary Structue, being ſo viſibily ſunk and come to nought, makes me ſuſpect that the erected Stories thereof, will tumble and fall: So that 'tis clear, we have the Apoſtle Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, the Churches Uſe in their days, and their Commands againſt the Seventh day, and for the Lords day, as a ſufficient Demurr to all his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Tradition: Into which I now deſcend, and muſt ſay that I have ſearched the <hi>Magdeburgenſes</hi> for his Quotations, but cannot find them where he quotes them; and therefore believe that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor uſed either another Edition, or another that is various either in the Bulk, or in the Pages. I found in them the <hi>Eliberine Council,</hi> but there he <hi>Twenty Third Canon</hi> hath nothing of <hi>a Faſt</hi> upon <hi>a Sabbath day.</hi> As to the other Authors, I have them not, and know not where to get them, that I might peruſe them; neither is it needful; for the matter of theſe Quotations, makes very little for his Cauſe: For whoever conſiders them, will find, 1. That very many, if not moſt of them, declare the Eſtabliſhment and Separation of <hi>the Dominical day</hi> for Divine Service. 2. That another great part of them, prove the Obſervation or keeping <hi>both</hi> of the Dominical day, and the Sabbath, in very many of the Churches. 3. Theſe tell us that the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was kept as <hi>a Faſt,</hi> by the moſt (if not by all) of the Churches that kept it; and the Lords-day
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:97175:70"/>as a <hi>Feſtival,</hi> which all our Eccleſiaſtical Writers acknowledge as before: And ſo evince that it was not kept with ſo equal Authority as the Lords day. (So does Dr. <hi>Young</hi> at large) which alſo ſhews that they never obſerved it as the ancient Sabbath; or 'twas enjoyned in the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: But upon a new Account, or for a new Reaſon; even becauſe our Lord Chriſt lay dead in the Grave on that day; Therefore <hi>they would Faſt and Humble themſelves, becauſe their Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was on that day in his loweſt Humiliation:</hi> (So far were they from this Gentleman's Opinion, that his State of Death was his <hi>Reſt</hi> after his Work of Redemption) and they would obſerve the Firſt day with Praiſes and Holy Rejoycings, <hi>as the Chriſtian Feſtival;</hi> becauſe 'twas <hi>the Lords day of Triumph over his Enemies,</hi> even of his <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi> Theſe include the greateſt part, by far, of his Hiſtorical Examples, and a very few are left which do not expreſly acknowledge theſe things: And they that do not expreſs them, may well be thought to include them. I mean, though ſome of theſe Quotations do not verbally tell us that when they kept this Sabbath, they alſo kept the Lords day, yet it may well be preſumed they did ſo; ſeeing 'twas the common Practice of ſuch Churches, to obſerve both of them in the foreſaid manner. Such an one, for Example, is that of <hi>Socrates Scholaſticus,</hi> who tells us (for I have exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined him, and find he does <hi>verbatim</hi> tell us) in a manner all the Churches in the World do Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate, and Receive the Holy Myſteries, every Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day after other: Yet the People inhabiting <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> of an old Tradition, do not
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:97175:70"/>uſe it. Yet doubtleſs, they alſo obſerved the <hi>Lords-day,</hi> ſeeing 'twas that which <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> had before by Edict enjoyned the Churches to do. And he ſaith in the very next <hi>Page,</hi> and in the ſame Chapter of this Quotation, that at <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocia,</hi> and at <hi>Cyprus,</hi> the Prieſts and Biſhops do Preach and Expound Holy Scripture at Evening-Prayer, on the Saturdays and Sundays by Candle-Light; and therefore we may well preſume that the other Churches did, which before he ſpake of: Theſe being ſome of theſe all. As for his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Account, when the Lord's day was brought into <hi>Scotland,</hi> viz. <hi>An.</hi> 1208. It may be very well anſwered, that the initiating, or bringing in of the Dominical day, does not refer to the day it ſelf, but only to the Authority that introduced it; even that in that Year it <hi>began</hi> to be Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Authority of a <hi>Council;</hi> which before it had not been: Or if it refer to the day it ſelf, it may not ſimply be underſtood, as if that day were never taken notice of at all in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as a San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified day: (For who ca believe this? ſeeing 'twas all along obſerved by the reſt of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, as his own Quotations acknowledge.) But <hi>reſpectively,</hi> as now 'twas by Authority enjoyned to be ſtrictly kept and ſanctified, and to be ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſeparated to Divine Service: Whereas before, they were Looſe and Profane in their Carriages upon it. All which is moſt probable, and very well concurrs with the truth of the Hiſtory. And therefore this Hiſtory does not, nor that of <hi>Englands</hi> late due Obſervance of the Lords day; or their keeping Markets on that day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> till
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:97175:71"/>the ſame Century, or any other evacuate the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of an Univerſal and Conſtant Tradition for the Lord's day: For even in theſe Nations, the Lords day might be then acknowledged to be the day of Divine Worſhip; though not ſo ſtrictly and duly kept; as we know in this very laſt Century among our Selves, <hi>Plays, Interludes,</hi> all manner of <hi>Sports, ſelling of things in our very Streets,</hi> have been permitted and practiſed. Yet ſtill <hi>the Lords day</hi> acknowledged in the Church to be <hi>the day of Divine Worſhip.</hi> And it cannot well be ſuppoſed that thoſe Chriſtian Churches, (as <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi>) who obſerved the Seventh day, becauſe on it our Saviour lay in the Grave (not becauſe 'twas commanded in the Fourth Precept, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'twas the Creator's Reſt after his Work) ſhould alltogether neglect and diſregard <hi>the Firſt day,</hi> ſeeing 'twas the day of his Conqueſt, and the Entrance into his Glorious Exaltation. This I thought convenient to ſay to thoſe Hiſtorical Collections of his, and muſt leave a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and exact Anſwer of them to thoſe who have better Helps, and more Leiſure to examine them.</p>
               <p>He gives us <hi>Page</hi> 102. <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi>'s Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion concerning the Fourth Command, (whom I ſuppoſe to be the ſame <hi>Thomas</hi> before quoted for the ſame) that ſome part of it is <hi>Moral,</hi> and ſome <hi>Ceremonial,</hi> &amp;c. Which Opinion of his, how he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terodox ſoever the Author deems it, I doubt not, but it is very Orthodox, and the Truth of God clearly evinced by the Light of Nature: And that no Perſon ſhall ever be Condemned for not obſerving a Seventh day of the Week, (much
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:97175:71"/>leſs for not obſerving the Laſt day of the Week) intirely to God's Worſhip and Service, without the Revelation of the Fourth Command to him; no more than he ſhall be Condemned for not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in the Lord Jeſus, without the Revelation of the Goſpel.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIX.</head>
               <p>BUt enough of this before, which invites me to reflect upon one Particular which I intended to have replyed to, in its proper place: But I know not how 'twas then neglected, which is <hi>Page</hi> 79. <hi>An Anſwer to another Objection</hi> againſt the Morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, <hi>viz. That the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue in not at all in force to the Gentiles:</hi> Which Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection methinks, ſhould not be ſo crudely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, nor in ſuch an unlimited and unqualified manner; for I dare to aſſert, That <hi>that One,</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he was, that this Author intends, does hold that the Decalogue in one reſpect <hi>does,</hi> and in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>does not</hi> oblige the Gentiles. That it does oblige them as to the Morality and Subſtance of every one of the Ten Commands, (the Fourth not excepted) That it does not oblige them, as thoſe Ten words were Engraven on Tables of Stone, as they were delivered to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> upon the <hi>Mount,</hi> in ſuch a dreadful and formidable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was the Receiver of them from God's Hand, and their Conveyer to the People: Which to be his Senſe, his very Production of the Preface for his Argument, ſufficiently proves.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:97175:72"/>Which (we doubt not) is a moſt Orthodox O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion; and not only the Judgment of <hi>One,</hi> but of almoſt (if not altogether) all our learned and ſolid Divines. For, how can that oblige the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> which they never heard, nor were in a Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to know? As Millions of them never were; and Millions more may never be: Who never heard of a Deliverance from <hi>Egypt,</hi> nor of a <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor of a burning Mountain, nor of horrible Thundrings and Lightnings, nor of ſuch a Deliverance of that Law? And the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who have, by Gods gracious and bleſſed Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, theſe things brought to their Cognizance, are not obliged to them, as given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but as given by <hi>God;</hi> not to them, as delivered out of the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and out of the Houſe of Bondage, which was peculiar only to the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> and thoſe that came out with them; not to them, as having a ſhare and Poſſeſſion in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> (the Motive to the Fifth Command,) for that was only <hi>peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> So then the Decalogue does not oblige all Man-kind, as 'twas given to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and as urged upon them with their ſingular and peculiar Obligations, but as 'twas engraven upon the Humane Nature in our firſt Creation, <hi>as the moral Perfection of the rational Creature,</hi> ſo it obliges all the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as well as the <hi>Jews.</hi> His Argument of the Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the then whole viſible Church, is a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake; for there were ſome of the viſible Church, who were not among them, as <hi>Jethro, Moſes</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-in-Law; and we believe more with him, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he was a great Man, or <hi>a Priest of Midian,</hi> Exod. 3.1. whoſe Faith in, and Worſhip of the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:97175:72"/>True God are clearly ſeen, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.8, 12. Wherefore this Deliverance of the Jews, could not ſo effect them or appertain to them: But, ſuppoſe that theſe Motives could have a typical and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Influence, and lay ſome kind of moral Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations upon the <hi>Heathens</hi> that may have the Tydings thereof ſent among them, it cannot be well imagined how it could ever affect, or be a Motive to thoſe Nations that never had the leaſt Notice thereof; and conſequently, the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> thus given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> is not in force toward the Gentiles <hi>as ſuch;</hi> for ſo 'twould equally oblige them all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XX.</head>
               <p>AND thus I have paſſed through all his Book that concerns the Sabbath; and have done what God hath enabled me to ſhew the Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Non-Concluſion of all his Arguments, having endeavoured to look into the Depth, and find out the Strength of every one of them: And on the other hand, to confirm and eſtabliſh ours againſt all his Endeavours to undermine and baſſle them. And, might here have concluded; but ſhall not 'till I have ſhewen him the <hi>Tradition</hi> of the <hi>Lords-days-Reſt</hi> down along from the <hi>Apostles</hi> Time, home to the Concluſion of the <hi>Fourth Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tury;</hi> which is the pureſt Antiquity, and enough for our purpoſe, being found in the moſt ancient orthodox Fathers, and ſpoken of as the Practice of the Church of God in their Days, whom I
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:97175:73"/>ſhall but name, and ſet down the Time of their flouriſhing in the Church, referring the Reader to <hi>Dr. Young,</hi> and <hi>Mr. Warren,</hi> to find out their Quotations thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> Co-temporary with the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> in the Year 160.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dioniſius</hi> Bp. of <hi>Corinth</hi> near the ſame time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> Anno. 200. <hi>Origen</hi> 226. <hi>Cyprian</hi> Martyr An. 250. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> An. 326. <hi>Hilary</hi> 355. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> 374. <hi>Hierome</hi> 385. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> 398. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi> in their Time. <hi>Euſebius</hi> (ſaith my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) teſtifies, 'twas obſerved all the World over. And <hi>Bp. Andrews</hi> (as I have read him) in his Speech againſt <hi>Thrask</hi> a Sabbatarian, in the Star-Chamber, avows it on his Credit, that there is not any Eccleſiaſtical Writer, in whom 'tis not found. Viz. <hi>The ſacred Obſervance of the Lord's Day,</hi> that is, <hi>the Firſt Day of the Week.</hi> Which Teſtimonies of <hi>ſo many</hi> excellent Doctors (yea, ſaith <hi>Bp. Andrews</hi> of <hi>all</hi> eminent Doctors) of <hi>ſo many</hi> great and flouriſhing <hi>Churches,</hi> carry much more Weight with them, than all his Collections can pretend to do againſt them.</p>
               <p>As touching <hi>Eaſter</hi> and it's Obſervance, that is no Part of this Controverſy; therefore I ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, that I am no Zelot for it's Obſervance, and am perſwaded it has leſs Grounds for it's Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration than any other of thoſe Feſtivals which are appropriated to our Lord, and in Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Birth, of his Manifeſtation, of his Aſcenſion, of his Miſſion of the Holy Ghoſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>the Lord's Day</hi> is a conſtant Memorial of that Reſurrection, being that Day of the Week where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he reſted from all the Work of his Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:97175:73"/>wherefore, ſeeing there is a <hi>weekly</hi> religious and ſolemn Commemoration thereof, there muſt needs be the leſs Cauſe for an <hi>Annual.</hi> As for the other Feſtivals which are appropriated to meer Men, and dedicated to their Remembrance and Praiſe; as I have nothing to ſay for them, ſo I think it neither prudent nor ſeaſonable to ſay any thing againſt them. But, <hi>let him that keepeth a Day, keep it to the Lord,</hi> and <hi>he that keepeth not a Day, unto the Lord let him not keep it:</hi> And let both main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Unity of the Spirit, in the Bond of Peace.</p>
               <p>Here I hoped to have annexed my Epilogue, but ſome Paſſages in the Diſcourſe of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a little Animadverſion. As when,</p>
               <p>He tells us, <hi>Page</hi> 134. (which he had done ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Times before) that the Change of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Day to the Firſt, was introduced by the <hi>Bp. of Rome,</hi> and ſo impoſed by him upon the other Churches, which he thinks evidenced by his former Collection. But, 1. We have ſeen it ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved <hi>before</hi> there was a Bp. of <hi>Rome,</hi> and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it from the Aſſemblies of the Diſciples and Chriſtians juſt upon our Saviour's Reſurrection, and in the Apoſtles Days. 2. We have ſeen it obſerved by very great Churches in the Purity of the Roman Faith, and the Moderation of the Roman Eccleſiaſtical Government, when either the Roman Biſhop did not pretend to any Authority over them; or if he did, they rightly and ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſiſted and refuſed it: And therefore 'twas ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an univerſal Reception of all the Churches conjunctly, as from the Apoſtles and ſcriptural Authority; than any Impoſition of <hi>Rome</hi> upon them.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:97175:74"/>
               <p>He has a ſtrange Notion, <hi>Page</hi> 130. (as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to me) which is, that firſt <hi>Rome</hi> endeavoured to introduce the Obſervation of the <hi>Paſſover</hi> upon the Lords-day; and ſo the weekly Holy Reſt upon that day; which to my Apprehenſion, implies that <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf obſerved the Paſſover; Lords-day, before ſhe did the weekly. Whereas 'tis clear, that <hi>Rome</hi> obſerved <hi>the firſt day of the week,</hi> becauſe 'twas the <hi>Dominical day,</hi> the day of our Lord's <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> whereas the proper <hi>Paſchal-day</hi> was two or three days before the <hi>Lords day:</hi> And therefore in Honour to that day, did the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> require <hi>Eaſter</hi> to be kept; and not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained <hi>Eaſter Firſt-day,</hi> as a Shooe-horn to bring in the weekly firſt day after. Moreover in thoſe Churches wherein they diſſented from <hi>Rome,</hi> as to the day of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> they concurred with her in the weekly <hi>Lords-day:</hi> So that the <hi>Lords-day</hi> was weekly obſerved by them, before <hi>Eaſter</hi> was kept upon that day; and therefore the yearly <hi>firſt day</hi> could not be an uſherer in of that week-day which was before it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXI.</head>
               <p>AS the Concluſion and Reſult of all this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I think, I have ſhewn, that the <hi>Lord Christ</hi> did not make the World; that <hi>Jehovah</hi> was not <hi>Chriſt</hi> before the World; that he never inſtituted the <hi>Seventh day,</hi> nor reſted on it, till his <hi>Incarnation;</hi> nor being <hi>Chriſt</hi> really till then; that he gave not the Commands on Mount <hi>Sinai:</hi>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:97175:74"/>Neither were they there given to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> but to the <hi>Jews</hi> only, and thoſe mixed People that came out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> That the Ten Commands were confirmed by our <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> in his Sermons and Diſcourſes; but the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> never ſo much as mentioned by him in them all; as that which was no part at all of the Moral Law; but purely poſitive, both in it ſelf, and in its Grounds and Motive upon which 'tis founded, and impoſed upon its Obſervers in the Old Teſtament; and therefore was liable to be changed with the other poſitive and ceremonial Precepts of the Law of God; that our <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> indeed obſerved it in his own Perſon in the Fleſh, becauſe he was made under the antecedent Law of all the Ceremonies and Moſaical Adminiſtration, and obſerved them all as well as the <hi>Sabbath;</hi> but yet he <hi>then</hi> ſpake, and did ſuch things as declared its approach to Diſſolution and its <hi>Non-Morality;</hi> that he reſted no more in the Grave on the <hi>Seventh day,</hi> than he did on the Croſs on the <hi>Sixth,</hi> when he hung dead thereon; but the day of his Reſt from the work of <hi>Redemption,</hi> was the firſt day of the week; which day he ſupreamly honoured above all the days of the week, by his <hi>Reſurrection</hi> thereon from the Dead; by his ſeveral Appearances thereon to his Diſciples after his Death; by his moſt gracious Diſcourſes thereon unto them (which he never did, nor made, on the <hi>Seventh day</hi> after his <hi>Reſarrection</hi>) and by the Miſſion of the Holy Ghoſt upon his Diſciples thereon: Upon which account St. <hi>John</hi> calls it the <hi>Lords day,</hi> and by all the Churches ever ſince, that <hi>Lords day</hi> has been taken to be <hi>the first day of the Week:</hi> That the Apoſtles and Believers
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:97175:75"/>kept the Lords day, or the firſt day of the week as their religious Reſt; and met together on that day as the day of their publick Aſſemblies, and we never read of any Aſſemblies on the <hi>Seventh day,</hi> ſave thoſe of the Jews (our Lords Enemies) in their Synagogues, to whom <hi>Paul</hi> went to preach the Goſpel then and there; but when he expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced their deſperate Obſtinacy; left that time, and thoſe Synagogues, and we never read that ever on that day he joyned with any religious Society; after that at <hi>Troas</hi> he preached and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred the Sacrament to the Believers on the <hi>firſt day,</hi> the <hi>Lords day;</hi> and that the Holy Ghoſt does call the firſt day of the week <hi>the Lords day,</hi> being the day of the Redeemer's Reſt from a far more glorious, laborious, gracious and beneficial, Work, than that of the Creation: And that there is an expreſs Prohibition of the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles; and conſequently, ſeeing the poſitive Morality of one day in Seven in the Fourth Command, is of perpetual Obligation to the Churches; therefore the firſt day muſt be that day, and the Sabbath was excluded, that the Lords day might ſucceed, and that the Promiſes made to the Reſt of one day in Seven in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, are made to, and entail'd upon the <hi>firſt day</hi> of thoſe Seven now, as they were upon the laſt of them, before its Expiration; and that a due Obſervation thereof, ſhall have a gracious Acceptation with, a bountiful Remuneration from our God and our Saviour, according to all the Bleſſed Experiences of the ſtrict and conſciencious Obſervers thereof. That there is a more expreſs and peremptory Abolition of this Sabbath in the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:97175:75"/>Scriptures of that Apoſtle, than there is, or can be found in them for the Ceſſation of many other particular, poſitive and ceremonial Inſtitutions; which yet Chriſtians in general (and this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in particular) diſregard as diſſolved and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed: And I profeſs, if I could ſee but half ſo much in the Second Command, to prove a Form of Prayer to be the <hi>Peſel</hi> there forbidden, or at leaſt included therein, I ſhould utterly deny all Forms as Idolatrous (which now I dare not do; but in ſome caſes hold them not only lawful, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and Praiſe-worthy) or but half ſo much in any Line or Sentence of the New Teſtament againſt the uſe of the Lords Prayer in the publick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; I would never ſo uſe it more, but to my due power would endeavour its Baniſhment thence: If, I ſay, but half ſo much as I find expreſſed for the Seventh days Depoſal; well may we wonder that in ſuch things a Man ſees what ſcarce no Man elſe ever did, in the word of God, and yet in this, that he ſhould not ſee what almoſt every Man elſe can plainly diſcover.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I queſtion not, but all our Divines and Miniſters of Congregations, are ſufficiently ſatisfied, that they ſerve God duly, as to the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of <hi>time</hi> on Lords days; and may, and do, in Faith, aſſociate on the Lords day, as the only Sacred day of the Week, with all other Chriſtians in the Apoſtles days ſince our Saviours Reſurrection, home to this very Generation: And I cannot but hope that this piece, how ſpecious ſoever it be, and with what confidence ſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended; however back'd with the Pretences of Divine Authority, of <hi>Jehovah</hi>'s Will, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:97175:76"/>pathetical Inculcations of thoſe in multitudes of its Pages, for the Obſervance of the <hi>Seventh day</hi> will find but very few, if any, Proſelites among our common Profeſſors; and, I am confident, none among our Wiſe, Stade, experienced Chriſtians; or if any be in danger of Infection, I pray to God that this Reply, intended for this end, may be an <hi>Antidote</hi> to ſecure them. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> it will be good Advice to this Gentleman, who hath cauſed the Expence of ſo much time in this Controverſie, to bethink himſelf how his Opinion leads us to <hi>Judaize;</hi> and this work of his tends only to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Church, to ſtumble the Weak, to imploy and pleaſe the Silly, Fantaſtical and Giddy in matters of Religion, to encourage the Profaners of the firſt day, or rather of the Lords day, to ſcandalize and grieve all, and therefore to ceaſe from farther Attempts of this kind. And all I deſire is, that the Reader would impartially com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare what he has written for his <hi>Seventh day</hi> againſt the <hi>Lords day;</hi> and what I have written for the <hi>Lords day,</hi> againſt his <hi>Seventh day;</hi> and beg Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Underſtanding from God to have a due Inſight into, and draw a right Concluſion from both.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:97175:76"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Samuel Clement</hi> at the <hi>Swan</hi> in <hi>S. Paul's Church- Yard.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>GOD's Revenge againſt Murther and Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, expreſſed in Thirty ſeveral Tragical Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories: Wherein are lively delineated the Various Stratagems, ſubtle Practices and deluding Orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry uſed by our Modern Gallants, in order to the ſeducing young Ladies to their unlawful Pleaſures. To which are annexed the Triumphs of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Chaſtity, in ſome Heroical Examples and Delightful Hiſtories. The whole illnſtrated with about fifty Elegant Epiſtles, relating to Love and Gallantry. By <hi>Thomas Wright.</hi> M. A. of S. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s <hi>Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Compleat Hiſtory of the Late Revolution, from the firſt Riſe of it to this preſent Time; in Three Parts.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh Grammar,</hi> ſetting forth the Grounds of the <hi>Engliſh Tongue;</hi> and particularly its Genius in making Compounds and Deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, with many other Uſeful and curious Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations: Wherein are alſo explained the uſual Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviations, the ſeveral hands uſed in Writing, and Characters in Printing, the Variety of Styles, the Art of true Pointing, and the Way to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand Books: With a Prefatory Diſcourſe
<pb facs="tcp:97175:77"/>about the Original and Excellency of the Engliſh Tongue; and at the end an Alphabetick Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Monoſyllables, being a Treatiſe of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thography for Writers, and of Rhymes for Poets. A Neceſſary Work in general for all ſorts of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons deſirous to underſtand the Ground and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and very proper to prepare Young Men for the <hi>Latin Tongue.</hi> By <hi>Guy Miege,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cereviſiarii Comes:</hi> Or, the New and True Art of Brewing, Illuſtrated by various Examples in making Beer, Ale and other Liquors, ſo that they may be moſt Durable, Brisk and Fragrant; and how they may be ſo ordered, as to yield the greateſt Quantity of Spirits in Diſtillation. To which is added, the right way to refine and bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Beer and Cyder; and a Cure for thoſe that are Sick and Ropy, ſo as to return them to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Sanity; as alſo the true Method of manuring Lands and the Art of making Salt-Water freſh. All proved by Demonſtration and Sound Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, to be more agreeable to Man's Body than otherwiſe, and ſo not only ſit for Engliſh Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, but alſo for Tranſportation. Publiſhed for the fake of Variety, and therefore recommend to all that eſteem demonſtrated Truths before No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Theory. By <hi>W. Y. worth,</hi> Medicin-Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:97175:77"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
